<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="16.04" dur="3.625">What&apos;s going on with the world right now?</text><text start="20.04" dur="1.999">Ok. Ask another question. </text><text start="27.664" dur="1.958">Is the world falling apart?</text><text start="30.497" dur="1.916">Keep going. </text><text start="34.996" dur="2.958">How did we get here? </text><text start="38.371" dur="2.458">....</text><text start="42.37" dur="1.708">Who&apos;s right and who&apos;s wrong?</text><text start="44.078" dur="2.375">....</text><text start="46.453" dur="2.708">What&apos;s real and what&apos;s fake?</text><text start="49.161" dur="1.833">Anything else?</text><text start="54.077" dur="2.333">What should I do?</text><text start="56.41" dur="2.791">These are very good questions.</text><text start="59.201" dur="2.625">It looks like you are playing Game A.</text><text start="61.826" dur="3.749">Would you like to play Game~B?  </text><text start="67.992" dur="2.333">Play Game~B? Yes | No</text><text start="92.4" dur="7.44">[heavy breathing]</text><text start="100.72" dur="9.2">What happened? You have been initiated. 
Huh? Let&apos;s move... we haven&apos;t much time.</text><text start="110.96" dur="6.56">T...time? For what? Until the 
parasite takes hold of you again...</text><text start="123.76" dur="4.08">You&apos;re weak but you now have eyes to see.</text><text start="129.52" dur="8.16">What am I looking at? Where am I? Like most everyone 
you know, you have been hijacked by a parasite.  </text><text start="139.12" dur="6.64">The parasite was born of Game A. The game you&apos;ve 
been playing your whole life. It tells you  </text><text start="145.76" dur="7.28">how to think, feel and what to do. Now that 
you are temporarily free of its influence  </text><text start="153.04" dur="12.08">we&apos;d like to take you on a journey. A journey? To 
where? A journey to Game~B. The journey to Game~B  </text><text start="165.12" dur="6.96">is a story about the relationship between 
humanity, technology and nature. It&apos;s a story  </text><text start="172.08" dur="6.08">not only about survival but the potential 
for thriving. You and your tribe will be  </text><text start="178.16" dur="5.68">among the first people to play Game~B. We 
have traced our steps back to the beginning  </text><text start="184.48" dur="13.68">just before the dawn of human civilization. 
Before Game A, there was the First Game.</text><text start="198.16" dur="4.56">The First Game was our most 
enduring and successful game  </text><text start="202.72" dur="7.36">a game we played for over 100 000 
years. Our nomadic ancestors stood apart  </text><text start="210.08" dur="5.6">from their natural cohabitants in 
their special ability to adapt across  </text><text start="215.68" dur="8.24">all bioregions of the earth. The key to their 
adaptability was culture—a new strategy for group  </text><text start="223.92" dur="8.16">cooperation. These early nomadic cultures operated 
within principles of wholeness and regeneration.  </text><text start="235.28" dur="6.32">The First Game was of course multiplayer. Each 
player is necessary to sustain the principle  </text><text start="241.6" dur="3.76">of wholeness by stewarding 
the cycle of regeneration.  </text><text start="246.0" dur="8.08">All players must be present and respect each 
other&apos;s roles. Roles? I am the sage who seeks truth  </text><text start="254.08" dur="5.52">and ensures its transmission to the coming 
generations. My wisdom is that of the mind.</text><text start="262.48" dur="6.96">I am the chief who seeks to build a 
better world for the coming generations.  </text><text start="269.44" dur="4.32">My wisdom is that of the body and its extensions.  </text><text start="276.56" dur="7.28">I am the matriarch who gives life and purpose to 
the coming generations. My wisdom is that of the  </text><text start="283.84" dur="10.64">heart. Which... role am I? As a Game~B pioneer, 
you must do what is yours to do and bring  </text><text start="294.48" dur="6.48">together all of the necessary roles to sustain 
the principles of wholeness and regeneration.</text><text start="300.96" dur="2.793">Auraaaaaaaaaaaoohh!</text><text start="303.753" dur="2.458">Nuhuh... aaaahhhh!</text><text start="306.24" dur="5.04">The parasite! It&apos;s waking up... we 
have to hurry. You mustn&apos;t allow   </text><text start="311.28" dur="12.56">the creature to take hold. Breathe deeply 
and keep your wisdom centers open. Come.</text><text start="332.16" dur="5.92">Nature&apos;s abundance functions in a 
constant state of regenerative motion.  </text><text start="338.08" dur="7.92">This is wholeness. As stewards, all players in 
the human tribe must move with nature&apos;s cycles  </text><text start="346.0" dur="6.16">as our nomadic ancestors once 
did. Here, take this talisman.  </text><text start="354.88" dur="7.76">In the First Game, cooperation was the rule within 
each tribe. By utilizing the co-creative strategy  </text><text start="362.64" dur="6.56">of culture, each player felt a sense of membership 
and belonging in their tribe. All tribes were  </text><text start="369.2" dur="7.12">indigenous to a specific place on earth—our 
bioregions—like here, along the Cascade Range.  </text><text start="376.96" dur="7.44">Each tribe grew niches around the habitats 
available to it. This is true for all living beings.  </text><text start="384.4" dur="6.88">Shelters, tools, weapons, clothing and medicines— 
all made from resources that were immediately  </text><text start="391.28" dur="5.36">available to them and skillfully constructed 
with knowledge of the local plants and animals.  </text><text start="397.28" dur="5.68">Although neighboring tribes were regarded 
as dangerous, the most resilient of tribes  </text><text start="402.96" dur="5.76">traded goods and knowledge in patterns 
of both cooperation and competition.</text><text start="411.84" dur="5.92">For a long time the number of tribes 
across all bioregions innately respected  </text><text start="417.76" dur="5.52">the principle of wholeness so they stayed 
in a hush but steady balance with nature.  </text><text start="424.16" dur="7.12">But even nature&apos;s bounty has her limits. Over 
time, the First Game became so successful,  </text><text start="431.84" dur="6.48">the number and size of tribes grew large 
forcing us into close proximity with one another.  </text><text start="438.96" dur="7.6">Once we were no longer free to roam, we had no 
choice but to settle in place and competition  </text><text start="446.56" dur="17.28">intensified for nature&apos;s bounty. 
A new game emerged. Game A.</text><text start="466.48" dur="9.76">Where are we now? Or, when? Here we stand before 
the cradle of civilization at the birth of Game  </text><text start="476.24" dur="7.84">A. As competition increased, the tribe began to lose 
its instinctual ability to sustain the principles  </text><text start="484.08" dur="9.28">of wholeness and regeneration. Game A is the game 
of growth, rivalry, control and accumulation. Human  </text><text start="493.36" dur="7.04">settlement meant the accumulation and control 
of resources, knowledge and people. The race to  </text><text start="500.4" dur="6.32">accumulate and control accelerated faster 
and faster and competition began to dominate  </text><text start="506.72" dur="7.52">cooperation. Though necessary to advance the 
human tribe, Game A would prove to be fragile.</text><text start="515.6" dur="4.24">Even the players that depended on each 
other began to compete with one another.  </text><text start="521.12" dur="6.64">The players assumed control and dominion over 
nature&apos;s land and her bounty—and over each other.  </text><text start="528.4" dur="6.32">Before long, culture would be divided into rigid 
class structures and those with the greatest  </text><text start="534.72" dur="8.24">accumulation sat at the top of an exclusive 
hierarchy. What we do to nature, we do to ourselves.  </text><text start="544.16" dur="7.68">The strategy of culture itself underwent diverse 
adaptation as empires competed for more and more  </text><text start="551.84" dur="6.4">accumulation and control—and killed off those 
who couldn&apos;t or wouldn&apos;t play the new game.  </text><text start="559.04" dur="10.08">In our race to master Game A, nature&apos;s stewardship 
was lost. Because Game A&apos;s technology takes from  </text><text start="569.12" dur="7.68">nature without bothering to give back, it is 
fundamentally exploitative. The strategy of  </text><text start="576.8" dur="6.56">rivalry and accumulation led to the exponential 
development of complicated technologies.  </text><text start="584.48" dur="7.44">Since these technologies require extraction from 
the geosphere, eventually they become lethal to  </text><text start="591.92" dur="8.08">the biosphere. As the game continues to advance, 
our global ecosystems are collapsing—all the  </text><text start="600.0" dur="6.96">while our technologies are gaining the potential 
for destruction &amp; depletion on a vast scale.</text><text start="613.04" dur="7.6">Compared to the First Game however, Game A is young— 
and its players are novice. When the principles of  </text><text start="620.64" dur="8.32">wholeness &amp;regeneration are abandoned, there 
is only one fate. Self-termination. Indeed all  </text><text start="628.96" dur="6.0">empires since the beginning of Game A have risen 
only to later be forced into disintegration.  </text><text start="636.16" dur="9.68">The pattern is clear now. We must play a new 
game if we are to survive and thrive. Game~B.</text><text start="647.2" dur="6.88">Does that mean going back to the First 
Game? No. The only way out is through.  </text><text start="655.2" dur="4.96">It is very important that we must 
take what we have learned from Game A  </text><text start="660.16" dur="5.04">then once again move to sustain the 
principles of wholeness and regeneration.  </text><text start="666.32" dur="8.0">The parasite you carry with you is an object of 
control and blind adherence to the rules of Game A.</text><text start="674.88" dur="7.92">It was set upon you in your earliest years. The 
parasite makes sure that you conform to Game A  </text><text start="683.36" dur="6.8">by conditioning you to view yourself as separate 
from nature and from other people—so that you  </text><text start="690.16" dur="8.32">forget the principle of wholeness and your purpose 
as a steward of the earth. The parasite knows only  </text><text start="698.48" dur="6.24">one god. The modern growth-based economy. 
But you can free yourself from its grasp.  </text><text start="705.76" dur="7.92">How? By starting with what you did at the outset 
of this journey. Asking more questions than  </text><text start="713.68" dur="9.04">trying to provide answers will open your mind. By 
first finding what is yours to do then building  </text><text start="722.72" dur="9.28">meaningful relationships with those whom you need 
to work with. This will open your heart. And finally  </text><text start="732.0" dur="7.44">by acting and creating from a place of integrity 
within your tribe. This will train your body to  </text><text start="739.44" dur="7.36">play Game~B. The more you keep these wisdom 
centers open and sustain the principle of  </text><text start="746.8" dur="11.04">wholeness within yourself, your tribe and the world, 
the less the parasite will have influence over you.</text><text start="770.24" dur="11.04">Woah... is this Game~B? The story of Game~B is not yet 
written nor guaranteed—but its potential is real.  </text><text start="781.28" dur="7.04">Now more than ever—the world needs our creativity 
and stewardship to create the conditions for life  </text><text start="788.32" dur="9.12">to thrive. The challenges that face humanity are 
far too complex for one person or tribe to fathom.  </text><text start="798.0" dur="10.16">The crises we see: ecological, political, social 
and educational are interconnected. To face this  </text><text start="808.16" dur="7.52">meta-crisis, we must consciously revitalize 
our tribe&apos;s special ability to adapt quickly  </text><text start="815.68" dur="6.48">with the co-creative strategy of culture—and 
we must do so in a bioregional mesh network  </text><text start="822.16" dur="5.52">across the globe. Restoring this 
co-creative engine to the human tribe  </text><text start="827.68" dur="7.92">will once again allow cooperation to out-compete 
competition—leading to an exodus out of Game A.</text><text start="836.72" dur="5.44">Therefore, by the rules of Game~B, the 
meta-crisis cannot be solved by a single  </text><text start="842.16" dur="7.6">tribe or ideology. The key is to expand our 
inter-tribal cooperation to the global scale  </text><text start="849.76" dur="6.56">and for this we will need open and 
decentralized access to our Game A technologies</text><text start="856.32" dur="7.28">along with a culture rejuvenated by 
wholeness. Nature creates humans, humans  </text><text start="863.6" dur="8.0">create technology and technology must be used to 
support the integrity of nature. Game A&apos;s strategy  </text><text start="871.6" dur="12.24">of driving rivalrous innovation and production 
while continuing extraction must come to an end.  </text><text start="886.32" dur="6.64">At the heart of this co-creative strategy of 
culture is a space to rediscover each other  </text><text start="892.96" dur="7.76">and our relationship with nature. As we learn about 
our role as stewards, we will revive the principles  </text><text start="900.72" dur="10.16">of wholeness and regeneration. Like our own bodies, 
the Game~B tribe must protect the heart. We start  </text><text start="910.88" dur="8.16">by acting locally while thinking globally. Like our 
nomadic ancestors, our economies become bioregional  </text><text start="919.6" dur="7.68">—this time however they are interconnected by a 
global mesh with the assistance of our technology.  </text><text start="927.28" dur="6.96">Tribe selection is the driving force of human 
evolution. What will distinguish us from our  </text><text start="934.24" dur="8.24">nomadic ancestors is our cooperation on all scales 
from the individual player, to the neighborhood,  </text><text start="943.52" dur="10.72">to the village, to the tribe, to the city, 
to the bioregion, to the globe and someday  </text><text start="954.24" dur="8.0">across the galaxy. Like the fungal networks 
beneath our feet, a rich system of channels  </text><text start="962.24" dur="6.24">for cooperation and movement will enable us 
to respond to the global challenges we face.</text><text start="971.12" dur="8.24">The work required to achieve this vision is 
today—incomprehensible. But it is time to play.  </text><text start="980.32" dur="5.6">Every day you must return to the symbol of 
wholeness to loosen the parasite&apos;s grasp.  </text><text start="986.56" dur="7.6">By keeping your wisdom centers open, you can let go 
of your conditioned ways of being. Lead with your  </text><text start="994.16" dur="7.04">strengths and find others who are committed to do 
the same. Make sure that your tribe has strengths  </text><text start="1001.2" dur="8.08">in all three forms of wisdom and that you respect 
each other&apos;s roles. Then, and only then, can you  </text><text start="1009.28" dur="14.56">start to play Game~B. There is a future of thriving 
that awaits us. It would be a shame to miss it.</text><text start="1023.84" dur="2.0">GRRRRRROOOOOOHHHHHUUUUGGHHH...</text><text start="1052.531" dur="11.332">gamebfilm.org</text></transcript>