<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="0.229" dur="1.321">Nate Hagens:
Greetings.</text><text start="1.55" dur="3.38">Welcome to another episode of The Great Simplification.</text><text start="4.93" dur="8.199">Today is part three with my friend and colleague
Daniel Schmachtenberger, the founding director</text><text start="13.129" dur="3.63">of The Consilience Project.</text><text start="16.759" dur="4.77">This one went in a completely different direction
than I expected.</text><text start="21.529" dur="7.941">I was fully energized to have a back and forth
discussion on my systems overview of the world...</text><text start="29.47" dur="8.109">energy, ecology, money, systems... and see
where Daniel agreed, differed, what we could</text><text start="37.579" dur="1.73">converge on.</text><text start="39.309" dur="3.941">Of course, it went in a completely different
direction where we talked about meta-narratives</text><text start="43.25" dur="1.47">themselves.</text><text start="44.72" dur="10.26">Why they&apos;re threatening to various sections
of society, how and why Daniel became a vegetarian,</text><text start="54.98" dur="8.78">how to take in the entire systemic meta-crisis
that humanity faces in a way that gives you</text><text start="63.76" dur="2.29">agency and not despair.</text><text start="66.05" dur="7.81">Whenever I finish one of these podcasts, I
have a pretty good sense of whether I liked</text><text start="73.86" dur="1.0">it, it was good.</text><text start="74.86" dur="2.19">This one was fantastic.</text><text start="77.05" dur="7.77">Though, you will see that my energy at the
beginning kind of faded into speechlessness</text><text start="84.82" dur="5.82">after some of the 15 paragraph thoughts that
Daniel dropped on me.</text><text start="90.64" dur="8.1">So, I hope you enjoy and learn and are inspired
from this conversation with my friend, Daniel,</text><text start="98.74" dur="3.191">which is turning into a longer series than
I originally intended.</text><text start="101.931" dur="5.139">And see you next week.</text><text start="107.07" dur="2.22">Thanks.</text><text start="109.29" dur="8.88">Nate Hagens:
Hello, Daniel.</text><text start="118.17" dur="1.71">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Howdy, Nate.</text><text start="119.88" dur="1.09">Good to see you.</text><text start="120.97" dur="4.78">Nate Hagens:
Good to see you again on our third podcast</text><text start="125.75" dur="1.0">together.</text><text start="126.75" dur="5.98">It was great to see you a couple weeks ago
in person at the conference.</text><text start="132.73" dur="6.55">I don&apos;t know if you have seen, but some people
have uploaded photos of our little presentation</text><text start="139.28" dur="1.0">together.</text><text start="140.28" dur="3.159">I have to say that me sitting next to you
on a chair...</text><text start="143.439" dur="3.891">I kind of look like someone on human growth
hormone next to you.</text><text start="147.33" dur="1.62">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
You&apos;re a big dude.</text><text start="148.95" dur="2.19">Nate Hagens:
That&apos;s why I like the podcast thing.</text><text start="151.14" dur="4.16">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
That was a good conversation we got to have</text><text start="155.3" dur="1.0">there.</text><text start="156.3" dur="1.019">I was happy it happened.</text><text start="157.319" dur="1.5">Nate Hagens:
Yeah.</text><text start="158.819" dur="1.431">We have to do more of those.</text><text start="160.25" dur="5.58">And that&apos;s kind of the purpose of this series
is to expand on the meta-narrative.</text><text start="165.83" dur="7.1">Not only what is it, but how it can influence
more human minds individually and collectively</text><text start="172.93" dur="3.01">towards important outcomes.</text><text start="175.94" dur="2.219">So, here&apos;s what I have in mind.</text><text start="178.159" dur="4.91">This is our third podcast in this series.</text><text start="183.069" dur="7.291">What I would like to propose is I will do
kind of an elevator pitch of my view of the</text><text start="190.36" dur="3.049">human predicament, which we discussed in the
first two episodes.</text><text start="193.409" dur="8.94">Then, I&apos;m going to hand the mic to you and
you can give your grand arc of the meta-narrative</text><text start="202.349" dur="10.17">of the meta-crisis, as you&apos;re kind of known
for, and interject how that rhymes or overlaps</text><text start="212.519" dur="2.58">with mine.</text><text start="215.099" dur="5.051">Where you might state things a little bit
differently but saying similar things, and</text><text start="220.15" dur="2.209">then also where we might differ.</text><text start="222.359" dur="4.6">And we&apos;ll expand on that.</text><text start="226.959" dur="2.431">I don&apos;t know what&apos;s going to come out of that.</text><text start="229.39" dur="2.51">I&apos;m genuinely curious.</text><text start="231.9" dur="4.419">Hopefully, like the last two episodes, we
will... and not only our episodes, but all</text><text start="236.319" dur="7.321">of our conversations and dozens of Voxers...
we&apos;ll learn from each other in real time,</text><text start="243.64" dur="1.56">which is something I greatly value.</text><text start="245.2" dur="2.77">Nate Hagens:
And then, building on that, Daniel, I would</text><text start="247.97" dur="7.69">like to talk about how not only yours and
my stories, but others in our network, when</text><text start="255.66" dur="5.79">we meet each other and we&apos;re working on different
things, we are constraining each other&apos;s expertise</text><text start="261.45" dur="1.64">and stories.</text><text start="263.09" dur="2.46">I would like your opinion on that.</text><text start="265.55" dur="5.3">Then, we could maybe discuss the importance
of these grand narratives.</text><text start="270.85" dur="6.03">Not only why they&apos;re important, but why they&apos;re
socially constrained and threatening to some</text><text start="276.88" dur="2.01">people.</text><text start="278.89" dur="5.15">We experienced that at that conference and
at other conferences as well.</text><text start="284.04" dur="6.99">And then, finally, I would like to queue up
the fourth episode in this series on what</text><text start="291.03" dur="8.45">is the criteria for civilization and how can
we think about this in a way that is productive</text><text start="299.48" dur="2.03">to our future?</text><text start="301.51" dur="1.73">So, that&apos;s what I have in mind.</text><text start="303.24" dur="2.35">Do you have anything to add or suggest?</text><text start="305.59" dur="7.261">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
It sounds like you&apos;re going to do a brief</text><text start="312.851" dur="4.349">recap of what we did in the first two and
where we&apos;re going to go in the next one, so</text><text start="317.2" dur="2.15">there&apos;s some continuity in the arc.</text><text start="319.35" dur="7.05">I&apos;m really happy about what we&apos;re getting
to explore across these four episodes together.</text><text start="326.4" dur="2.61">Nate Hagens:
Cool.</text><text start="329.01" dur="1.0">Okay.</text><text start="330.01" dur="9.69">So, the first episode, you interviewed me
about energy and our economy and the big system.</text><text start="339.7" dur="4.95">The second episode, we were trying to get
to what we&apos;re going to discuss today, which</text><text start="344.65" dur="8.93">is your meta-narrative, paper clip maximizer,
things like that.</text><text start="353.58" dur="9.93">I&apos;ll briefly recap my component of the first
two, which is that humans are a social species</text><text start="363.51" dur="7.89">that has arrived here in 2022 as a self-organized
economic system.</text><text start="371.4" dur="8.13">That, as individuals, as small businesses,
as corporations, as nation states, we are</text><text start="379.53" dur="8.18">optimizing financial surplus that&apos;s tethered
to energy, which is highly tethered to fossil</text><text start="387.71" dur="5.04">energy, which we&apos;re drawing down 10 million
times faster than it was sequestered.</text><text start="392.75" dur="5.15">And there&apos;s waste that is not included in
our economic prices.</text><text start="397.9" dur="6.4">And so when you talk about climate change
or overpopulation or some of these issues,</text><text start="404.3" dur="1.35">those are all downstream.</text><text start="405.65" dur="4.03">Those are symptoms of the core problem.</text><text start="409.68" dur="7.88">The core issue is a biological-social species
finding a bolus of fossil sunlight that has</text><text start="417.56" dur="7.86">boosted our goods and services and economic
output for a brief time in history.</text><text start="425.42" dur="1.39">And embedded in there...</text><text start="426.81" dur="7.11">I expect we&apos;ll get into this... is everything
in our economic system requires energy, materials,</text><text start="433.92" dur="1.8">and technology.</text><text start="435.72" dur="7.43">And so how those three things combine to create
productivity and wealth has been the driver</text><text start="443.15" dur="1.26">of our system.</text><text start="444.41" dur="5.22">Nate Hagens:
My view is we have two possible pathways forward.</text><text start="449.63" dur="4.59">Actually, only one, but they will converge
at some point.</text><text start="454.22" dur="8.09">The first pathway is that we continue to innovate
and either develop new technology or new access</text><text start="462.31" dur="2.91">to energy and resources.</text><text start="465.22" dur="8.81">We continue to grow the size of the human
economy globally and we grow it enough that</text><text start="474.03" dur="10.57">we&apos;re able to service and maintain the prior
financial claims and we thus kick the can.</text><text start="484.6" dur="3.96">That would be good for the human economy.</text><text start="488.56" dur="2.98">Probably would be bad for the natural world.</text><text start="491.54" dur="6.86">The second path is the one that I think is
becoming more imminent, which is that our</text><text start="498.4" dur="9.04">technology, our central banks, our innovation,
are not enough to overcome the depletion of</text><text start="507.44" dur="4.2">the high quality, low entropy energy and materials.</text><text start="511.64" dur="9.739">And, therefore, we have a date that our financial
claims on reality end up re-tethering to our</text><text start="521.379" dur="3.201">actual physical reality.</text><text start="524.58" dur="9.21">That is what my work is focused on is how
to have humans, individuals and groups and</text><text start="533.79" dur="4.13">governments, meet that future halfway.</text><text start="537.92" dur="6.64">And so that&apos;s kind of my ecological, energy
material, human behavior, anthropological</text><text start="544.56" dur="6.139">view of the human predicament.</text><text start="550.699" dur="1.74">Handing the mic to you.</text><text start="552.439" dur="2.231">How does this match?</text><text start="554.67" dur="3.039">How would you say things differently?</text><text start="557.709" dur="3.901">Where do you disagree?</text><text start="561.61" dur="2.57">Lay it on me.</text><text start="564.18" dur="4.7">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I hope that people are watching this after</text><text start="568.88" dur="4.119">having watched the previous ones in the series
and that you&apos;ll put the links to those in</text><text start="572.999" dur="1.721">the show notes here.</text><text start="574.72" dur="4.29">And if not, maybe pause this one and go back.</text><text start="579.01" dur="5.04">Those other ones will be a better starting
use of time because I want to reference concepts</text><text start="584.05" dur="4.7">that we constructed in there.</text><text start="588.75" dur="6.19">Because the story the way you just retold
it actually only makes deep sense if somebody</text><text start="594.94" dur="6.319">has what we discussed in the first episode,
really understanding Jevons paradox and why</text><text start="601.259" dur="5.76">the traditional idea of how we innovate our
way out with efficiencies doesn&apos;t solve the</text><text start="607.019" dur="1.641">issue.</text><text start="608.66" dur="1.63">I&apos;ll assume those concepts are familiar.</text><text start="610.29" dur="2.77">Nate Hagens:
I&apos;ll just pause you right there.</text><text start="613.06" dur="2.879">That&apos;s part of the challenge of our work,
isn&apos;t it?</text><text start="615.939" dur="5.37">Because there is never a one hour thing that
we could just say, &quot;Here it is.&quot;</text><text start="621.309" dur="2.051">These things are all nuanced.</text><text start="623.36" dur="2.279">And the human brain doesn&apos;t like nuance.</text><text start="625.639" dur="3.341">The human brain generally likes certainty.</text><text start="628.98" dur="5.709">This story that we&apos;re telling is not only
nuanced but complex and it takes a long time</text><text start="634.689" dur="1.911">to unpack.</text><text start="636.6" dur="1.51">That&apos;s why we&apos;re doing four of these.</text><text start="638.11" dur="5.01">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I think evolutionary psych is a very riddled</text><text start="643.12" dur="1.0">field.</text><text start="644.12" dur="5.079">It&apos;s very interesting, but very riddled because
we study humans who&apos;ve been ubiquitously conditioned,</text><text start="649.199" dur="6.05">mostly in the kind of weird model, and then
we take that to be human nature.</text><text start="655.249" dur="5.731">And then we try to describe why we are biologically
oriented to be that way.</text><text start="660.98" dur="4.149">It&apos;s easy with reductionism to say, &quot;See,
here&apos;s this gene that correlates or something,&quot;</text><text start="665.129" dur="5.08">but this is why I like looking at different
cultures, where there&apos;s a difference in the</text><text start="670.209" dur="5.18">median of an important quality, difference
in the distribution, across the whole culture.</text><text start="675.389" dur="1.961">Because it shows it&apos;s not just an outlier
person.</text><text start="677.35" dur="1.94">It&apos;s actually a different development.</text><text start="679.29" dur="3.419">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I think we might have even talked about this</text><text start="682.709" dur="1.0">before.</text><text start="683.709" dur="4.211">You have cultures that were radically more
violent and radically more peaceful over fairly</text><text start="687.92" dur="5.07">long periods of time in large populations
and also ones that had much higher value on</text><text start="692.99" dur="2.38">the quality of education ubiquitously.</text><text start="695.37" dur="7.079">The Jewish culture is a very interesting example
because even in it, the embedding environments,</text><text start="702.449" dur="6.06">the education level and the pogroms, low economic
status, low access to public education, whatever,</text><text start="708.509" dur="5.12">was still very high relative to the embedding
environment, in which case things like the</text><text start="713.629" dur="2.06">capacity for...</text><text start="715.689" dur="4.87">The value system on attention and nuance and
whatever can be developed.</text><text start="720.559" dur="3.65">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Fortunately, I don&apos;t hold that human nature</text><text start="724.209" dur="5.701">is inexorable part of our problems, but a
lot of human conditioning to develop the capacities</text><text start="729.91" dur="4.969">that nature makes possible, but not a given
is an important part of it.</text><text start="734.879" dur="4.091">And I will say that it is true culturally...</text><text start="738.97" dur="5.989">I just watched one of those dreadful things
last night where the interviewer goes around</text><text start="744.959" dur="7.341">and asks average American citizens, or what&apos;s
supposed to represent average American citizens,</text><text start="752.3" dur="4.329">which state Utah is in and they have no idea...
and they think Africa&apos;s a country... to kind</text><text start="756.629" dur="2.15">of indicate how dumb the population is.</text><text start="758.779" dur="4.261">Obviously, they&apos;re taking outlier dumb cases
and presenting them... or uneducated cases</text><text start="763.04" dur="2.43">and presenting them as more median than they
are.</text><text start="765.47" dur="8.14">But I think it&apos;s important to understand that
the things that we&apos;re going to suggest, especially</text><text start="773.61" dur="5.9">in the next episode, are deeply informed by
thoughts on human nature and the capacity</text><text start="779.51" dur="3.71">for it to be able to meet requisites with
different conditioning environments.</text><text start="783.22" dur="1.789">Nate Hagens:
Agreed.</text><text start="785.009" dur="3.12">My point... Perhaps nuance was the wrong word.</text><text start="788.129" dur="7.7">My point is that, in today&apos;s internet age,
things that are short and concise and things</text><text start="795.829" dur="4.01">that are certain, an absolute...</text><text start="799.839" dur="4.72">Climate change is going to kill us all or
climate change is a hoax.</text><text start="804.559" dur="5.901">Those things get more views, more attention
seconds to use your language, than something</text><text start="810.46" dur="5.46">that&apos;s, well, it could be this and it depends
on this and those nuanced assertions.</text><text start="815.92" dur="2.949">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So, this is interesting.</text><text start="818.869" dur="1.14">I think this is...</text><text start="820.009" dur="5.211">Obviously, that&apos;s something about the way
the brain, the neurophysiology and psyche</text><text start="825.22" dur="4.619">together, are being conditioned by tech and
culture and the economy together.</text><text start="829.839" dur="6.37">And obviously, we&apos;re looking very specifically
at things like the way that Facebook and platforms</text><text start="836.209" dur="5.66">like that, trying to optimize time on site
and engagement, identify that the stickiest</text><text start="841.869" dur="4.83">things keep people from bouncing and those
happen to be the limbically hijacking things,</text><text start="846.699" dur="5.781">so use literally personalized AI-level technology
to double down on the worst traits in humans</text><text start="852.48" dur="6.64">at a multi-billion person, kind of trillion
dollar scale.</text><text start="859.12" dur="1.75">That&apos;s not our inexorable nature.</text><text start="860.87" dur="3.05">That&apos;s our nature being conditioned for a
specific purpose.</text><text start="863.92" dur="3.37">But it is something we have to overcome and
that we have to work with here.</text><text start="867.29" dur="7.169">I think this goes to the topic you were asking
of...</text><text start="874.459" dur="3.86">Thinking about grand narratives just in general,
being able to think about the whole well enough</text><text start="878.319" dur="4.64">that we can think about solutions even to
parts that don&apos;t mess up other things, the</text><text start="882.959" dur="6.3">minimum required complexity of just reality
as such that we do have to recondition ourself</text><text start="889.259" dur="7.531">to be able to seek instantaneous certainty
and in instantaneous solutions less and be</text><text start="896.79" dur="4.149">able to take the time to go deep enough in
the thing that you really get the insights</text><text start="900.939" dur="2.64">of what the many different causes are and
not a singular cause.</text><text start="903.579" dur="1.25">And what solutions-</text><text start="904.829" dur="2.181">Nate Hagens:
Is that a skill like meditation?</text><text start="907.01" dur="3.24">How does someone develop that?</text><text start="910.25" dur="9.91">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
When we&apos;re talking about the social media</text><text start="920.16" dur="4.5">thing, and obviously this is not only social
media, there are different kinds of reward</text><text start="924.66" dur="1.0">circuits.</text><text start="925.66" dur="3.339">This is also why it&apos;s interesting to think
about it in terms of brain and evolutionary</text><text start="928.999" dur="2.571">biology versus conditioning.</text><text start="931.57" dur="5.819">There are one-marshmallow reward circuits
and there are two-marshmallow reward circuits.</text><text start="937.389" dur="4.531">I&apos;ll assume people know the two-marshmallow
experiment.</text><text start="941.92" dur="7.07">The one-marshmallow reward circuits, when
you have an economy that makes a lot of those</text><text start="948.99" dur="3.899">available... which evolution didn&apos;t make a
lot of one-marshmallow reward circuits available.</text><text start="952.889" dur="4.26">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Typically, you had to actually perform evolutionarily</text><text start="957.149" dur="3.25">relevant work to get rewards of various kinds.</text><text start="960.399" dur="5.37">One of the things that we&apos;ve been able to
do and that, specifically, economics has incentivized</text><text start="965.769" dur="6.35">is being able to take the thing that there&apos;s
an evolutionary reward attached to and strip</text><text start="972.119" dur="4.211">it from the work that you would have to do
to get it to make something that sells better.</text><text start="976.33" dur="1.5">That&apos;s what the supply side is.</text><text start="977.83" dur="5.48">The supply side is incentivized to drive demand,
right?</text><text start="983.31" dur="2.529">We&apos;ve talked about this before.</text><text start="985.839" dur="1.68">What fast food is to food.</text><text start="987.519" dur="4.471">I didn&apos;t have to hunt or gather or whatever
and I just get a concentration of salt, fat,</text><text start="991.99" dur="4.699">and sugar with maximum palatability stripped
of fiber and micronutrients.</text><text start="996.689" dur="6.291">It hits all of the dopaminergic reward centers,
but neither has transcendent nor did it actually</text><text start="1002.98" dur="4.349">require any evolutionary activity of my body.</text><text start="1007.329" dur="3.7">That&apos;s pretty much the same thing that porn
is to actual sex, which involves intimacy</text><text start="1011.029" dur="3.521">and relationship and lots of things like that.</text><text start="1014.55" dur="1.289">And it&apos;s the same thing-</text><text start="1015.839" dur="1.961">Nate Hagens:
So, we&apos;re getting the payoffs without the</text><text start="1017.8" dur="2.099">work in our culture.</text><text start="1019.899" dur="4.17">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Without the work and without the actual, even</text><text start="1024.069" dur="1.75">deeper, nutrients.</text><text start="1025.819" dur="1.561">Without the deeper fulfillers.</text><text start="1027.38" dur="5.36">If I&apos;m hungry and I crave McDonald&apos;s, there&apos;s
this fascinating thing where people who die</text><text start="1032.74" dur="5.14">of diseases of obesity are actually also dying
of certain types of micronutrient starvation.</text><text start="1037.88" dur="5.059">Because every time they eat more stuff and
they get filled with calories and micronutrients,</text><text start="1042.939" dur="2.281">they&apos;re actually not getting trace minerals.</text><text start="1045.22" dur="3.229">They&apos;re not getting phytonutrients.</text><text start="1048.449" dur="1.701">And so then the hunger is even deeper.</text><text start="1050.15" dur="1.8">It&apos;s not a real satisfier.</text><text start="1051.95" dur="1.92">It&apos;s a pseudosatisfier.</text><text start="1053.87" dur="3.74">Not only are they not doing the work, they&apos;re
also not getting the deeper thing that...</text><text start="1057.61" dur="4.949">The salt/fat/sugar was evolutionarily bound
to the other micronutrients that were needed.</text><text start="1062.559" dur="4.861">And the same thing in terms of people don&apos;t
get a sense of deep intimacy and connection</text><text start="1067.42" dur="5.52">and the meaningfulness of life from porn that
they would from an actual intimate relationship.</text><text start="1072.94" dur="3.97">They don&apos;t get it from social media that they
would from real friendships.</text><text start="1076.91" dur="4.78">The real friendships mean I can&apos;t just be
an asshole and then bail.</text><text start="1081.69" dur="3.2">I actually have to work through all the human
conflict, which means I have to look at how</text><text start="1084.89" dur="3.33">I contributed to it, which means I have to
become a better person, but it&apos;s hard.</text><text start="1088.22" dur="3.63">Nate Hagens:
Bringing it back to the original question...</text><text start="1091.85" dur="5.241">In ancestral times, we would&apos;ve been sitting
around a campfire, hashing out the complex</text><text start="1097.091" dur="8.489">problem that we faced and so our brain power
wasn&apos;t a limiter there, but what&apos;s happening</text><text start="1105.58" dur="1.339">now is two things.</text><text start="1106.919" dur="7.38">Number one, the situation is unbelievably
complex, and it can only be understood in</text><text start="1114.299" dur="2.1">an individual mind.</text><text start="1116.399" dur="4.53">You can&apos;t get a climate expert, an energy
expert, an AI expert, and a psychologist in</text><text start="1120.929" dur="7.59">a room and each of them opine on their part
of the meta-crisis and then assume that everyone</text><text start="1128.519" dur="1.65">understands everything.</text><text start="1130.169" dur="6.881">It has to be assembled in an individual mind
and then, hopefully, you&apos;ll grow the number</text><text start="1137.05" dur="1.27">of those minds.</text><text start="1138.32" dur="2.37">But first of all, it&apos;s complex.</text><text start="1140.69" dur="6.66">And second of all, we&apos;re being bombarded by
Facebook and other things competing for things</text><text start="1147.35" dur="2.39">that are not relevant to our future.</text><text start="1149.74" dur="7.559">That are not giving us a full, healthy experience,
both calorically and mentally and otherwise.</text><text start="1157.299" dur="3.321">Nate Hagens:
So, that&apos;s kind of what I meant, buzz.</text><text start="1160.62" dur="5.83">I&apos;ve been doing this longer than you have,
for 20 years, and finally, the real world...</text><text start="1166.45" dur="3.87">I mean, for better or worse, the real world
is catching up to this story.</text><text start="1170.32" dur="5.31">More people are trying to understand it because
they recognize something is quite wrong with</text><text start="1175.63" dur="2.73">our current cultural stories.</text><text start="1178.36" dur="6.189">It took these things happening in real time
for that awareness.</text><text start="1184.549" dur="1.451">But I&apos;m just observing that.</text><text start="1186.0" dur="7.19">I know that these things are difficult to
be simplified and said clearly in a short</text><text start="1193.19" dur="1.0">bit of time.</text><text start="1194.19" dur="5.21">Here, I&apos;ve already spent our first 18 minutes
on a sidetrack.</text><text start="1199.4" dur="1.84">But keep going, my friend.</text><text start="1201.24" dur="3.09">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
There&apos;s actually something that you said about</text><text start="1204.33" dur="4.05">the must be processed in a single human mind
that&apos;s important and I want to come back to.</text><text start="1208.38" dur="6.72">But just to make sense of the detour and why
I was mentioning the thing in food and online</text><text start="1215.1" dur="1.86">relationships and all those areas...</text><text start="1216.96" dur="4.44">There&apos;s a hyper-normal stimulus that is separated
from the rest of what made it evolutionarily</text><text start="1221.4" dur="3.05">relevant.</text><text start="1224.45" dur="3.55">That&apos;s the one-marshmallow reward circuit
rather than the two-marshmallow reward circuit</text><text start="1228.0" dur="9.799">that involves some self-application for some
kind of delayed and healthier gratification.</text><text start="1237.799" dur="4.903">That obviously is also the case with the kind
of reward circuits associated with sense-making</text><text start="1242.702" dur="1.0">and understanding.</text><text start="1243.702" dur="4.018">The one-marshmallow reward circuits are to
get certainty very quickly without the work</text><text start="1247.72" dur="3.069">of actually trying to study and understand
the situation and just-</text><text start="1250.789" dur="1.0">Nate Hagens:
Ah.</text><text start="1251.789" dur="4.73">So, that certainty is a one-marshmallow.</text><text start="1256.519" dur="1.0">That makes sense.</text><text start="1257.519" dur="1.991">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And so I know what in-group I&apos;m a part of</text><text start="1259.51" dur="5.6">because we&apos;re all outraged at the terrible
Trumpers or the dumb libtards, whatever it</text><text start="1265.11" dur="1.0">is, on the other side.</text><text start="1266.11" dur="2.699">I know what in-group I&apos;m a part of and I feel
safe because there&apos;s lots of us and we&apos;re</text><text start="1268.809" dur="4.171">really certain and we&apos;re really sanctimonious.</text><text start="1272.98" dur="1.96">And I get that feeling of...</text><text start="1274.94" dur="7.359">There&apos;s a false sense of identity and esteem
and kind of the Maslow&apos;s need sense, which</text><text start="1282.299" dur="1.0">is sanctimony.</text><text start="1283.299" dur="4.991">I get to feel esteem because I feel so obviously
smarter than the dumb ones who think the other</text><text start="1288.29" dur="2.34">wrong thing.</text><text start="1290.63" dur="6.0">I also get to feel the security that is associated
with feeling certain even though it&apos;s a false</text><text start="1296.63" dur="1.0">certainty.</text><text start="1297.63" dur="1.96">And so I would say those are...</text><text start="1299.59" dur="6.7">The need for belonging and the need for security
and the need for esteem are all getting hijacked.</text><text start="1306.29" dur="6.05">Getting turned into political warfare in a
way that is useful for political parties and</text><text start="1312.34" dur="3.11">people who want to sell their wares and whatever
else it is.</text><text start="1315.45" dur="5.449">But those are all the one-marshmallow reward
circuits of like, wait, did I actually read</text><text start="1320.899" dur="4.931">all of the literature on climate change in-depth
or on vaccines or on whatever it is and really</text><text start="1325.83" dur="5.13">come to sense about this on my own or did
I get a sense of certainty really prematurely</text><text start="1330.96" dur="2.339">and really kind of handed to me?</text><text start="1333.299" dur="2.991">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Similarly, when you&apos;re saying what are the</text><text start="1336.29" dur="3.019">skills underneath it, I think the skill of...</text><text start="1339.309" dur="7.261">The quality of earnestness in our desire to
understand the reality we live in and the</text><text start="1346.57" dur="5.339">earnestness associated with a pure desire
for clear understanding as well as a desire</text><text start="1351.909" dur="1.201">to be effective.</text><text start="1353.11" dur="4.429">And the recognition that, if my map is wrong,
I&apos;m not going to navigate well, especially</text><text start="1357.539" dur="3.171">if I am falsely certain.</text><text start="1360.71" dur="4.25">And then the willingness to sit in uncertainty
for a lot longer.</text><text start="1364.96" dur="4.069">The willingness to not be part of an in-group
that is certain.</text><text start="1369.029" dur="5.38">The willingness to let go of the moral righteous
superiority and to sit in the uncertainty</text><text start="1374.409" dur="4.801">of that so that I can, without bias, actually
come to make progressively better sense of</text><text start="1379.21" dur="1.0">the world.</text><text start="1380.21" dur="2.949">And then to still never get certain because
there&apos;s always more stuff that I don&apos;t even</text><text start="1383.159" dur="1.61">know that I don&apos;t know that&apos;s going to continue
to-</text><text start="1384.769" dur="1.801">Nate Hagens:
But isn&apos;t that a really high bar?</text><text start="1386.57" dur="5.81">To reject certainty and sit with uncertainty
and sit outside of your in-group?</text><text start="1392.38" dur="2.789">Isn&apos;t that a rare human that can do that?</text><text start="1395.169" dur="5.641">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Statistically rare in the current environment?</text><text start="1400.81" dur="1.06">Yes.</text><text start="1401.87" dur="4.679">Requiring genetics everybody doesn&apos;t have?</text><text start="1406.549" dur="1.74">No.</text><text start="1408.289" dur="5.901">Now, we could say that&apos;s not possible for
everybody, in which case we should say democracy</text><text start="1414.19" dur="1.41">is no longer relevant.</text><text start="1415.6" dur="5.449">We should get rid of democracy because having
a bunch of people that are falsely certain,</text><text start="1421.049" dur="5.911">and angrily righteous about it, trying to
do some system of open governance is obviously</text><text start="1426.96" dur="3.62">not going to work well, in which case we should
find a small number of people and make them</text><text start="1430.58" dur="2.93">the new nobility.</text><text start="1433.51" dur="1.32">That&apos;s the Chinese answer, right?</text><text start="1434.83" dur="1.38">In the current environment.</text><text start="1436.21" dur="1.75">There are other groups that are working on
that.</text><text start="1437.96" dur="4.15">If you want an open society where everyone
gets to participate in choice-making, then</text><text start="1442.11" dur="2.27">everybody has to do a good job of sense-making.</text><text start="1444.38" dur="2.909">To do a good job of sense-making and meaning-making.</text><text start="1447.289" dur="3.5">What is really meaningful here and what is
really going on here?</text><text start="1450.789" dur="6.13">If you want anything like a democratic or
open society, the minimum required investment</text><text start="1456.919" dur="5.031">is authentic, deep informed-ness about the
nature of the issues, which also requires</text><text start="1461.95" dur="2.3">adequate educated-ness to be capable of that.</text><text start="1464.25" dur="2.591">Nate Hagens:
I personally fully agree with that as you</text><text start="1466.841" dur="4.399">know, but I think that is a minority view
probably.</text><text start="1471.24" dur="4.91">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Well, I think it&apos;s a minority of people that</text><text start="1476.15" dur="5.23">think about what the prerequisites of a democracy
to really function well in a complex world.</text><text start="1481.38" dur="3.38">It&apos;s a minority of people that even think
about theory of governance.</text><text start="1484.76" dur="5.93">I don&apos;t know that many people would really
disagree with it if the logic was presented.</text><text start="1490.69" dur="3.15">Nate Hagens:
Okay.</text><text start="1493.84" dur="5.15">I&apos;ve kind of already changed the outline of
this conversation, which was, of course, with</text><text start="1498.99" dur="2.6">you and I probably inevitable.</text><text start="1501.59" dur="5.76">You wanted to put a pin in the whole meta-narrative
can be understood in an individual mind.</text><text start="1507.35" dur="2.01">You had something to say there.</text><text start="1509.36" dur="4.25">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
That&apos;s actually really important because one</text><text start="1513.61" dur="3.73">of the things that I would say...</text><text start="1517.34" dur="8.62">One of the fundamental aspects of the meta-crisis,
if you want to call it that, is that for us</text><text start="1525.96" dur="10.19">to be able to coordinate lots of human activity
in a big corporation or a military or whatever,</text><text start="1536.15" dur="5.359">we need to be able to decompose complex tasks
into a bunch of small tasks, everybody do</text><text start="1541.509" dur="3.03">those, and recompose the small tasks.</text><text start="1544.539" dur="5.961">So, we divide up understanding the world into
the natural sciences and the social sciences</text><text start="1550.5" dur="4.07">and then the natural sciences and the biology
and chemistry and then biology into ecology</text><text start="1554.57" dur="2.329">and microbiology and whatever.</text><text start="1556.899" dur="3.071">The idea that we can then somehow recompose
that.</text><text start="1559.97" dur="5.38">But in doing so... and this is kind of key
to reductionism is we convert the complex</text><text start="1565.35" dur="1.03">to the complicated.</text><text start="1566.38" dur="9.049">We convert the self-organizing nature of nature
to some taxonomy that you can separate thinking.</text><text start="1575.429" dur="4.541">You can understand the parts and that the
parts are not fundamentally also defined by</text><text start="1579.97" dur="2.0">their relationship to each other.</text><text start="1581.97" dur="10.28">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And so, whenever that happens, we can optimize</text><text start="1592.25" dur="4.039">for a part without realizing that it&apos;s at
the expense of another part that is outside</text><text start="1596.289" dur="3.37">of our domain of study.</text><text start="1599.659" dur="3.791">This is why we end up getting iatrogenic medicines
where we look at the cause of the disease</text><text start="1603.45" dur="4.24">in this very narrow way because we had to
split up the complexity of the body into gastroenterology</text><text start="1607.69" dur="2.89">and oncology and neurology and et cetera.</text><text start="1610.58" dur="4.99">Then, we say, &quot;Well, you have high cholesterol,
so we&apos;re going to give you a statin or you</text><text start="1615.57" dur="1.0">have this, so we&apos;re going to give you that.&quot;</text><text start="1616.57" dur="2.53">That thing produces side effects in other
parts of the body.</text><text start="1619.1" dur="2.64">They didn&apos;t look into the deeper cause across
the systems.</text><text start="1621.74" dur="3.01">That&apos;s why a complex chronic disease doesn&apos;t
actually have cures.</text><text start="1624.75" dur="5.08">Because we don&apos;t understand them because you
have things that start in the gut and then</text><text start="1629.83" dur="2.42">affect the immune system and then affect the
nervous system.</text><text start="1632.25" dur="2.2">You have to understand those complex causations.</text><text start="1634.45" dur="1.76">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
The same is true with...</text><text start="1636.21" dur="5.329">Can you fix the environment without understanding
industry and infrastructure and economics</text><text start="1641.539" dur="1.531">and human political theory?</text><text start="1643.07" dur="1.77">It&apos;s all deeply connected.</text><text start="1644.84" dur="4.43">When you decompose it and you try to solve
the problems in isolation, you end up just</text><text start="1649.27" dur="3.06">moving the problem somewhere else.</text><text start="1652.33" dur="2.76">And so the need for...</text><text start="1655.09" dur="4.63">Of course, no one person can understand everything,
but they can seek to understand in a way that</text><text start="1659.72" dur="6.13">has more cognizance of the depth of interconnectedness.</text><text start="1665.85" dur="4.72">That&apos;s the only way to be able to do something
like any degree of specialization that is</text><text start="1670.57" dur="1.89">not itself part of the problem.</text><text start="1672.46" dur="5.11">Nate Hagens:
Let&apos;s go into my second question that I had</text><text start="1677.57" dur="9.719">planned for you now and get back to your changes
and edits to my systems overview.</text><text start="1687.289" dur="7.691">Why is it that, when we go to a conference
or there&apos;s a presentation or something, the</text><text start="1694.98" dur="6.029">larger fly up high enough and look down at
the topography of the human predicament...</text><text start="1701.009" dur="10.071">Why there is so much pushback from people
who are single issue, focused on social justice</text><text start="1711.08" dur="10.79">or inequality or climate change or Bitcoin
or politics, and yet, like you just said,</text><text start="1721.87" dur="4.36">you need to look at how all this stuff fits
together in order to see the right map of</text><text start="1726.23" dur="1.319">our future.</text><text start="1727.549" dur="2.0">Why is it so difficult?</text><text start="1729.549" dur="6.691">What is happening socially here and how might
it be overcome or at least steered so we can</text><text start="1736.24" dur="6.26">get more people looking at... squinting and
seeing roughly what a more accurate systems</text><text start="1742.5" dur="3.11">map would look like?</text><text start="1745.61" dur="10.159">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
The answer is begged in the question itself.</text><text start="1755.769" dur="9.601">Let&apos;s say that someone starts to understand
climate change and understand the significance</text><text start="1765.37" dur="1.679">of that issue portends to all life.</text><text start="1767.049" dur="4.981">And then they look at how long people have
understood this and how long they&apos;ve worked</text><text start="1772.03" dur="3.45">on it and that it&apos;s not making progress.</text><text start="1775.48" dur="5.059">It by itself seems like an overwhelmingly
large and bordering on impossible task.</text><text start="1780.539" dur="1.311">And so critical.</text><text start="1781.85" dur="1.05">Existential.</text><text start="1782.9" dur="4.7">Why would anyone move any attention to anything
other than just move this thing forward, right?</text><text start="1787.6" dur="6.31">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Similarly, let&apos;s say that you witnessed firsthand</text><text start="1793.91" dur="6.11">what happens inside of a factory farm or the
clear cutting of rainforests in an area.</text><text start="1800.02" dur="6.85">The idea that anyone else wants to go up to
some higher, highfalutin, abstraction place</text><text start="1806.87" dur="4.939">that seems kind of academic when these orangutans
are burning to death as the Indonesian forests</text><text start="1811.809" dur="3.761">are getting cut down to make fucking paper
bags...</text><text start="1815.57" dur="5.63">The realness of the issues, the imminence
of the issues...</text><text start="1821.2" dur="7.53">If you live in a ghetto and you&apos;re focused
on social justice because you have a direct</text><text start="1828.73" dur="6.039">relationship with what the police are like
and institutional racism is like and what</text><text start="1834.769" dur="4.091">redlining is like and those things and then
you hear something like these talks, you&apos;re</text><text start="1838.86" dur="2.34">like, we fucking live in existential risk
every day.</text><text start="1841.2" dur="3.559">Just walking around with our skin color with
the police around is an existential risk every</text><text start="1844.759" dur="6.17">day and you want to talk about fundamental
problems of world views?</text><text start="1850.929" dur="1.22">Come live in our world.</text><text start="1852.149" dur="3.76">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
It&apos;s easy to understand why anyone who is</text><text start="1855.909" dur="1.781">touching something...</text><text start="1857.69" dur="7.38">The existential risk for people in the Ukraine
is not a hypothetical issue in the future,</text><text start="1865.07" dur="1.0">right?</text><text start="1866.07" dur="2.079">Or for people in Syria.</text><text start="1868.149" dur="5.75">And so what you and I are doing is a position
of privilege in a way that we aren&apos;t in Ukraine</text><text start="1873.899" dur="4.49">or we aren&apos;t in the ghetto or we aren&apos;t in
a rainforest that&apos;s being clearcut, where</text><text start="1878.389" dur="1.62">our way of life is being imminently destroyed.</text><text start="1880.009" dur="3.74">We&apos;re able to look at all those things and
have our heartbreak from every single one</text><text start="1883.749" dur="6.361">of them and be like, fuck, all of those are
existential for some people and some life,</text><text start="1890.11" dur="4.49">some animals, and all of them also portend
patterns that could be existential or catastrophic</text><text start="1894.6" dur="1.579">for everything.</text><text start="1896.179" dur="2.1">And none of them seem to be getting much better.</text><text start="1898.279" dur="3.961">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Maybe more on-the-ground activism of that</text><text start="1902.24" dur="1.91">type isn&apos;t actually going to cut it.</text><text start="1904.15" dur="5.099">Maybe something else is actually required
and maybe we&apos;re wrong.</text><text start="1909.249" dur="1.341">Maybe we&apos;re wrong.</text><text start="1910.59" dur="1.88">That&apos;s an important point.</text><text start="1912.47" dur="1.61">But that&apos;s kind of how I came to it.</text><text start="1914.08" dur="5.469">I&apos;m guessing that you might have had a similar
story of I can&apos;t actually turn away from any</text><text start="1919.549" dur="1.0">of these issues.</text><text start="1920.549" dur="2.301">Once I&apos;ve been exposed enough, I can&apos;t turn
away from them.</text><text start="1922.85" dur="3.5">And I also don&apos;t think any of them are getting
better, so I think the fundamental approach</text><text start="1926.35" dur="1.67">is missing something.</text><text start="1928.02" dur="5.31">Maybe there&apos;s something about the deeper structures
that all those problems are symptoms of that,</text><text start="1933.33" dur="3.29">unless we understand it, we actually can&apos;t
solve any of them.</text><text start="1936.62" dur="4.02">And if we do understand it, maybe we can do
something more fundamentally effective everywhere.</text><text start="1940.64" dur="3.09">Nate Hagens:
That&apos;s exactly my view.</text><text start="1943.73" dur="6.939">My observation to you... and we shared a couple
Voxers on it last week or two weeks ago...</text><text start="1950.669" dur="11.1">was that, since I feel that so deeply and
viscerally and almost spiritually, I expect</text><text start="1961.769" dur="4.301">that other people, when they see the connections
and the underlying structure, will feel the</text><text start="1966.07" dur="3.469">same way I do and I&apos;m often disappointed with
that.</text><text start="1969.539" dur="2.491">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
But it&apos;s like...</text><text start="1972.03" dur="7.989">I can&apos;t feel what it&apos;s like to be in an indigenous
tribe living in the Amazon and then actually</text><text start="1980.019" dur="5.081">have mining companies or logging companies
come in and devastate my whole world and have</text><text start="1985.1" dur="3.939">the petrol dumped in where everybody gets
cancer from the water.</text><text start="1989.039" dur="3.61">I can&apos;t feel that if I don&apos;t have some grounding
in it.</text><text start="1992.649" dur="1.571">I got to go there and be with them.</text><text start="1994.22" dur="4.03">And, still, I&apos;ll only get a little bit of
it.</text><text start="1998.25" dur="4.049">I can&apos;t really feel what it&apos;s like to be a
mother in Ukraine right now.</text><text start="2002.299" dur="2.901">I can kind of get a sense, but we have to
ground in it to get it.</text><text start="2005.2" dur="1.049">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
The same thing is true.</text><text start="2006.249" dur="5.4">If you and I are sharing stories where we&apos;ve
spent years and years in data and abstract</text><text start="2011.649" dur="4.641">thought about it, of course, nobody else is
going to be able to get all of that without</text><text start="2016.29" dur="1.46">some grounding in it.</text><text start="2017.75" dur="3.13">Then, it&apos;s just our job to say, all right,
what is the best one?</text><text start="2020.88" dur="1.419">Is it even relevant for everybody?</text><text start="2022.299" dur="2.031">It&apos;ll be relevant for some people and not
others.</text><text start="2024.33" dur="3.51">Other people doing a better job with the issues
that they&apos;re already connected to is the right</text><text start="2027.84" dur="1.0">thing.</text><text start="2028.84" dur="3.339">We want to just move our attention to say
is there anything from our domain of focus</text><text start="2032.179" dur="6.801">that could help them with that thing that
they&apos;re focused on because what they&apos;re doing</text><text start="2038.98" dur="1.0">is critical.</text><text start="2039.98" dur="5.5">Sometimes, if being able to work on more fundamental
systemic kinds of change is important, then</text><text start="2045.48" dur="3.78">it&apos;s like, all right, how do we actually help
the concept but also the experiential grounding</text><text start="2049.26" dur="1.0">of it to land?</text><text start="2050.26" dur="1.0">And it&apos;s a process.</text><text start="2051.26" dur="1.609">This is the two-marshmallow thing.</text><text start="2052.869" dur="5.22">In the same way we would like other people
to not jump to certainty too quickly, we need</text><text start="2058.089" dur="3.201">to also... and they would go through a process
of sense-making...</text><text start="2061.29" dur="3.83">we also need to go through a process of people&apos;s
sense-making with them.</text><text start="2065.12" dur="2.87">And it takes some time.</text><text start="2067.99" dur="2.329">Nate Hagens:
Okay.</text><text start="2070.319" dur="4.451">I&apos;m with you on that.</text><text start="2074.77" dur="4.289">Going back to the original choreography-</text><text start="2079.059" dur="1.84">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
The one thing I wanted to share here about</text><text start="2080.899" dur="5.43">worldviews and meta-narratives real quick
and then we can go back...</text><text start="2086.329" dur="5.081">If you would have somebody on your team put
in the show notes the conversations between</text><text start="2091.41" dur="3.28">David Bohm and Krishnamurti, the link to that...</text><text start="2094.69" dur="5.68">Some of the most beautiful things ever recorded
on video that I watched and influenced me</text><text start="2100.37" dur="2.19">growing up.</text><text start="2102.56" dur="4.09">They were in this very deep inquiry about
what is the fundamental nature of the problems</text><text start="2106.65" dur="3.87">in the world and what is the fundamental nature
of human conflict and poor human choices.</text><text start="2110.52" dur="4.64">They both shared really insightful frames
on it.</text><text start="2115.16" dur="1.86">Krishnamurti&apos;s was...</text><text start="2117.02" dur="4.77">He said the highest stage of intelligence
is to observe without evaluation, meaning</text><text start="2121.79" dur="1.53">we actually don&apos;t see the world.</text><text start="2123.32" dur="4.34">We see the world through the very limited
lens through which we meaning-make it.</text><text start="2127.66" dur="6.24">If you can see the world, if you can sense
more deeply, then you can do better sense</text><text start="2133.9" dur="1.0">making.</text><text start="2134.9" dur="3.63">But I can&apos;t sense-make stuff I didn&apos;t even
take in and I&apos;m not going to take it in if</text><text start="2138.53" dur="2.39">I&apos;m pushing it through filters too quickly.</text><text start="2140.92" dur="3.52">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So, that&apos;s very relevant, but I&apos;m actually</text><text start="2144.44" dur="3.27">going to emphasize the one Bohm shared here.</text><text start="2147.71" dur="4.31">Bohm said the fundamental cause of all the
problems in the world, environmental war all</text><text start="2152.02" dur="6.0">the way down to family conflict, is what he
called a fragmented consciousness.</text><text start="2158.02" dur="2.809">He talked about wholeness and the implicate
order.</text><text start="2160.829" dur="1.851">Because remember.</text><text start="2162.68" dur="1.64">He studied with Einstein.</text><text start="2164.32" dur="4.039">Einstein said it&apos;s an optical delusion of
consciousness to believe there are separate</text><text start="2168.359" dur="1.0">things.</text><text start="2169.359" dur="2.141">There is, in reality, one thing we call universe.</text><text start="2171.5" dur="5.39">It&apos;s such a deep thing to think about what
Einstein was saying because it&apos;s like, I think</text><text start="2176.89" dur="4.169">of myself as a separate human a lot of times,
but what am I without the Sun?</text><text start="2181.059" dur="2.06">I don&apos;t exist at all.</text><text start="2183.119" dur="1.591">What am I without the electromagnetic field?</text><text start="2184.71" dur="1.0">I don&apos;t exist.</text><text start="2185.71" dur="1.06">What am I without the higgs boson?</text><text start="2186.77" dur="1.0">I don&apos;t exist.</text><text start="2187.77" dur="6.92">What am I without plants or algae or the biosphere
or the ozone layer.</text><text start="2194.69" dur="2.34">Me as a separate thing is actually a misnomer.</text><text start="2197.03" dur="1.54">It doesn&apos;t even exist.</text><text start="2198.57" dur="4.759">It&apos;s what Einstein called a delusion of consciousness
to believe that there are parts that...</text><text start="2203.329" dur="1.991">Just because there&apos;s distinction, we think
they&apos;re separable.</text><text start="2205.32" dur="1.07">And they&apos;re not separable.</text><text start="2206.39" dur="2.43">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Then, of course, in that delusion, we can</text><text start="2208.82" dur="4.84">try to optimize for a part at the expense
of something else, either on purpose or without</text><text start="2213.66" dur="2.51">knowing it, and we cause a lot of problems.</text><text start="2216.17" dur="5.11">If you do it without knowing it, we call it
mistake theory and externalities.</text><text start="2221.28" dur="2.66">If you do it intentionally, we call it conflict
theory.</text><text start="2223.94" dur="2.07">War, oppression, whatever.</text><text start="2226.01" dur="5.829">So, David Bohm said the underlying cause of
all the problems is not perceiving from wholeness</text><text start="2231.839" dur="1.0">first.</text><text start="2232.839" dur="4.731">And it&apos;s so true that the generator function
of the generator function, the deepest thing,</text><text start="2237.57" dur="1.019">starts there.</text><text start="2238.589" dur="8.551">Which is, if you think about it in terms of
I can try to benefit myself in the moment</text><text start="2247.14" dur="3.61">at the expense of my future self, that&apos;s the
one-marshmallow activities.</text><text start="2250.75" dur="6.71">But that&apos;s the connection to my temporally
momentary self and not to the wholeness of</text><text start="2257.46" dur="1.97">myself across time.</text><text start="2259.43" dur="5.48">And so the addictive hit in the moment that
messes up my future life is a theory of trade</text><text start="2264.91" dur="3.439">offs based on not actually seeing the wholeness
of myself across time.</text><text start="2268.349" dur="2.501">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I can try to benefit one part of myself at</text><text start="2270.85" dur="4.92">the expense of another part, which is all
of our internal conflicts, or myself relative</text><text start="2275.77" dur="5.21">to someone else, advantaging myself relative
to them is traditional conflict, or I try</text><text start="2280.98" dur="3.67">to advantage somebody else at my own expense,
martyring and co-dependence, which ends up</text><text start="2284.65" dur="4.84">creating resentment and passive aggressiveness
and problems, or my in-group relative to an</text><text start="2289.49" dur="3.339">in-group or my species relative to the biosphere.</text><text start="2292.829" dur="4.201">When you recognize the interconnectedness,
you see that all of those are short-term pump</text><text start="2297.03" dur="2.329">and dumps.</text><text start="2299.359" dur="5.521">And that, if you see the interconnectivity
of the whole thing, none of those parts can</text><text start="2304.88" dur="4.65">authentically and enduringly be optimized
independent of all the other ones.</text><text start="2309.53" dur="7.1">We can get into how we do this systems framing,
and we should, but I hold, in terms of the</text><text start="2316.63" dur="4.699">deepest way to look at it, is that particular
pattern of perception and identity.</text><text start="2321.329" dur="1.601">Nate Hagens:
Two comments.</text><text start="2322.93" dur="2.22">One, that was trippy.</text><text start="2325.15" dur="9.48">Two, you made me think that maybe instead
of refining and simplifying the meta-narrative</text><text start="2334.63" dur="6.35">so that more people can understand it, which
is my vocation right now, it may be more productive</text><text start="2340.98" dur="5.879">to boost the number of humans that are in
a place where they perceive their role as</text><text start="2346.859" dur="1.151">a whole...</text><text start="2348.01" dur="2.73">as part of the whole, like you were saying.</text><text start="2350.74" dur="9.44">I mean, we need orders of magnitude more humans
from that cognitive development space that</text><text start="2360.18" dur="5.201">are able to see that that&apos;s more important
than, hey, there&apos;s climate change, there&apos;s</text><text start="2365.381" dur="5.438">energy depletion, there&apos;s nuclear, the AI,
all that stuff.</text><text start="2370.819" dur="4.231">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
It might seem like I&apos;m forcing things as a</text><text start="2375.05" dur="7.36">fit here, but I believe that the ancient wisdom
traditions had wise people that saw similar</text><text start="2382.41" dur="2.84">things and encoded them differently.</text><text start="2385.25" dur="7.53">It&apos;s said by many Vedic philosophers that
the Bhagavad Gita, the great kind of scripture,</text><text start="2392.78" dur="4.25">one of them, of Hinduism, chapter two, verse
48 is fundamental.</text><text start="2397.03" dur="2.309">Established in yoga.</text><text start="2399.339" dur="1.0">Perform action.</text><text start="2400.339" dur="4.201">Yoga means union with all that is, &quot;yogastha
kuru karmani&quot; is the quote.</text><text start="2404.54" dur="5.16">And it says, &quot;Established in yoga, or union
with all that is, from the place where you</text><text start="2409.7" dur="4.649">recognize that your existence doesn&apos;t exist
without everything else and from the place</text><text start="2414.349" dur="4.111">where you cognitively but also experientially
get that, where there&apos;s an intimacy with all</text><text start="2418.46" dur="2.24">life, and act from there.</text><text start="2420.7" dur="4.12">Spontaneous right action emerges from that
place.&quot;</text><text start="2424.82" dur="3.74">When, in the Bible, it says, &quot;Seek ye first
the kingdom and all these things shall be</text><text start="2428.56" dur="5.18">added on to you,&quot; the place at which everything
is sons and daughters of the same reality,</text><text start="2433.74" dur="4.58">the place at which there is a sense of the
sacredness of all life in the union with it,</text><text start="2438.32" dur="3.32">then right action starts to be informed from
there.</text><text start="2441.64" dur="7.87">I do think it is a different orientation from
which sense-making and meaning-making happen</text><text start="2449.51" dur="2.5">differently and inform choice-making differently.</text><text start="2452.01" dur="4.25">Nate Hagens:
Well, I&apos;m beginning to get a suspicion that</text><text start="2456.26" dur="7.48">we may have an episode four and five, but
let me just ask you a follow-up to that.</text><text start="2463.74" dur="2.069">You know me pretty well by now.</text><text start="2465.809" dur="2.721">I have very limited experience with psychedelics.</text><text start="2468.53" dur="5.12">I had a magic mushroom omelet on Koh Samui,
Thailand.</text><text start="2473.65" dur="6.37">I remember an 18-inch tall Jesus Christ running
up my leg and I have not really done it since.</text><text start="2480.02" dur="8.16">But I do have spiritual epiphanies being in
nature and feeling that oneness that I&apos;m told</text><text start="2488.18" dur="5.82">happens on ayahuasca or some of these other
psychedelics.</text><text start="2494.0" dur="1.92">Mushrooms.</text><text start="2495.92" dur="6.879">Some of my most mystical experiences in life
are seeing the vibrant green in the trees</text><text start="2502.799" dur="3.091">and the birds and the insects.</text><text start="2505.89" dur="10.26">I felt the connection then and I felt my heartbreak
all along because I think some of the costs</text><text start="2516.15" dur="3.36">of our economic system are back loaded.</text><text start="2519.51" dur="4.549">As we bend and hopefully not break, some of
these things are going to get worse before</text><text start="2524.059" dur="1.481">they get better.</text><text start="2525.54" dur="6.069">I live with that... you could call it trauma
or grief or something... every day, but that</text><text start="2531.609" dur="5.531">also motivates my work and the things that
we&apos;re discussing.</text><text start="2537.14" dur="4.61">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
You can&apos;t just get the cognitive model across</text><text start="2541.75" dur="2.319">to people because that&apos;s not even where it
came from.</text><text start="2544.069" dur="3.091">Why did you do the work to get the cognitive
model?</text><text start="2547.16" dur="5.55">It came from that experience of sacredness
and interconnectedness and the heartbreak.</text><text start="2552.71" dur="4.74">That&apos;s what actually motivates the desire
to figure out how to serve the thing and protect</text><text start="2557.45" dur="2.47">the thing better.</text><text start="2559.92" dur="5.46">It&apos;s not just the understanding that resulted
from what drove that work that has to come</text><text start="2565.38" dur="1.0">across to people.</text><text start="2566.38" dur="1.919">It&apos;s the facilitation of those experiences.</text><text start="2568.299" dur="3.921">Nate Hagens:
How do you merge that all together in a productive</text><text start="2572.22" dur="1.09">way?</text><text start="2573.31" dur="5.68">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Well, first, the fact that you said you&apos;re</text><text start="2578.99" dur="3.589">inquiring into psychedelics but that you just
had experiences in nature...</text><text start="2582.579" dur="7.691">Psychedelics are one way to access non-ordinary
states of consciousness.</text><text start="2590.27" dur="4.66">You can do it with deep time in nature, with
fasting, with meditation, with breath work,</text><text start="2594.93" dur="1.689">with lots of things.</text><text start="2596.619" dur="5.271">I think psychedelics can be profound tools,
but I also think they can be one-marshmallows</text><text start="2601.89" dur="5.179">to spirituality, where you get the high state
hit without any of the work of really communing</text><text start="2607.069" dur="3.601">with nature or learning to calm the mind.</text><text start="2610.67" dur="5.159">Getting a false sense of knowingness independent
of some of the other important parts.</text><text start="2615.829" dur="4.491">So, the depth of time in nature I generally
prefer.</text><text start="2620.32" dur="5.019">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
This is actually something I want to say because</text><text start="2625.339" dur="4.601">people ask me this and I&apos;m sure they ask you
this sometimes.</text><text start="2629.94" dur="5.94">In CBT, cognitive behavioral therapy, there
is a very popular term called catastrophizing.</text><text start="2635.88" dur="6.719">That people end up having more psychological
pain and drama in their life because they</text><text start="2642.599" dur="3.281">anticipate the worst possible things that
don&apos;t end up happening.</text><text start="2645.88" dur="3.88">There&apos;s that Mark Twain quote, &quot;I&apos;ve suffered
of great many terrible things in my life and</text><text start="2649.76" dur="4.099">a few of them actually happened,&quot; meaning
most of the great, terrible things are shit</text><text start="2653.859" dur="3.661">we just made up that never happened and we
suffered from them anyways.</text><text start="2657.52" dur="4.039">CBT tries to help people get over catastrophizing.</text><text start="2661.559" dur="6.78">I&apos;ve noticed that many people who focus on
catastrophic risk have a catastrophizing disposition</text><text start="2668.339" dur="1.731">and it happens in other areas of their life.</text><text start="2670.07" dur="4.249">The gift of it is it makes them think through
possible catastrophes for the world better</text><text start="2674.319" dur="2.581">than most people, so they can be protectors.</text><text start="2676.9" dur="1.0">Awesome.</text><text start="2677.9" dur="3.53">But it also has some pretty big downsides
in that they oftentimes catastrophize their</text><text start="2681.43" dur="3.46">own personal life and relationships in ways
that makes it hard for them to be collaborated</text><text start="2684.89" dur="2.64">with because they have a hard time trusting
people because they catastrophize that other</text><text start="2687.53" dur="2.7">people will always fuck them over or whatever
else it is.</text><text start="2690.23" dur="5.02">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And so for what it&apos;s worth, I don&apos;t have a</text><text start="2695.25" dur="1.4">catastrophizing disposition.</text><text start="2696.65" dur="2.73">I actually have a very optimistic disposition.</text><text start="2699.38" dur="10.969">I got interested in catastrophic risk as a
byproduct of that same thing.</text><text start="2710.349" dur="6.101">Of a very local, small scale love of these
animals and then the heartbreak at what happened.</text><text start="2716.45" dur="5.94">Love of these environments, a sense of sacredness
of life, and then that it was being harmed.</text><text start="2722.39" dur="1.82">I just wanted to solve that local issue.</text><text start="2724.21" dur="3.32">And then I started to understand that local
issue wasn&apos;t just local.</text><text start="2727.53" dur="3.809">And then I got to start to understand, fuck,
it&apos;s not just factory farms on cows, it&apos;s</text><text start="2731.339" dur="3.73">factory farms on lots of animals, which also
goes along with clear cutting and then overfishing</text><text start="2735.069" dur="1.0">of the oceans.</text><text start="2736.069" dur="1.191">And then it just kept expanding.</text><text start="2737.26" dur="1.52">So, then...</text><text start="2738.78" dur="1.52">All right.</text><text start="2740.3" dur="1.0">Man.</text><text start="2741.3" dur="3.43">What other great horrors are there that need
tended to, but that are only horrific because</text><text start="2744.73" dur="1.2">life is beautiful?</text><text start="2745.93" dur="4.21">If life wasn&apos;t beautiful, if those cows lives
weren&apos;t sacred, I wouldn&apos;t give a shit.</text><text start="2750.14" dur="1.191">I&apos;d just be like, fine, let it happen.</text><text start="2751.331" dur="1.049">Let it burn down.</text><text start="2752.38" dur="1.3">If the Amazon didn&apos;t...</text><text start="2753.68" dur="2.76">If there wasn&apos;t something sacred about all
the life there, I&apos;d be like, I don&apos;t care.</text><text start="2756.44" dur="3.28">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And so the anger at the people who are hurting</text><text start="2759.72" dur="6.49">it or the heartbreak or the fear is the epiphenomena
of the fact that it&apos;s intrinsically meaningful</text><text start="2766.21" dur="1.27">and beautiful for everybody.</text><text start="2767.48" dur="4.03">And so it&apos;s important for them to remember
that and realize, hey, the only reason I&apos;m</text><text start="2771.51" dur="3.299">scared or pissed off is because there&apos;s something
I really love.</text><text start="2774.809" dur="4.28">And then how do I come back into a direct
relationship with what is sacred to me and</text><text start="2779.089" dur="1.311">how do I be of best service?</text><text start="2780.4" dur="3.54">Is the anger the right way or do I actually
want to come back into the sense of love and</text><text start="2783.94" dur="6.63">beauty and sacredness and be more for than
against?</text><text start="2790.57" dur="10.36">So, it&apos;s not like one has to have some perverse
obsession with doom porn to want to focus</text><text start="2800.93" dur="5.09">on AI risk and climate risk and economic risk
and nuclear risk.</text><text start="2806.02" dur="3.86">When one is wanting to serve life and then
they think about all the things that are going</text><text start="2809.88" dur="5.06">on, it can make natural sense to study those
things but from a fundamentally different</text><text start="2814.94" dur="1.32">place inside.</text><text start="2816.26" dur="3.04">Nate Hagens:
Wow.</text><text start="2819.3" dur="6.539">So, here&apos;s another question I didn&apos;t intend
on asking you.</text><text start="2825.839" dur="4.431">I gave you my two-minute elevator pitch of
my story.</text><text start="2830.27" dur="2.819">I think we are headed for...</text><text start="2833.089" dur="3.561">As you know, I call it a great simplification.</text><text start="2836.65" dur="7.49">When our economic output is no longer able
to continue to grow at the scale that our</text><text start="2844.14" dur="3.6">cultural and financial expectations have given
it.</text><text start="2847.74" dur="3.01">And we&apos;re going to have to respond to that.</text><text start="2850.75" dur="2.73">Now, since I&apos;ve had this-</text><text start="2853.48" dur="4.03">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
You know I agree with you on that frame.</text><text start="2857.51" dur="3.7">What we do about it we can get into...</text><text start="2861.21" dur="5.3">Nate Hagens:
That&apos;s a point on our original plan.</text><text start="2866.51" dur="3.37">What&apos;s been surprising to me... and maybe
you&apos;ll have some thoughts on this given what</text><text start="2869.88" dur="9.26">you just said... is, six months into this
podcast and after my movie and some of my</text><text start="2879.14" dur="9.72">other videos, I fully expected to be grilled
and have stones cast at me from finance MBAs</text><text start="2888.86" dur="3.64">and economists and technologists.</text><text start="2892.5" dur="3.79">And there have not been that many of those.</text><text start="2896.29" dur="1.94">Probably because they&apos;re just not paying attention.</text><text start="2898.23" dur="2.48">That could be Occam&apos;s razor.</text><text start="2900.71" dur="6.159">But I have gotten a lot of stones, surprisingly,
from people that think I&apos;m too optimistic.</text><text start="2906.869" dur="1.17">You don&apos;t understand.</text><text start="2908.039" dur="1.101">We&apos;re headed for collapse.</text><text start="2909.14" dur="2.899">There&apos;s nothing we can do.</text><text start="2912.039" dur="2.77">Humans are going to go extinct by 2050.</text><text start="2914.809" dur="1.871">You don&apos;t understand climate.</text><text start="2916.68" dur="3.439">We&apos;re already on runaway towards Venus and
there&apos;s nothing we can do.</text><text start="2920.119" dur="5.17">As soon as global dimming kicks in, it&apos;s game
over.</text><text start="2925.289" dur="4.141">All these things.</text><text start="2929.43" dur="4.79">Anyone that&apos;s paying attention to the story
that thinks collapse is not at least a reasonable</text><text start="2934.22" dur="2.71">possibility isn&apos;t paying attention.</text><text start="2936.93" dur="1.419">But I think it&apos;s a possibility.</text><text start="2938.349" dur="1.841">It&apos;s not a likelihood.</text><text start="2940.19" dur="4.99">And I want to do everything I can to make
the future better than the default.</text><text start="2945.18" dur="4.9">But it&apos;s very fascinating to me that most
of the pushback that I&apos;ve gotten personally</text><text start="2950.08" dur="1.64">in my inbox...</text><text start="2951.72" dur="4.32">I mean, there&apos;s a lot of congratulatory supportive
stuff, but most people are poking holes saying</text><text start="2956.04" dur="3.49">I&apos;m too optimistic, which is kind of ironic.</text><text start="2959.53" dur="6.309">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Okay, this is really interesting.</text><text start="2965.839" dur="5.641">I want to share a personal story about it,
but first...</text><text start="2971.48" dur="6.609">Most people have had the experience at some
point in their life when they are really suffering</text><text start="2978.089" dur="3.27">about something.</text><text start="2981.359" dur="4.091">Somebody else tells them to just cheer up
or be optimistic or it&apos;s not that bad and</text><text start="2985.45" dur="3.32">they feel much worse.</text><text start="2988.77" dur="5.9">This is like the gaslighting phenomena, where
especially someone is...</text><text start="2994.67" dur="4.48">Say somebody is dealing with someone in their
life who they know is lying to them and whatever.</text><text start="2999.15" dur="3.719">And someone else says, &quot;No, it&apos;s not really
happening or it&apos;s not that bad or why don&apos;t</text><text start="3002.869" dur="3.021">you take responsibility for it?&quot;</text><text start="3005.89" dur="3.88">Of course, people should take responsibility
for what they can, but a superficial assessment.</text><text start="3009.77" dur="2.44">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
There&apos;s a place that, when someone&apos;s really</text><text start="3012.21" dur="5.19">in pain, they just actually want someone else
to feel it with them.</text><text start="3017.4" dur="4.949">They don&apos;t want to be made wrong and they
don&apos;t want it to be lessened.</text><text start="3022.349" dur="4.48">Because the thing that makes the pain even
worse is the loneliness of no one else can</text><text start="3026.829" dur="3.481">hold this with me.</text><text start="3030.31" dur="5.68">Sometimes the optimism prematurely seems like
a spiritual bypass to prevent the grief.</text><text start="3035.99" dur="3.45">They actually just need to be in the grief
and they need to know anyone else sees the</text><text start="3039.44" dur="3.75">thing that they see and can feel it with them.</text><text start="3043.19" dur="5.38">Now, of course, there&apos;s the separation of
the cognitive thinking through it versus the</text><text start="3048.57" dur="1.529">emotional experience.</text><text start="3050.099" dur="2.7">People conflate these and they&apos;re not all
that clear on it.</text><text start="3052.799" dur="3.431">They&apos;re like, &quot;No, it just is this way and
I&apos;m not trying to get empathy.</text><text start="3056.23" dur="2.79">I&apos;m just trying to tell you the way it is.&quot;</text><text start="3059.02" dur="6.14">I would say, in that place, they&apos;re under-discerning
about the way internal process works.</text><text start="3065.16" dur="6.83">So, there is a place where there&apos;s a space
that is needed to not jump to the optimism</text><text start="3071.99" dur="6.869">too quickly and to actually be able to just
feel collective trauma and grieve.</text><text start="3078.859" dur="4.75">That then gets to bring us to a state that
is capable of saying, without denying any</text><text start="3083.609" dur="4.561">of that or bypassing it, now, what is the
space of agency?</text><text start="3088.17" dur="2.0">What is possible to do?</text><text start="3090.17" dur="5.5">Again, this is tricky because we can&apos;t do
this on a podcast with people.</text><text start="3095.67" dur="2.51">This is deep, embodied, personal work.</text><text start="3098.18" dur="4.0">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So, that was one thing I wanted to say about</text><text start="3102.18" dur="1.419">it.</text><text start="3103.599" dur="3.23">And the other one is...</text><text start="3106.829" dur="4.651">This is totally not where you and I thought
we were going to go with this, but this podcast</text><text start="3111.48" dur="1.0">was where we&apos;re going.</text><text start="3112.48" dur="5.4">I&apos;ll share a spiritual experience I had that
was a big part of my process.</text><text start="3117.88" dur="9.55">Like many people, there was a series of life-defining
experiences.</text><text start="3127.43" dur="3.96">This was a young one, so it sounds naive and
it is.</text><text start="3131.39" dur="2.929">Please give the benefit of the doubt that
I think about it in more refined ways than</text><text start="3134.319" dur="4.851">I did when I was 15, but this is 15 year old
insight.</text><text start="3139.17" dur="3.669">Because I was homeschooled, I didn&apos;t have
a curriculum.</text><text start="3142.839" dur="1.51">I got to study whatever I wanted.</text><text start="3144.349" dur="2.71">When I got deeply into...</text><text start="3147.059" dur="5.81">I got into the animal activism stuff when
I was nine, but from 12 to 15, I was working</text><text start="3152.869" dur="5.651">with Greenpeace and PETA and whatever, lots
of orgs, and just kind of full time studying</text><text start="3158.52" dur="4.93">all of the metrics that I could of species
extinction and soil erosion and biodiversity</text><text start="3163.45" dur="5.21">loss and planetary boundaries and all those
things.</text><text start="3168.66" dur="6.05">I had enough of a sense of science and math
to be able to do some forecasting.</text><text start="3174.71" dur="3.94">Nate Hagens:
When you were 12 to 15.</text><text start="3178.65" dur="1.0">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="3179.65" dur="1.0">But I wasn&apos;t doing that in addition to school.</text><text start="3180.65" dur="1.0">That was my school.</text><text start="3181.65" dur="7.209">I was spending all of my time doing that.</text><text start="3188.859" dur="7.98">I came to the conclusion, as unequipped as
I was and naive as it was, that self-induced</text><text start="3196.839" dur="3.45">human extinction was inevitable in the relatively
near term.</text><text start="3200.289" dur="4.861">Because I was trying to look at the things
that were getting better that were adequate</text><text start="3205.15" dur="3.939">to solve the problems and what those curves
looked like relative to the points of no return</text><text start="3209.089" dur="1.0">and they just weren&apos;t convergent.</text><text start="3210.089" dur="8.02">The things get to points of no return before
we get to the adequate solution spaces.</text><text start="3218.109" dur="4.361">And so that brought me to where I think many
of those people who wrote to you was.</text><text start="3222.47" dur="1.06">Like, you don&apos;t get the math.</text><text start="3223.53" dur="1.0">The math is bad.</text><text start="3224.53" dur="1.0">We&apos;re fucked.</text><text start="3225.53" dur="7.009">And, of course, then being unwilling to accept
that and wanting to feel some sense of agency.</text><text start="3232.539" dur="6.201">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Again, as an emotionally disturbed but caring</text><text start="3238.74" dur="5.25">and emotionally immature 15 year old, I started
thinking about depopulation strategies.</text><text start="3243.99" dur="4.69">Because I&apos;m like, we just can&apos;t do it with
this many people.</text><text start="3248.68" dur="2.26">The collective ignorance mass is too high.</text><text start="3250.94" dur="2.7">The collective utilization of resources is
too high.</text><text start="3253.64" dur="2.13">If there was a lot less people, we could make
it.</text><text start="3255.77" dur="4.88">And if we don&apos;t, then we&apos;ll end up doing things
that end up leading to no people and a lot</text><text start="3260.65" dur="1.78">of harm to the rest of the species.</text><text start="3262.43" dur="5.409">So, I started thinking about technological
population reduction solutions.</text><text start="3267.839" dur="4.811">This is one of the reasons that I&apos;m concerned
about decentralized exponential technologies</text><text start="3272.65" dur="4.24">like tabletop CRISPR and stuff is because
I know there are other people thinking about</text><text start="3276.89" dur="3.32">those things and the technology to be able
to act on it is getting much easier than it</text><text start="3280.21" dur="3.129">was back all those years ago when I was 15.</text><text start="3283.339" dur="3.661">Even then, I was able to think about some
things.</text><text start="3287.0" dur="4.349">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
One of the experiences that took me off of</text><text start="3291.349" dur="5.871">that path was...</text><text start="3297.22" dur="7.139">I can&apos;t say exactly why it happened, but Bucky
Fuller...</text><text start="3304.359" dur="3.231">I heard him say this so many times when I
was a kid, but it hit me all of a sudden in</text><text start="3307.59" dur="1.0">a different way.</text><text start="3308.59" dur="2.32">He talked about this example of...</text><text start="3310.91" dur="8.67">That, when a bird is developing inside of
the egg, the yolk is what becomes the bird.</text><text start="3319.58" dur="4.88">The egg white is the kind of unrenewable amino
acid resource it is using to develop itself.</text><text start="3324.46" dur="5.931">That it is using up an unrenewable resource
and it is producing metabolic waste that isn&apos;t</text><text start="3330.391" dur="4.708">being processed in its finite little space
in a way that is totally self-terminating.</text><text start="3335.099" dur="2.901">The little bird doesn&apos;t know it&apos;s inside of
an eggshell because it doesn&apos;t have a reference</text><text start="3338.0" dur="2.57">frame.</text><text start="3340.57" dur="2.92">If we were to anthropomorphize... which, of
course, the little bird is not doing this...</text><text start="3343.49" dur="5.15">but if we were to anthropomorphize being the
little bird embryo and they&apos;re developing</text><text start="3348.64" dur="5.189">and it recognized at a certain point, man,
I&apos;m running out of egg whites here and I&apos;m</text><text start="3353.829" dur="4.401">creating shit in my space, what am I going
to do?</text><text start="3358.23" dur="1.74">I don&apos;t know.</text><text start="3359.97" dur="1.0">Just keep on eating.</text><text start="3360.97" dur="1.5">I guess we&apos;ll figure it out later.</text><text start="3362.47" dur="1.48">Because what else can I do?</text><text start="3363.95" dur="1.19">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
You get to a certain point.</text><text start="3365.14" dur="1.16">Runs out of egg white.</text><text start="3366.3" dur="5.2">It just happens to be that evolution made
it such that the amount of egg white was exactly</text><text start="3371.5" dur="3.68">what it needed to be able to then be at a
place where it had a beak that could break</text><text start="3375.18" dur="4.03">free from the shell that could then also eat
seeds on the outside that its little developing</text><text start="3379.21" dur="3.97">GI tract and underdeveloped beak couldn&apos;t
have done.</text><text start="3383.18" dur="4.33">Now, it&apos;s eating seeds that its poop fertilizes
and it&apos;s part of this process.</text><text start="3387.51" dur="5.579">But the developmental phase of it was unsustainable
because it was a developmental phase.</text><text start="3393.089" dur="6.021">Just a fetus inside of a womb, if it continued
there forever, it would obviously kill the</text><text start="3399.11" dur="2.39">mom and kill itself.</text><text start="3401.5" dur="3.619">But it goes through this 40-week, for human
development, and then it goes through a discrete</text><text start="3405.119" dur="1.581">phase shift.</text><text start="3406.7" dur="4.099">The breaking out of the eggshell is different
than the development in the eggshell and different</text><text start="3410.799" dur="2.191">than the development afterwards.</text><text start="3412.99" dur="3.93">And the birth process is different than the
40 weeks of development in utero and then</text><text start="3416.92" dur="3.139">different than the post-umbilical development
afterwards.</text><text start="3420.059" dur="2.31">The same with the caterpillar to the chrysalis
to the butterfly.</text><text start="3422.369" dur="5.361">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I just saw all of these cases of developmental</text><text start="3427.73" dur="4.69">periods, where if you were to just take their
trajectory and forecast it forward, you would</text><text start="3432.42" dur="1.21">just see self-termination.</text><text start="3433.63" dur="3.81">But there was a forecast and then there was
a discrete phase shift.</text><text start="3437.44" dur="1.28">And it took a minute, right?</text><text start="3438.72" dur="5.77">The birth might take 50 hours or 20 hours
or whatever it takes and the chrysalis takes</text><text start="3444.49" dur="1.68">a little while.</text><text start="3446.17" dur="4.23">But I was getting this experience that all
the forecasting I was doing was a developmental</text><text start="3450.4" dur="2.25">period for humanity.</text><text start="3452.65" dur="2.82">There was a discrete phase shift that I couldn&apos;t
see possible.</text><text start="3455.47" dur="4.27">Of course, sometimes the baby dies in birth
or the mom dies in birth.</text><text start="3459.74" dur="2.809">It&apos;s not a guaranteed thing.</text><text start="3462.549" dur="6.471">And so how to not just look at changing the
shape of the curves, but how to look at what</text><text start="3469.02" dur="6.66">types of discrete phase shifts could occur
and what a world on the other side of certain</text><text start="3475.68" dur="4.409">phase shifts might look like and how to facilitate
that became a different way for me to think</text><text start="3480.089" dur="3.481">about the future than just a continuation
of these curves and trying to change the shape</text><text start="3483.57" dur="1.0">of it.</text><text start="3484.57" dur="1.549">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
But one of the things it did was...</text><text start="3486.119" dur="1.871">I had not studied discrete phase shifts.</text><text start="3487.99" dur="5.629">I hadn&apos;t studied how, in lots of systems,
you have a movement towards a certain kind</text><text start="3493.619" dur="4.48">of far from equilibrium point and then a discrete
phase shift to something totally different.</text><text start="3498.099" dur="4.061">I didn&apos;t even know that was a structure I
wasn&apos;t factoring when I thought I was forecasting</text><text start="3502.16" dur="1.0">well.</text><text start="3503.16" dur="4.99">So, I had a false sense of certainty based
on not understanding some phenomena, but understanding</text><text start="3508.15" dur="3.33">other ones well, but I didn&apos;t know the ones
I didn&apos;t know.</text><text start="3511.48" dur="8.52">That false sense of certainty had me thinking
from a moral place about depopulation strategies.</text><text start="3520.0" dur="7.78">One of the things that I find is so scary
about utilitarian calculus is how much...</text><text start="3527.78" dur="5.819">If my goal is harm reduction and I&apos;m willing
to commit some harm in a trolley problem to</text><text start="3533.599" dur="5.911">keep a worse harm from happening, but if I
get false certainty that X worse harm is for</text><text start="3539.51" dur="4.64">sure going to happen, it justifies me doing
super fucked up stuff so long as it&apos;s less.</text><text start="3544.15" dur="5.689">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I feel like, and I know from my own experience,</text><text start="3549.839" dur="5.891">it is really easy to come to catastrophic
certainties that just aren&apos;t true.</text><text start="3555.73" dur="3.37">I remember everybody&apos;s concern about Y2K.</text><text start="3559.1" dur="5.54">I remember the concern about the Cuban missile
crisis and 2012 and a zillion things like</text><text start="3564.64" dur="1.0">it.</text><text start="3565.64" dur="5.06">It&apos;s interesting how bad both our catastrophic
and our hopeful predictions are historically.</text><text start="3570.7" dur="4.59">It doesn&apos;t go the good or the bad way we think
it&apos;s going to go.</text><text start="3575.29" dur="5.539">And so I would love if the people who are
really concerned about the world issues would</text><text start="3580.829" dur="7.101">recognize that they end up having the same
premature certainty biases that the optimists</text><text start="3587.93" dur="1.5">have on the other side.</text><text start="3589.43" dur="4.22">That the Trump supporters and anti-Trumpers
have.</text><text start="3593.65" dur="5.159">And that it&apos;s a lack of a certain kind of
cognitive, emotional, spiritual maturity needed</text><text start="3598.809" dur="3.741">to just keep sitting with the uncertainty
of maybe it&apos;s all catastrophic, but maybe</text><text start="3602.55" dur="1.0">it isn&apos;t.</text><text start="3603.55" dur="2.36">And if maybe it isn&apos;t, maybe there&apos;s shit
you really should do and maybe you don&apos;t know</text><text start="3605.91" dur="2.5">what the right thing to do is.</text><text start="3608.41" dur="2.629">That&apos;s actually harder than just saying, wow,
it&apos;s all fucked.</text><text start="3611.039" dur="3.611">I&apos;m just going to be one of the mature people
who accepts it.</text><text start="3614.65" dur="2.77">It&apos;s harder to be like, I actually don&apos;t know.</text><text start="3617.42" dur="3.78">And so I&apos;m obligated to work on it as best
I can in the presence of still not knowing.</text><text start="3621.2" dur="2.94">Nate Hagens:
You did make me cry on our last podcast with</text><text start="3624.14" dur="4.43">your story about the plow and animism.</text><text start="3628.57" dur="2.969">This was really profound, what you just said.</text><text start="3631.539" dur="3.981">And I kind of agree with it because you&apos;re
describing kind of my place.</text><text start="3635.52" dur="7.33">I&apos;ve veered towards certainty at times, but
the more I know and the more I talk with people</text><text start="3642.85" dur="4.449">like you, there are lots of variables.</text><text start="3647.299" dur="7.52">The whole freaking thing is moving every day
and events change and our understandings change</text><text start="3654.819" dur="1.5">and I don&apos;t know what to do.</text><text start="3656.319" dur="2.8">I&apos;m reasonably confident what&apos;s not going
to happen.</text><text start="3659.119" dur="2.601">I don&apos;t know what&apos;s going to happen.</text><text start="3661.72" dur="6.48">My role is I want to pass the baton to more
prosocial humans that can take a decent chunk</text><text start="3668.2" dur="3.54">of this on board and play a role.</text><text start="3671.74" dur="4.18">The other thought I had is, when I was 15,
I was freaking watching Gilligan&apos;s Island</text><text start="3675.92" dur="4.899">and Scooby-Doo, so I already respected you
before this, but now I even have a higher</text><text start="3680.819" dur="4.581">level of respect for you that you were doing
this when you were 12 to 15.</text><text start="3685.4" dur="1.659">I just can&apos;t imagine that.</text><text start="3687.059" dur="3.491">I mean, I first started really caring about
this when I was like 31.</text><text start="3690.55" dur="5.42">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I was obviously homeschooled, exposed to certain</text><text start="3695.97" dur="1.819">things, which I think is pretty common for...</text><text start="3697.789" dur="3.81">I mean, anybody would respond to the things
they&apos;re exposed to.</text><text start="3701.599" dur="5.02">The earlier part of that journey was something
so random.</text><text start="3706.619" dur="4.281">My family was in a gas station in Iowa and
a...</text><text start="3710.9" dur="2.219">Actually, in Texas.</text><text start="3713.119" dur="3.291">We were on a trip.</text><text start="3716.41" dur="4.99">A tractor trailer pulled in and it was a cattle
truck.</text><text start="3721.4" dur="4.36">It was a taking cows from a factory farm to
slaughterhouse.</text><text start="3725.76" dur="1.67">The ones with the holes in the side for air.</text><text start="3727.43" dur="1.0">The ventilation holes.</text><text start="3728.43" dur="5.98">I went up and I looked in the holes and the
cow right near me was missing an eye.</text><text start="3734.41" dur="2.699">There was blood and abcess coming from it.</text><text start="3737.109" dur="1.7">It was a terrible stench.</text><text start="3738.809" dur="2.581">All the cows were obviously terrified.</text><text start="3741.39" dur="1.68">There was feces all over them.</text><text start="3743.07" dur="6.43">It was just like an Auschwitz scene, you know?</text><text start="3749.5" dur="4.72">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I grew up eating meat, including from factory</text><text start="3754.22" dur="1.0">farms.</text><text start="3755.22" dur="1.0">McDonald&apos;s, whatever.</text><text start="3756.22" dur="1.0">Just no cognizance.</text><text start="3757.22" dur="1.0">I just didn&apos;t put it together.</text><text start="3758.22" dur="2.04">But I also grew up loving animals.</text><text start="3760.26" dur="4.25">That cognitive dissonance that so many people
have where they don&apos;t get, wait, dog, cow,</text><text start="3764.51" dur="1.0">not that different.</text><text start="3765.51" dur="6.829">I asked my parents why those animals were
in that condition.</text><text start="3772.339" dur="6.101">They said, &quot;That&apos;s where the hamburgers come
from,&quot; and my world just broke.</text><text start="3778.44" dur="4.54">I never ate animals again after that day.</text><text start="3782.98" dur="2.45">I read Diet for A New America the next day.</text><text start="3785.43" dur="1.669">Starting the next day.</text><text start="3787.099" dur="3.121">And then I couldn&apos;t think about anything else.</text><text start="3790.22" dur="4.149">Because I&apos;m like, wait, we&apos;re just focused
on our own little life going well and there</text><text start="3794.369" dur="6.571">are billions of other sentient beings that
are just being completely fucking tortured</text><text start="3800.94" dur="2.57">and then murdered in a tortuous way.</text><text start="3803.51" dur="1.0">How can my...</text><text start="3804.51" dur="3.22">What&apos;s wrong with my species?</text><text start="3807.73" dur="3.93">How can I just be focused on my own personal
life and be stoked when that&apos;s happening?</text><text start="3811.66" dur="1.0">I can&apos;t.</text><text start="3812.66" dur="5.659">You&apos;d have to be so disconnected that you&apos;re
a sociopath in a way to be just be focused</text><text start="3818.319" dur="1.361">on your own life and stoked.</text><text start="3819.68" dur="2.82">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
That was the beginning of feeling very suicidal</text><text start="3822.5" dur="2.42">about these things for me.</text><text start="3824.92" dur="3.76">Because I&apos;m like, this planet is...</text><text start="3828.68" dur="1.429">The way that we&apos;re operating is so fucked.</text><text start="3830.109" dur="1.551">I just can&apos;t be complicit with it.</text><text start="3831.66" dur="1.0">I want out.</text><text start="3832.66" dur="1.47">It doesn&apos;t make sense.</text><text start="3834.13" dur="4.26">And then I&apos;m like, well, that doesn&apos;t help
any of the animals and so I can&apos;t do that.</text><text start="3838.39" dur="4.09">And then I&apos;m like, but I also can&apos;t just feel
like my life is a success with that being</text><text start="3842.48" dur="1.0">the case.</text><text start="3843.48" dur="5.619">I can&apos;t kill myself, but for my life to succeed,
theirs has to be better.</text><text start="3849.099" dur="1.661">So, how do we fix factory farms?</text><text start="3850.76" dur="1.609">Of course, that was the first one.</text><text start="3852.369" dur="4.071">Then, it went from factory farms to also whaling
and then overfishing and then clear cutting</text><text start="3856.44" dur="1.0">of the forest.</text><text start="3857.44" dur="1.94">And then it started to look at extreme poverty
of people.</text><text start="3859.38" dur="1.179">It just grew.</text><text start="3860.559" dur="9.74">But it&apos;s that insight of like, there is no
way to actually be sane in the world and see</text><text start="3870.299" dur="3.681">it clearly and then just hold our life separate
from everything else.</text><text start="3873.98" dur="8.52">The only way through for me is actually, how
do we make a more sane, kind, just world?</text><text start="3882.5" dur="5.859">I think different people get exposed to things
at different points, but if they have some</text><text start="3888.359" dur="5.151">time and space to feel, it&apos;s a very natural
human process.</text><text start="3893.51" dur="5.44">Nate Hagens:
Thank you for that.</text><text start="3898.95" dur="2.03">I feel much the same way.</text><text start="3900.98" dur="4.859">I think I&apos;m older than you, but I matured
at a later age than you.</text><text start="3905.839" dur="4.561">And I think maybe that&apos;s why we&apos;ve formed
a deep friendship.</text><text start="3910.4" dur="6.459">Because, first of all, we care about the future
and we want to influence things to the best</text><text start="3916.859" dur="3.901">of our skills and our networks and our knowledge.</text><text start="3920.76" dur="5.97">But I think it feels good to meet another
human who is aware of all these existential</text><text start="3926.73" dur="8.389">risks and the trajectory and the probability
distribution of various futures and just admits,</text><text start="3935.119" dur="1.371">yeah, I don&apos;t know.</text><text start="3936.49" dur="5.44">It&apos;s all awful and I don&apos;t know what to do,
but let&apos;s roll up our sleeves and find some</text><text start="3941.93" dur="1.77">paths forward.</text><text start="3943.7" dur="7.48">Just the existence of that, another human
being feeling that, is so buoying to my psychology</text><text start="3951.18" dur="1.639">and my feeling.</text><text start="3952.819" dur="2.79">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="3955.609" dur="9.73">I think when the people say, hey, you&apos;re being
falsely optimistic, they&apos;re actually needing</text><text start="3965.339" dur="5.941">to feel or longing to feel met in the tragic
place they&apos;re in.</text><text start="3971.28" dur="3.22">I think you and I have talked about this before.</text><text start="3974.5" dur="7.869">Mark Gaffney is a friend who, the first time
talked, after it was clear we resonated for</text><text start="3982.369" dur="1.771">a while, he asked me if I was post-tragic.</text><text start="3984.14" dur="1.47">I asked him what the model was.</text><text start="3985.61" dur="5.31">He was saying there&apos;s a kind of pre-tragic
optimism that people will have, where they</text><text start="3990.92" dur="3.62">have ideals that have not yet been shattered
on the reality of the world.</text><text start="3994.54" dur="1.89">We call it naivete.</text><text start="3996.43" dur="3.78">And then there&apos;s the encountering the tragedy
of the world and having the ideals shatter</text><text start="4000.21" dur="2.22">and there&apos;s a cynicism that can emerge there.</text><text start="4002.43" dur="7.2">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And then there is a post-tragic place that</text><text start="4009.63" dur="4.35">is committed to being in service to the sacredness
of life whether you can succeed or not.</text><text start="4013.98" dur="1.42">It&apos;s still the right way to...</text><text start="4015.4" dur="3.719">It&apos;s still the right hill to die on.</text><text start="4019.119" dur="4.572">That doesn&apos;t even need the certainty of success
to have it be the right sacred thing to be</text><text start="4023.691" dur="2.098">living that way.</text><text start="4025.789" dur="6.971">And then that also realizes that there is
a false certainty of the tragic place.</text><text start="4032.76" dur="2.63">Just like there was a false certainty of the
naive place.</text><text start="4035.39" dur="3.83">And that the universe is much bigger than
both of those false certainties.</text><text start="4039.22" dur="3.96">And so then it says, cognizant of all the
tragedy and cognizant of all the reason to</text><text start="4043.18" dur="6.169">be cynical and holding that, we&apos;re still going
to look for solutions and still also operate</text><text start="4049.349" dur="5.671">with the sacredness of life at the center.</text><text start="4055.02" dur="1.2">I think that&apos;s the task.</text><text start="4056.22" dur="2.329">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
It&apos;s so interesting because you and I both</text><text start="4058.549" dur="6.57">know we could solve all of these things, make
an economic system that doesn&apos;t have an embedded</text><text start="4065.119" dur="7.391">growth obligation and closed-loop materials
economy powered by regenerative energy and</text><text start="4072.51" dur="5.76">overcome war and bind AI and biotech, and
then a solar flare just takes us all out in</text><text start="4078.27" dur="2.549">a way that we can&apos;t control for shit.</text><text start="4080.819" dur="4.49">And so there is something about just sitting
also with the fragility and the impermanence</text><text start="4085.309" dur="3.341">of the whole thing that we just have to hold.</text><text start="4088.65" dur="7.07">When people think about how thin the crust
of the Earth is, it&apos;s like a ball of lava</text><text start="4095.72" dur="4.7">with a little bitty boat of a thin crust and
a tiny, thin atmosphere in a bunch of vacuum</text><text start="4100.42" dur="3.0">outer space right next to a sun that can do
solar flares.</text><text start="4103.42" dur="2.55">You&apos;re like, we&apos;re here at all.</text><text start="4105.97" dur="1.01">We&apos;re here at all.</text><text start="4106.98" dur="1.0">That&apos;s amazing.</text><text start="4107.98" dur="1.549">Who knows for how long it will be?</text><text start="4109.529" dur="5.58">How do we both serve the continuation of life
and be with the profundity and beauty of it</text><text start="4115.109" dur="3.261">in its fragility at the same time?</text><text start="4118.37" dur="3.639">Nate Hagens:
I don&apos;t really feel like going back to the</text><text start="4122.009" dur="5.531">egregore and attention seconds and paper clip
maximizer now.</text><text start="4127.54" dur="2.969">If we&apos;re going to do that, we&apos;re going to-</text><text start="4130.509" dur="3.31">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I think we can do that next time.</text><text start="4133.819" dur="1.0">Nate Hagens:
Okay.</text><text start="4134.819" dur="8.811">Given everything that you&apos;ve just shared,
looking ahead to next time, what would you</text><text start="4143.63" dur="7.58">like to say to the listeners to get them on
board this way of thinking and to pay attention</text><text start="4151.21" dur="8.399">to our next conversation that we&apos;re going
to ultimately try to get to the criteria for</text><text start="4159.609" dur="1.0">civilization?</text><text start="4160.609" dur="9.021">In my opinion, that&apos;s always two conversations
or two things you need to check.</text><text start="4169.63" dur="3.959">One is what is conceptually, technologically,
materially possible?</text><text start="4173.589" dur="4.171">And the other is how do we get there from
where we are now?</text><text start="4177.76" dur="3.01">Those are separate questions.</text><text start="4180.77" dur="3.94">Yeah, Daniel.</text><text start="4184.71" dur="3.64">You&apos;ve thrown me for a loop here.</text><text start="4188.35" dur="2.739">I wanted to talk about cognitive-</text><text start="4191.089" dur="1.46">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I have some thoughts.</text><text start="4192.549" dur="2.701">Nate Hagens:
... material economy and mesh with your worldview</text><text start="4195.25" dur="2.82">and now I&apos;m at a deeper place.</text><text start="4198.07" dur="1.069">Help me out.</text><text start="4199.139" dur="2.641">Give me your thoughts.</text><text start="4201.78" dur="5.169">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Some of the primary frames that people are</text><text start="4206.949" dur="7.551">related to in from the larger systems that
have developed is they&apos;re seen as consumers</text><text start="4214.5" dur="7.87">or customers in the market and they are seen
as voters, if they&apos;re in the US or another</text><text start="4222.37" dur="4.14">democratic country, for the state.</text><text start="4226.51" dur="4.31">They&apos;re going to buy a product or not buy
a product.</text><text start="4230.82" dur="3.87">They&apos;re going to vote yes or no on a proposition
or vote for this candidate or that.</text><text start="4234.69" dur="5.029">It&apos;s an extremely constrained set of choices
that doesn&apos;t require them being creative or</text><text start="4239.719" dur="3.581">them understanding well.</text><text start="4243.3" dur="8.939">It&apos;s a supply side forcing, it&apos;s an institutional
forcing, of the choice to be very constrained.</text><text start="4252.239" dur="4.021">So, of course, people have been conditioned
that way for so long that they don&apos;t even</text><text start="4256.26" dur="2.939">realize that they&apos;re just being conditioned
that way and that it&apos;s not really deep or</text><text start="4259.199" dur="1.601">authentic choice.</text><text start="4260.8" dur="3.36">And so, of course, if we&apos;re trying to get
people to vote for us rather than the other</text><text start="4264.16" dur="6.0">guy or buy our product because our company
is going to solve the industry&apos;s problem or</text><text start="4270.16" dur="5.329">whatever it is, we don&apos;t have to get them
to make sense well.</text><text start="4275.489" dur="5.201">In fact, we actually just want to give them
quick certainty and outrage to both join our</text><text start="4280.69" dur="1.52">side and get other people to join our side.</text><text start="4282.21" dur="2.43">We&apos;ll do the sense-making for you.</text><text start="4284.64" dur="3.74">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Neither you or I are trying to do that.</text><text start="4288.38" dur="4.67">We&apos;re not saying go vote for a specific party
or a specific proposition or go purchase a</text><text start="4293.05" dur="1.0">thing.</text><text start="4294.05" dur="3.95">We&apos;re saying there is a deeper way of being
able to make sense of how what seems like</text><text start="4298.0" dur="3.93">a lot of different issues in the world are
interconnected, where understanding that gives</text><text start="4301.93" dur="7.11">us a different possibility space with which
to think about how to forward.</text><text start="4309.04" dur="5.83">So, it&apos;s not oriented to immediate political
action in the same way.</text><text start="4314.87" dur="3.01">That doesn&apos;t mean that it&apos;s not oriented to
action, but in a different way.</text><text start="4317.88" dur="1.0">In a deeper way.</text><text start="4318.88" dur="2.88">But it is also much more two-marshmallow.</text><text start="4321.76" dur="1.77">It requires a lot more of the people.</text><text start="4323.53" dur="3.32">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And so a couple things I want to say in terms</text><text start="4326.85" dur="5.18">of where we go next time when we&apos;re sharing
cognitive models about what about the relationship</text><text start="4332.03" dur="5.12">between our infrastructure and our social
structures and our cultures and worldview</text><text start="4337.15" dur="5.319">or superstructure and the biosphere and the
nature of the exponential curves and technology...</text><text start="4342.469" dur="5.061">What about those things causes which kinds
of problems and what would necessary and sufficient</text><text start="4347.53" dur="4.439">design criteria of a better economic system
or a better supply chain or a better culture,</text><text start="4351.969" dur="2.971">educational system, or legal system look like?</text><text start="4354.94" dur="1.469">We have to figure that stuff out.</text><text start="4356.409" dur="2.08">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Everything that we&apos;ve talked about today that</text><text start="4358.489" dur="6.611">we didn&apos;t intend to talk about is from where
we approach figuring those things out.</text><text start="4365.1" dur="1.96">Where it&apos;s not against the bad guys.</text><text start="4367.06" dur="2.47">It is for the thriving of life.</text><text start="4369.53" dur="7.77">It&apos;s not premature certainty of either the
naive possibility or the cynical impossibility,</text><text start="4377.3" dur="4.36">but something that has been through both of
those and holds a deeper humility about how</text><text start="4381.66" dur="6.729">much is in the unknown unknowns set, including
possible solutions.</text><text start="4388.389" dur="7.821">It&apos;s a place that doesn&apos;t think that we get
real security on a little planet with a thin</text><text start="4396.21" dur="3.32">biosphere floating next to a sun that does
coronal mass ejections.</text><text start="4399.53" dur="1.71">We just don&apos;t get that thing.</text><text start="4401.24" dur="5.34">There is a different emotional way of relating,
where the driver of all of it is the prima</text><text start="4406.58" dur="4.1">facie, the inherent sacredness of life that
happens when you chill the fuck out over all</text><text start="4410.68" dur="3.48">the other agendas and disconnects and are
just present with it.</text><text start="4414.16" dur="9.19">Those are the places where, if you come from
there, the sense-making and the activity is</text><text start="4423.35" dur="2.49">differently motivated and differently informed.</text><text start="4425.84" dur="2.95">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Now, understanding the models is still really</text><text start="4428.79" dur="1.0">important.</text><text start="4429.79" dur="5.31">This is heart, will, mind all working together.</text><text start="4435.1" dur="3.16">It&apos;s pretty easy to see that any two of those
three don&apos;t work.</text><text start="4438.26" dur="9.55">You get mind and heart and no will and you
get really smart, caring academics who feel</text><text start="4447.81" dur="4.429">broken and hopeless at the impossibility of
the world.</text><text start="4452.239" dur="5.261">You get heart and will without deep mental
frames and you get activists who are willing</text><text start="4457.5" dur="4.71">to go put their life at risk to chain themselves
to a boat or whatever, but they don&apos;t know</text><text start="4462.21" dur="3.91">how to think through strategy at the scope
of what has to change.</text><text start="4466.12" dur="4.34">You put will and mind together but without
heart where there&apos;s narrow value systems and</text><text start="4470.46" dur="3.199">you get the kind of sociopathic rule that
currently runs the world.</text><text start="4473.659" dur="4.281">That knows how to be highly strategic, knows
how to be highly agentic, but to serve some</text><text start="4477.94" dur="2.12">narrow interest at the expense of somebody
else.</text><text start="4480.06" dur="2.9">It takes all three of those together.</text><text start="4482.96" dur="4.39">And so what we&apos;re going to be talking about
next time is some of the strategic frames</text><text start="4487.35" dur="3.18">or the theoretical frames that inform better
strategy.</text><text start="4490.53" dur="3.84">And not a specific strategy, but a kind of
meta-strategy.</text><text start="4494.37" dur="3.91">Meaning in whatever domain one happens to
be working in as the situation changes.</text><text start="4498.28" dur="1.98">That&apos;s where the theoretical frameworks come
in.</text><text start="4500.26" dur="2.86">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I think it was Bertrand Russell...</text><text start="4503.12" dur="1.68">I don&apos;t remember...</text><text start="4504.8" dur="12.12">Who said something to the effect of, if the
only value of knowledge was its immediate,</text><text start="4516.92" dur="6.04">clear utility, then mechanics would be the
only thing really worth studying.</text><text start="4522.96" dur="3.63">The reason one studies philosophy is not so
much what you immediately do with it but what</text><text start="4526.59" dur="1.0">it can do to you.</text><text start="4527.59" dur="4.69">What it can do to you in the way that you
relate to all information and all situations</text><text start="4532.28" dur="1.64">from a deeper place.</text><text start="4533.92" dur="4.89">So, some of the philosophic inquiry that we
go into is not that someone now knows, okay,</text><text start="4538.81" dur="4.19">now I know how to fix climate change or the
American democracy or Facebook.</text><text start="4543.0" dur="6.6">It&apos;s, now, I&apos;m perceiving the world with more
nuance and more complexity and from a different</text><text start="4549.6" dur="5.76">place, whereby maybe the local PTA issue that
I&apos;m about to deal with, I&apos;ll have new insights</text><text start="4555.36" dur="4.1">on.</text><text start="4559.46" dur="1.34">All the things still needed tending.</text><text start="4560.8" dur="1.189">All the local things need tending.</text><text start="4561.989" dur="2.011">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
There will be some people who are listening</text><text start="4564.0" dur="3.86">who are institutional...</text><text start="4567.86" dur="4.18">who work at major institutions, who are oriented
to how do we change the financial system and</text><text start="4572.04" dur="2.349">legal system and regulate tech.</text><text start="4574.389" dur="4.631">Most of the people won&apos;t be working in those
domains, but that doesn&apos;t mean that it&apos;s irrelevant</text><text start="4579.02" dur="1.81">to understand the world we live in better.</text><text start="4580.83" dur="3.86">There&apos;s a relevance to have a better understanding
of the world even if you don&apos;t know what to</text><text start="4584.69" dur="4.74">do with it exactly because it can help you
perceive differently the situations that you&apos;re</text><text start="4589.43" dur="1.64">in and where you can do something with it.</text><text start="4591.07" dur="5.28">So, when we get into these frameworks next
time, it&apos;s not to give certainty about catastrophe.</text><text start="4596.35" dur="5.38">It&apos;s to understand the principles that are
driving it well enough that you can see applications</text><text start="4601.73" dur="6.9">of them in all kinds of domains, think about
those domains better, and start to get a sense</text><text start="4608.63" dur="3.759">of what adequate solutions at scale might
entail.</text><text start="4612.389" dur="2.471">Nate Hagens:
Excellent.</text><text start="4614.86" dur="2.58">I really look forward to that.</text><text start="4617.44" dur="5.549">I had COVID, we were traveling, so this was
a big gap, but maybe we can do that next conversation</text><text start="4622.989" dur="1.391">at the end of August ish.</text><text start="4624.38" dur="3.64">I know you&apos;re also traveling.</text><text start="4628.02" dur="5.52">This conversation was completely unexpected
and was like an everlasting marshmallow, so</text><text start="4633.54" dur="4.139">I thank you for your wisdom and grace.</text><text start="4637.679" dur="1.801">Yeah.</text><text start="4639.48" dur="7.82">I really value you as a fellow traveler, as
a friend, and let&apos;s keep going, my friend.</text><text start="4647.3" dur="4.689">Nate Hagens:
If you enjoyed or learned from this episode</text><text start="4651.989" dur="5.271">of The Great Simplification, please subscribe
to us on your favorite podcast platform and</text><text start="4657.26" dur="4.83">visit thegreatsimplification.com for more
information on future releases.</text></transcript>