<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="0.0" dur="6.06">Here is the long awaited fourth installment
in a series with Daniel Schmachtenberger.</text><text start="6.06" dur="7.92">We dive deeper into the nuances of humans
with our relationship with energy, materials</text><text start="13.98" dur="1.74">and technology.</text><text start="15.72" dur="6.96">How does technology intensify the multipolar
trap on a world order based on growth?</text><text start="22.68" dur="5.4">Is there a way out or could global solutions
just make the problem worse?</text><text start="28.08" dur="7.38">We closed this fourth conversation queuing
up what our eventual goal was, which is a</text><text start="35.46" dur="7.62">what to do framework on bend and not break
for society in coming decades.</text><text start="43.62" dur="3.42">Once again, here is Daniel Schmachtenberger.</text><text start="58.5" dur="2.58">We got really sidetracked 
on the last conversation, </text><text start="61.08" dur="3.48">and I&apos;m going to try to be a task master here</text><text start="64.56" dur="5.34">to keep us on topic, but with you and me,
who knows where this will go.</text><text start="70.44" dur="8.28">So here is my intent for this conversation,
this is part four of a series called Bend</text><text start="78.72" dur="7.56">Not Break, which is the ultimate intent of
framing our macroeconomic human predicament,</text><text start="86.94" dur="2.94">understanding the game board of the constraints </text><text start="89.88" dur="2.88">and challenges, which then 
inform the opportunities,</text><text start="92.76" dur="8.46">so that we can navigate coming centuries and
educate, inform and inspire more humans to</text><text start="101.22" dur="3.6">play a role at various scales of the challenges
we face.</text><text start="106.8" dur="5.46">So if you don&apos;t mind, I&apos;m just going to briefly
recap our first conversations.</text><text start="112.26" dur="6.18">Our first conversation you kind of interviewed
me and we talked about the energy, money,</text><text start="118.44" dur="8.46">economic growth basis of modern early 21st
century society and how we got here and our</text><text start="126.9" dur="8.04">dependence on fossil hydrocarbons, how we
paper over some of our limits with increased</text><text start="134.94" dur="5.04">monetary claims and what are the drivers of
growth.</text><text start="139.98" dur="9.84">The second, you talked about the maximum power,
which is that organisms and ecosystems in</text><text start="149.82" dur="7.86">nature self-organize to access energy gradients
and human societies are also very similar,</text><text start="157.68" dur="7.26">you talked about hyper agents and some other
fundamental aspects, kind of building blocks</text><text start="164.94" dur="0.66">of your narrative.</text><text start="166.2" dur="10.8">And the last conversation was intended to
talk about different meta macroeconomic framings</text><text start="177.0" dur="3.36">of how everything fits 
together, energy, materials, </text><text start="180.36" dur="4.56">technology, money, human behavior, but instead</text><text start="184.92" dur="9.54">we ended up going down a very interesting
and personal track on why we prefer certainty,</text><text start="194.46" dur="8.76">why being scared about the future leads us,
hopefully, to a post tragic place where we</text><text start="203.22" dur="4.8">can understand our difficult reality and still
be inspired to play a role.</text><text start="208.02" dur="8.64">And we really had a beautiful and almost intimate
conversation, but it wasn&apos;t what I had intended.</text><text start="216.66" dur="12.18">So here we are today and what I would like
to do today is the global economy is running</text><text start="228.84" dur="6.96">into lots of risks and headwinds and we read
things in the news every day about the Bank</text><text start="235.8" dur="3.6">of England and the German energy situation.</text><text start="239.4" dur="8.46">And I want to fly up high enough to explain
what is happening because the standard story</text><text start="247.86" dur="7.02">taught in macroeconomics in the world&apos;s business
schools and colleges doesn&apos;t really have an</text><text start="254.88" dur="7.92">explanatory story that makes sense of where
we are and where we might go forward.</text><text start="262.8" dur="10.5">Now, I&apos;ve developed a story, which is that
humans in aggregate are functioning as a kind</text><text start="273.3" dur="8.28">of blind amoeba, or a super organism that
self-organizes.</text><text start="281.58" dur="9.54">Because we use the market as the arbiter of
our decisions that everything is outsourced</text><text start="291.12" dur="4.86">to this exponentially growing system that </text><text start="297.66" dur="4.98">individuals, families, small 
businesses, corporations,</text><text start="302.64" dur="7.86">nation states, all make decisions to optimize
growing profits, an accumulation of wealth.</text><text start="310.5" dur="7.92">And if you aggregate that all, it&apos;s all tethered
to using energy because GDP is historically</text><text start="318.42" dur="8.52">and currently around 99% correlated with energy
use and about a 100% correlated with material</text><text start="326.94" dur="8.94">use like copper or lithium or plastics or
concrete or wood, that all that together is</text><text start="335.88" dur="2.46">growing at around the same rate that GDP is.</text><text start="338.34" dur="7.5">And that we create monetary overlays on this
whole system and that system is not being</text><text start="345.84" dur="7.2">controlled by billionaires or by politicians,
but it is kind of got its own emergent momentum</text><text start="353.04" dur="0.78">and metabolism.</text><text start="353.82" dur="5.88">And so we&apos;re in this like runaway train and
we&apos;re shoveling fuel into the engine.</text><text start="359.7" dur="10.92">And so from that vantage point, we will keep
growing until something breaks in the ecosystems</text><text start="370.62" dur="11.58">of the world or we will stop growing and then
we have a geopolitical social response to</text><text start="382.2" dur="7.44">a smaller pie where everyone has less, or
on average everyone has less, and so this</text><text start="389.64" dur="6.54">is a blind super organism that none of us
directly control.</text><text start="396.18" dur="6.0">So that&apos;s kind of my overview, we could get
into more detail there, but what I&apos;d like</text><text start="402.18" dur="5.16">to do today is have you unpack your version
of that narrative.</text><text start="407.34" dur="2.7">How does everything fit together?</text><text start="410.04" dur="6.48">If you fly up high enough and look down at
how humans arrived to this point, how do energy</text><text start="416.52" dur="9.3">materials, money, behavior, technology fit
together and how does that inform the possible</text><text start="425.82" dur="5.1">choices and changes and governance and constraints
of the future?</text><text start="430.92" dur="1.62">That was a mouthful.</text><text start="432.54" dur="1.26">Does that make sense?</text><text start="433.8" dur="1.86">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="435.66" dur="7.56">I think you and I got connected because friend
connected us who recognized that we were both</text><text start="443.22" dur="6.24">trying to look at some of the dynamics that
were underneath the various types of risks</text><text start="449.46" dur="0.84">humanity faces.</text><text start="450.3" dur="7.86">And not look at biodiversity loss and species
extinction and ocean acidification and climate</text><text start="458.16" dur="5.64">change and all the planetary boundaries and
war and supply chain risks as separate issues,</text><text start="463.8" dur="2.34">but see what they have in common that is driving
them.</text><text start="466.14" dur="5.94">You talked about this in terms of dynamics
of the super organism and I talked about them</text><text start="472.08" dur="5.04">as generator functions of catastrophic risk,
but I think we&apos;re looking at the same thing</text><text start="477.12" dur="4.5">using different lenses and at this point our
lenses have inter-informed each other.</text><text start="482.7" dur="5.88">I think it&apos;s pretty easy to see that all the
problems that we look at in the world, one</text><text start="488.58" dur="4.5">of the lenses they have in common involves
the system of macroeconomics that the world</text><text start="493.08" dur="0.54">is working with.</text><text start="493.62" dur="6.72">Meaning that there&apos;s perverse incentive, that
what generates profit for a company or a country</text><text start="500.34" dur="6.84">or an individual often does so at the expense
of another company or country or other individuals</text><text start="507.18" dur="1.68">or the environment as a whole.</text><text start="509.46" dur="7.92">And so then when that profit equals not just
security and survivability but also game theoretic</text><text start="517.38" dur="6.72">advantage of their ability to influence their
own fate in the world and whatever mechanisms</text><text start="524.1" dur="5.46">they use to generate more profit than somebody
else, i.e better technology, that that can</text><text start="529.56" dur="5.76">be re-engineered and employed by others, so
you get these kind of races.</text><text start="535.86" dur="4.56">Whether it&apos;s a arms race militarily or just
market wise, you can think of it as a kind</text><text start="540.42" dur="6.96">of arms race to be able to convert the natural
world into profit faster and increase relative</text><text start="547.38" dur="0.9">game theory.</text><text start="550.14" dur="6.42">The profit is... modern economic theory is
that that profit is a measure of production,</text><text start="556.56" dur="6.36">how much value we added to the raw resources
and that we only profit if we produce goods</text><text start="562.92" dur="3.72">and services that other people want to buy,
which means that it benefits their life because</text><text start="566.64" dur="2.94">we solve some legitimate problem, therefore,
GDP equals good.</text><text start="570.6" dur="8.34">Therefore, more total revenue means more problem
solved for more people, and more total profit</text><text start="578.94" dur="4.8">means that we were able to operate efficiently
and the profit measure equals the amount of</text><text start="583.74" dur="2.04">value that we added that is being monetized.</text><text start="586.32" dur="6.42">That&apos;s not totally untrue and we can see in
the Pinker and Hans Rosling and other kind</text><text start="592.74" dur="3.54">of narratives the true part of that, none
of us want to go back to the pre-Novocaine</text><text start="596.28" dur="3.72">pre-pain killer world, those parts are true.</text><text start="600.0" dur="6.9">But it&apos;s also true that profit is not just
a measure of added production but of extraction</text><text start="606.9" dur="5.16">and externalization and that those profit
numbers also have added extraction externalization</text><text start="612.06" dur="2.52">and not just the profit but even the revenue
numbers.</text><text start="614.58" dur="6.36">As you mentioned with oil, the way we price
oil is how much does it cost us to extract</text><text start="620.94" dur="0.18">it?</text><text start="621.12" dur="4.32">It costs a certain amount to get a barrel
out, now we have to sell it for more than</text><text start="625.44" dur="3.48">that, but we can&apos;t sell it for a whole lot
more because somebody else will undercut us</text><text start="628.92" dur="5.76">price-wise and so it&apos;s a cost of extraction
plus a tiny margin determined by competition.</text><text start="635.4" dur="6.0">And that does not include the cost of what
the environment took to make the oil if we</text><text start="641.4" dur="3.78">were going to make it ourselves so we weren&apos;t
using up a unrenewable resource.</text><text start="645.18" dur="5.1">And it doesn&apos;t include the cost of the harm
to the environment that happens in the burning</text><text start="650.28" dur="4.32">of it, the manufacturer, the refinement, all
the aspects of the pollution and the waste.</text><text start="654.6" dur="4.26">And this is obviously true not just for oil
but for every single aspect of the materials</text><text start="658.86" dur="0.42">economy.</text><text start="659.28" dur="4.56">Nate Hagens:
An ecological economist would say that GDP</text><text start="663.84" dur="2.94">counts the goods but doesn&apos;t include the bads.</text><text start="666.78" dur="7.62">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, I think simplistically GDP is... actually,</text><text start="674.4" dur="6.06">there&apos;s a really nice way to talk about this,
which is there is a kind of meta perverse</text><text start="680.46" dur="3.12">incentive that everybody has, economically </text><text start="683.58" dur="3.72">and technologically and 
politically, but particularly</text><text start="687.3" dur="7.56">economically, which is to overemphasize the
opportunity and under-emphasize the risk of</text><text start="694.86" dur="1.56">any new technology or new venture.</text><text start="697.38" dur="2.82">And let&apos;s particularly look at new technologies.</text><text start="702.24" dur="8.16">So let&apos;s say I&apos;m going to develop AI for a
particular purpose, or it could be biotech</text><text start="710.4" dur="8.28">or whatever, any new technology, if I emphasize,
for this AI, what the amazing opportunity</text><text start="718.68" dur="5.04">is, it&apos;s going to allow us to do protein folding
stuff that will solve cancer, then of course</text><text start="723.72" dur="3.36">everybody wants us to move as fast as possible
because people are going to have family members</text><text start="727.08" dur="4.44">that have cancer and we&apos;re going to make a
lot of profit associated with solving some</text><text start="731.52" dur="1.38">real legitimate problems that people care
about.</text><text start="733.56" dur="3.9">If we focus on the risk side too much, &quot;But
if we can apply this to protein folding that</text><text start="737.46" dur="6.12">can solve cancer, is this also going to be
used for bio weapons that intentionally, or</text><text start="743.58" dur="4.02">even via lab leaks having created those monstrous
things, end up wiping out everybody?&quot;</text><text start="747.6" dur="5.22">Or could it also be applied to developing
better chemical weapons or a million other</text><text start="752.82" dur="0.54">bad things?</text><text start="753.36" dur="6.78">If I say, &quot;All right, I don&apos;t want to advance
this technology for its opportunity without</text><text start="760.14" dur="4.14">really understanding the risk landscape well,&quot;
because let&apos;s say that I&apos;m developing it for</text><text start="764.28" dur="3.96">this positive purpose, but now that I&apos;ve developed
it&apos;s out there, the barrier of entry for anyone</text><text start="768.24" dur="3.18">else to use it for other purposes is way,
way lower.</text><text start="771.42" dur="4.74">So it&apos;s not just what purpose am I developing
it for, but what purpose is this new easier</text><text start="776.16" dur="3.3">capacity usable for by anyone who has any
incentive to use it.</text><text start="780.06" dur="5.04">If I say &quot;I want to do a really comprehensive
risk assessment and ensure that the combination</text><text start="785.1" dur="4.44">of how we move the technology forward with
the regulatory landscape and the safety&apos;s</text><text start="789.54" dur="5.16">put in place is actually net good for the
world,&quot; then if someone else doesn&apos;t do that</text><text start="794.7" dur="4.02">and they just say, &quot;Oh, the risks aren&apos;t that
bad, the opportunities are awesome,&quot; they</text><text start="798.72" dur="4.44">race ahead, they get first mover advantage
in the market and they will end up getting</text><text start="803.16" dur="4.92">the network effects of whatever kind of Metcalfe
law benefits happen.</text><text start="808.08" dur="6.24">And so they just win economically, and they
won&apos;t financially responsible for the harms</text><text start="814.32" dur="7.62">that it causes protected by limited liability
corporation type laws and things like that.</text><text start="821.94" dur="4.86">So the corporations will get to privatize
the benefits and socialize the losses and</text><text start="826.8" dur="3.36">as a result, nobody is incented to do good
thorough risk assessment.</text><text start="830.16" dur="6.84">Everyone is incented to do some kind of plausible
deniability box checking risk assessment that</text><text start="837.0" dur="5.34">is not really a deep or honest risk assessment
and then claim that they couldn&apos;t have predicted</text><text start="842.34" dur="3.24">that bad thing could have happened or their
hands were tied while they were following</text><text start="845.58" dur="3.84">the perverse incentive associated with the
profit metric.</text><text start="849.42" dur="4.08">Nate Hagens:
But if we did appropriate risk analysis for</text><text start="853.5" dur="6.84">glyphosate or the examples you just said,
if we did, if we tested everything, we would</text><text start="860.34" dur="1.68">make no products at all pretty much.</text><text start="862.02" dur="3.06">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
We would make a lot less products, the world</text><text start="865.08" dur="6.48">would be better comprehensively and we wouldn&apos;t
be facing the break issues that you&apos;re focused</text><text start="871.56" dur="0.12">on.</text><text start="871.68" dur="2.4">It&apos;s just the game theory of how to do that&apos;s
very hard.</text><text start="874.08" dur="2.04">It&apos;s not just the game theory is hard.</text><text start="876.12" dur="4.08">The game theory is hard because unless you
can make sure that everybody does those risk</text><text start="880.2" dur="2.34">assessments, then you don&apos;t...</text><text start="882.54" dur="5.16">If you do the risk assessment, you just lose,
and so what it actually means is the more</text><text start="887.7" dur="1.62">ethical players have less influence.</text><text start="889.32" dur="6.3">And so currently the multipolar trap is, &quot;Well
I think I&apos;m more ethical than the other guy</text><text start="895.62" dur="4.26">building the AI or building the CRISPR or
whatever, and since there is a race and the</text><text start="899.88" dur="4.62">first mover advantage is significant, I have
to win the race to be able to steer the field.</text><text start="904.5" dur="5.52">So I&apos;m going to go ahead and cut corners on
risk assessment because if I don&apos;t, an even</text><text start="910.02" dur="1.5">less ethical actor will run everything.</text><text start="911.52" dur="3.48">Nate Hagens:
Well my view is the super organism doesn&apos;t</text><text start="915.0" dur="1.92">include ethics and its decisions.</text><text start="916.92" dur="4.26">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So we&apos;ll get to the... so the super organism</text><text start="921.18" dur="4.92">is like if you take this multipolar trap that
has all of these different actors in a race</text><text start="926.1" dur="3.24">with each other, you would say that&apos;s a property
of the super organism.</text><text start="929.34" dur="5.94">Now we&apos;re dropping down a layer to say that
property of the super organism is what makes</text><text start="935.28" dur="4.32">it to where all these players don&apos;t feel like
they actually have the capability of doing</text><text start="939.6" dur="3.24">the ethical thing because they will just be
kind of priced out and-</text><text start="942.84" dur="3.48">Nate Hagens:
Even if they&apos;re ethical individual humans,</text><text start="946.32" dur="6.42">their position within the economic hierarchy
doesn&apos;t allow them to express their ethical</text><text start="952.74" dur="0.3">view.</text><text start="953.04" dur="2.46">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="955.5" dur="8.46">In general, I think we talked about this once,
that if we look at China&apos;s taking of Tibet</text><text start="963.96" dur="1.08">or  </text><text start="967.14" dur="9.12">colonialist taking of Native American territories
via genocide in the founding of the US, it</text><text start="976.26" dur="1.92">wasn&apos;t based on who the more ethical actor
was.</text><text start="978.18" dur="6.72">It wasn&apos;t based on which civilization should
be in terms of some philosophical true, good</text><text start="984.9" dur="3.36">and beautiful, it was based 
on effective dominance, </text><text start="988.26" dur="3.0">which is a combination of violence and economic</text><text start="991.26" dur="1.08">productive capacity.</text><text start="992.94" dur="12.3">And so given that what ends up winning in
a very Darwinian sense and what is good in</text><text start="1005.24" dur="3.96">an ethical or philosophical sense or even
in a long-term viability sense aren&apos;t the</text><text start="1009.2" dur="2.52">same thing, that&apos;s at the core of something
we have to address.</text><text start="1012.32" dur="6.48">Is that where you have a scenario that what
wins in the short term forces everybody to</text><text start="1018.8" dur="4.32">race towards that thing, even if everyone
racing towards that thing makes an entire</text><text start="1023.12" dur="1.68">system self-terminate in the long term.</text><text start="1025.64" dur="2.82">And that&apos;s what we call the multipolar trap.</text><text start="1028.46" dur="4.38">It&apos;s expressed in the tragedy of the commons,
the military arms race, the market race to</text><text start="1032.84" dur="5.88">the bottom, and you could define it as a property
of the super organism to exploit all the energy</text><text start="1038.72" dur="1.92">in its environment and then hit a cliff.</text><text start="1041.54" dur="6.0">And we know that typically you have the peak
number of cancer cells in a person&apos;s body</text><text start="1047.54" dur="3.06">right before they die and then all the cancer
cells die when they kill a host.</text><text start="1050.6" dur="8.04">So the cancer cells individually are utilizing
metabolic resource faster than the other cells</text><text start="1058.64" dur="1.68">and reproducing faster than the other cells.</text><text start="1060.32" dur="5.52">So it seems like they&apos;re winning at a very
short-term game, but they are actually then</text><text start="1065.84" dur="1.56">killing the host that they depend upon.</text><text start="1067.4" dur="6.72">And so lots of people have drawn the analogy
that human presence on the biosphere looks</text><text start="1074.12" dur="6.72">a lot like a cancer where it is maximizing
its extraction from that which it depends</text><text start="1080.84" dur="3.54">upon in a way that is actually breaking the
substrated depends upon.</text><text start="1084.38" dur="4.44">Nate Hagens:
So is the purpose of this conversation to</text><text start="1088.82" dur="6.06">educate and influence cancer cells to become
self-aware, to change their behaviors?</text><text start="1094.88" dur="2.76">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Well I think one of the things we&apos;re also</text><text start="1097.64" dur="11.88">talking about that&apos;s tricky is
where it seems like the cancer cell behavior</text><text start="1110.36" dur="7.68">is actually following rational self-interest
defined by the game theoretics of, &quot;If I stop</text><text start="1118.04" dur="4.8">being a cancer cell, the body&apos;s still going
to die because I can&apos;t stop everybody else</text><text start="1122.84" dur="4.56">from doing it and so unless I can stop a certain
critical mass from doing it,&quot; and this gets</text><text start="1127.4" dur="6.24">down to the, &quot;If we don&apos;t cut the trees down
but we don&apos;t have some rule of law that makes</text><text start="1133.64" dur="5.1">sure nobody does, then all it means is the
other tribe that&apos;s in competition with us</text><text start="1138.74" dur="3.96">cuts all the trees down, we still don&apos;t get
to protect the forest and they&apos;ll use that</text><text start="1142.7" dur="3.06">economic advantage against us in the next
tribal warfare and we&apos;re fucked.</text><text start="1145.76" dur="3.48">So not only are we going to cut the trees
down faster than we need, we&apos;re going to race</text><text start="1149.24" dur="3.84">to cut them down faster than the other guy
because we can&apos;t get everyone to agree not</text><text start="1153.08" dur="0.24">to.&quot;</text><text start="1153.32" dur="4.8">Nate Hagens:
Which is why, at least at first, hearing about</text><text start="1158.12" dur="10.14">the ecological biophysical narrative of the
super organism and you&apos;re, going to tell me</text><text start="1168.26" dur="5.64">where yours fits in here, at least at first
feels to someone that they don&apos;t have any</text><text start="1173.9" dur="7.08">agency because what is one person&apos;s change
due to this larger dynamic that you&apos;re describing?</text><text start="1180.98" dur="4.08">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So if we take an example, if we try to get</text><text start="1185.06" dur="4.62">hopeful and we say, &quot;But let&apos;s look at where
we did change really bad things because some</text><text start="1189.68" dur="4.38">small number of one persons really did stand
up for something, they got other one persons</text><text start="1194.06" dur="2.22">to stand up, they got a critical mass and
we shifted it.&quot;</text><text start="1197.9" dur="2.58">Let&apos;s take a couple examples that are often
given.</text><text start="1200.48" dur="10.74">Let&apos;s take cigarettes or mothers against drunk
driving and seat belts or HFCs CFCs in ozone,</text><text start="1212.18" dur="9.42">we could give plenty of examples, but it&apos;s
true that we have not... that we don&apos;t have</text><text start="1221.6" dur="4.56">a history where we&apos;ve never solved anything
that matters, ecologically or socially.</text><text start="1226.16" dur="6.12">There are some times where people out of concern
for the commons have went against some profit</text><text start="1232.28" dur="5.52">stream and actually won a thing, but they
are different in kind than what we&apos;re facing</text><text start="1237.8" dur="1.908">now and I want to point out where they&apos;re
different in kind.</text><text start="1239.708" dur="2.712">Nate Hagens:
And different in scale, but go on.</text><text start="1242.42" dur="3.24">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
They&apos;re different in scale and different in</text><text start="1245.66" dur="1.14">kind in a way that&apos;s connected.</text><text start="1247.46" dur="5.28">So if we look at cigarettes, and four out
of five doctors choose camel cigarettes, we</text><text start="1252.74" dur="3.24">obviously haven&apos;t gotten rid of cigarettes,
but we&apos;ve made it to where you have to be</text><text start="1255.98" dur="3.36">18 to buy them and they have to have a surgeon
general&apos;s warning that this will kill you</text><text start="1259.34" dur="3.54">before you use it and we&apos;ve definitely decreased
a total number of people that use cigarettes</text><text start="1262.88" dur="1.8">and they can&apos;t use them in the buildings and
stuff.</text><text start="1265.76" dur="1.32">That took a lot of work.</text><text start="1267.08" dur="9.66">A lot of people died of lung cancer and secondhand
lung cancer first, et cetera for a vested</text><text start="1276.74" dur="3.54">interest profit stream that knew it was wrong
from well before it was regulated.</text><text start="1282.38" dur="7.32">But the sale of tobacco, as big a deal as
it was, was not at... it was not the engine</text><text start="1289.7" dur="2.1">of creation for the economy as a whole.</text><text start="1291.8" dur="2.7">It was one sector of the economy, it was one
product.</text><text start="1295.28" dur="7.5">When we&apos;re talking about climate change, as
you focus on, there are no industries that</text><text start="1302.78" dur="0.54">don&apos;t need energy.</text><text start="1303.32" dur="5.52">There is no such thing as even the possibility
of any good or service that doesn&apos;t need energy.</text><text start="1309.74" dur="5.52">So when we&apos;re trying to deal with something
that is the byproduct of using energy itself,</text><text start="1315.26" dur="4.98">it is connected to the machine of creation
rather than one little area, in the same way</text><text start="1320.24" dur="5.7">that it&apos;s like HFCs and CFCs, not every single
industry was based on aerosol propellants.</text><text start="1326.84" dur="4.38">And so you were able to change that without
having to change macroeconomics.</text><text start="1331.22" dur="4.14">You really only had to change an industry
and so you could get enough force to do it.</text><text start="1335.36" dur="5.82">When you&apos;re trying to change something that
is at the heart of macroeconomics itself,</text><text start="1341.18" dur="2.34">the vested interests that are against it is
everything.</text><text start="1344.48" dur="5.1">And it&apos;s not only that every industry and
thus every single business requires it, it&apos;s</text><text start="1349.58" dur="3.36">that also every nation states geopolitical
position requires it.</text><text start="1353.48" dur="3.54">So literally power itself is bound to it.</text><text start="1357.02" dur="6.0">So the entire machinery of power will resist
anything that would decrease its relative</text><text start="1363.02" dur="1.44">power capacity.</text><text start="1364.46" dur="4.5">And this is why from backing out of the Kyoto
Treaty to whatever the whole history of the</text><text start="1368.96" dur="13.38">thing, why has it been so hard is because
if any... so there the market can get us to</text><text start="1382.34" dur="4.38">organize based on incentive, but if incentive
isn&apos;t adequate and we actually have to use</text><text start="1386.72" dur="3.96">a anti incentive, we have to use a deterrent,
the market doesn&apos;t really do deterrents well.</text><text start="1390.68" dur="3.72">So you have a state that does that, which
is you make it illegal and someone will get</text><text start="1394.4" dur="3.36">arrested if they break the law or their business
will stop being able to operate.</text><text start="1398.96" dur="5.82">So this multipolar trap that we talk about
where there is some near term incentive where</text><text start="1404.78" dur="3.66">if any agent does that, they win in the short
term and it creates a race for everybody to</text><text start="1408.44" dur="6.0">do that, we&apos;ve figured out how to solve multipolar
traps inside of a nation state by rule of</text><text start="1414.44" dur="2.28">law and monopoly of force and enforcement.</text><text start="1416.72" dur="3.54">So we can say, &quot;No, we&apos;re not going to cut
down all the trees, we&apos;re going to have a</text><text start="1420.26" dur="4.56">national park, we&apos;re going to keep trees in
the national park and no logger is allowed</text><text start="1424.82" dur="0.42">to cut there.&quot;</text><text start="1425.24" dur="8.82">And what that means is a monopoly of violence
will forcibly stop you if you&apos;re cutting there</text><text start="1434.06" dur="3.0">and take you to jail to protect the rule of
law.</text><text start="1437.06" dur="8.28">And so inside of a nation state, we&apos;re able
to prevent most multipolar traps, but we do</text><text start="1445.34" dur="3.66">not have international governance to deal
with global ones.</text><text start="1449.0" dur="6.36">And so then we end up getting the various
nation states competing with each other and</text><text start="1456.74" dur="5.64">this is both... this is why there is a desire
for something like global governance is because</text><text start="1463.34" dur="5.34">the global oceans or the global atmosphere
or the global biodiversity or global commons</text><text start="1468.68" dur="4.92">that we depend upon can&apos;t have a situation
where each country, if they make the right</text><text start="1473.6" dur="3.42">choice, gets disadvantaged so that nobody
makes the right choice.</text><text start="1477.02" dur="5.82">The reason we don&apos;t want a one world government
is because how do you have something that</text><text start="1482.84" dur="4.44">has that much power that doesn&apos;t become corrupt
and how do you ensure that there are checks</text><text start="1487.28" dur="0.9">and balances on it?</text><text start="1488.18" dur="4.14">So we do need something like effective global </text><text start="1492.32" dur="2.46">governance, which does not 
have to be a government,</text><text start="1494.78" dur="5.7">it can be a decentralized process, but that
still allows us to solve the multipolar traps.</text><text start="1500.48" dur="3.3">Nate Hagens:
I&apos;ll push back a little bit on that because</text><text start="1503.78" dur="9.06">even within countries, the pressure to continue
economic growth even understanding, and deeply</text><text start="1512.84" dur="5.52">caring about some of the negative impacts
of decisions, these countries are powerless</text><text start="1518.36" dur="0.48">to do it.</text><text start="1518.84" dur="6.3">Look at Germany right now, they&apos;re importing
train loads of coal and they&apos;re taking down</text><text start="1525.14" dur="2.22">old growth forests for trees.</text><text start="1527.36" dur="7.08">This has nothing to do with the global situation,
they are compelled to get energy to keep their</text><text start="1534.44" dur="0.9">industries going.</text><text start="1535.34" dur="6.12">Of course it&apos;s a externally imposed emergency
thing because of Ukraine and Russia, but there&apos;s</text><text start="1541.46" dur="7.38">lots of examples like this that to keep the
mouths fed, we make populist...</text><text start="1548.84" dur="2.7">Well look at Brazil, that&apos;s not a global thing.</text><text start="1551.54" dur="4.8">They continue to tear down the rainforest
to grow more soybeans for beef and that&apos;s</text><text start="1556.34" dur="2.606">an economic decision within the country of
Brazil.</text><text start="1558.946" dur="0.01">But go on.</text><text start="1558.956" dur="6.924">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Of course it&apos;s a global thing, is if any country</text><text start="1565.88" dur="5.22">does not grow its GDP relative to other countries
that are, it&apos;s overall geopolitical position</text><text start="1571.1" dur="0.9">is going to decrease.</text><text start="1572.0" dur="7.8">And so a country does not have total sovereignty
and last time you and I were together with</text><text start="1579.8" dur="6.42">Samo, he was asking the question of how many
countries are there actually in terms of entities</text><text start="1586.22" dur="3.152">that can make real strategic decisions, and
he&apos;s like-</text><text start="1589.372" dur="2.068">Nate Hagens:
And there&apos;s not 195, there&apos;s like 10 or something</text><text start="1591.44" dur="0.876">like that he said</text><text start="1592.316" dur="2.784">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
One hypothesis is only countries that have</text><text start="1595.1" dur="7.38">nukes, the other hypothesis is only countries
that have nukes and or some critical control</text><text start="1602.48" dur="6.0">of an aspect of the global supply chain that
everybody needs, but basically has some play</text><text start="1608.48" dur="5.22">on power that is fundamental and everybody
else is to some degree a vassal nation.</text><text start="1613.7" dur="1.86">It&apos;s an interesting conversation.</text><text start="1615.56" dur="4.2">But you&apos;re right, it&apos;s not like a country
has total sovereignty within it because it</text><text start="1619.76" dur="4.56">also has to do with external pressures and
in a global media world it has to do with</text><text start="1624.32" dur="0.78">internal pressures.</text><text start="1625.88" dur="8.04">And so the external pressures do force everybody
to keep up with growth, it&apos;s kind of the nation</text><text start="1633.92" dur="3.6">state keeping up with the Joneses in the most
kind of destructive way.</text><text start="1637.52" dur="7.74">But the point is, if you have rule of law
and a monopoly of violence, you can bind a</text><text start="1645.26" dur="0.78">multipolar trap.</text><text start="1646.04" dur="3.54">It doesn&apos;t necessarily mean you will, it doesn&apos;t
necessarily mean they&apos;ll be very politically</text><text start="1649.58" dur="4.56">feasible, which is why there are no nations
that have done that for oil because they just</text><text start="1654.14" dur="0.72">couldn&apos;t.</text><text start="1654.86" dur="5.16">They couldn&apos;t because there is no way that
they would maintain economic viability within</text><text start="1660.02" dur="2.22">the overall global system that exists.</text><text start="1664.88" dur="5.94">So what we were mentioning is no country is
going to take the lead on properly pricing</text><text start="1670.82" dur="8.82">oil and say, &quot;We&apos;re going to price oil at
the actual cost that it would take us to produce</text><text start="1679.64" dur="4.74">it renewably in terms of how we manufacture
those hydrocarbons and how we process the</text><text start="1684.38" dur="6.72">externalities,&quot; and the price is 10 or a thousand
dollars a barrel, depending upon how you price</text><text start="1691.1" dur="0.54">it, but it&apos;s...</text><text start="1691.64" dur="6.96">I mean a gallon, but it&apos;s a fuck ton up from
where it currently is, they would be so radically</text><text start="1698.6" dur="5.34">disadvantaged GDP-wise relative to every other
country in their ability to build militaries</text><text start="1703.94" dur="1.32">or keep up with trade or whatever.</text><text start="1705.26" dur="2.58">And particularly, the leading nations aren&apos;t
going to do that.</text><text start="1707.84" dur="4.14">So the US isn&apos;t going to do it if China doesn&apos;t,
China&apos;s not going to do it if the West doesn&apos;t.</text><text start="1711.98" dur="8.52">And as a result, you have this situation where
any nation has an anti-incentive to lead.</text><text start="1720.5" dur="4.98">Nate Hagens:
Except paradoxically, given my worldview,</text><text start="1725.48" dur="6.96">and I&apos;m not sure you agree with this, a country
that chose to do that or was forced to do</text><text start="1732.44" dur="8.46">that, to simplify first and beat the rush
would have major economic and social pain</text><text start="1740.9" dur="6.54">now, but would self-organize in a way while
the rest of the global system is still intact,</text><text start="1747.44" dur="5.82">that they may be more resilient 20, 30, 40
years from now based on what they were forced</text><text start="1753.26" dur="0.24">to do.</text><text start="1753.5" dur="0.216">Now</text><text start="1753.716" dur="3.624">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
The challenge is always the gap between when</text><text start="1757.34" dur="4.44">you start to do the thing and how much advantage
everyone else gets in that time and what they</text><text start="1761.78" dur="2.88">do relative to you in that time before your
thing pays off.</text><text start="1765.44" dur="2.22">There&apos;s a time to ROI on it.</text><text start="1767.66" dur="1.32">It&apos;s the same with getting into-</text><text start="1770.18" dur="2.28">Nate Hagens:
Well it&apos;s power.</text><text start="1772.46" dur="3.42">It&apos;s energy per unit time, it&apos;s power, which
we talked about before.</text><text start="1775.88" dur="1.38">So you...</text><text start="1778.82" dur="6.96">I&apos;m sorry to interrupt, but implicit in what
you&apos;re saying is something I fully agree with,</text><text start="1785.78" dur="9.3">which we are in this rapidly rushing river
and we can&apos;t swim upstream, we&apos;re compelled</text><text start="1795.08" dur="5.7">to go downstream with everyone else until
there&apos;s a waterfall or the river calms or</text><text start="1800.78" dur="0.54">whatever.</text><text start="1802.7" dur="6.0">It&apos;s an economic compulsion globally, at least
for the near term.</text><text start="1808.7" dur="1.8">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="1810.5" dur="13.62">So the competitive interests do force us to
keep up with the game or lose as a result</text><text start="1824.12" dur="7.86">of not keeping up in that game, lose in ways
that are intolerable before the ROI of our</text><text start="1831.98" dur="0.84">new investment happens.</text><text start="1834.74" dur="7.32">The answer to that, why the name of this whole
thing is Bend Not Break is if the major players</text><text start="1842.06" dur="10.8">can come to an agreement to all recognize
that future state and decide to be willing</text><text start="1852.86" dur="4.86">to accept constraints on their own behavior
knowing that the other ones will also accept</text><text start="1857.72" dur="5.4">constraints on their behavior, some kind of
voluntary agreement, because unlike in the</text><text start="1863.12" dur="1.86">nation state example I gave where you can </text><text start="1864.98" dur="2.82">have a monopoly of force, 
there is no international</text><text start="1867.8" dur="5.34">monopoly of force because how do you enforce
a deterrent on countries that have nukes in</text><text start="1873.14" dur="1.32">critical parts of your supply chain?</text><text start="1875.0" dur="0.9">It&apos;s very hard.</text><text start="1875.9" dur="6.0">The cost of implementing the deterrents is
oftentimes worse in the short-term than whatever</text><text start="1881.9" dur="2.22">you were trying to avoid so you just leave
it alone.</text><text start="1884.12" dur="3.18">So, &quot;Okay, we don&apos;t get off fossil fuels or
we have a nuclear war.&quot;</text><text start="1887.3" dur="1.596">It&apos;s like or</text><text start="1888.896" dur="2.004">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
our entire economy breaks because we can&apos;t</text><text start="1890.9" dur="2.46">do import with China or they can&apos;t do export
with us or whatever.</text><text start="1893.36" dur="3.54">So the cost of deterrent is a very real thing
to have to factor.</text><text start="1896.9" dur="2.64">So you can&apos;t force that thing.</text><text start="1899.54" dur="4.86">You have to somehow reach agreements with
agents that are hopefully capable of being</text><text start="1904.4" dur="8.64">rational enough to see that in a time period
that is not so far out that it&apos;s unreasonable</text><text start="1913.04" dur="2.16">to think about, the alternative is much worse.</text><text start="1915.2" dur="4.92">And this is I think the whole reason you have
a podcast and the reason I podcast with you</text><text start="1920.12" dur="7.98">and like that is to try to show the inexorable
world situation if we continue on the path</text><text start="1928.1" dur="7.68">that we&apos;re on, such that those who are in
the positions of power could come to make</text><text start="1935.78" dur="5.58">the kinds of agreements that make those choices
possible for each other that bring about a</text><text start="1941.36" dur="1.56">different, better, long-term world situation.</text><text start="1942.92" dur="3.18">Nate Hagens:
And it would by definition have to be people</text><text start="1946.1" dur="10.02">in those 10 real countries that hold the reigns;
US, China, Russia, France, Germany, UK and</text><text start="1956.12" dur="0.78">a couple others.</text><text start="1956.9" dur="1.68">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Probably.</text><text start="1958.58" dur="5.52">The US and China agreeing by themselves would
be enough to move the entire world that way,</text><text start="1964.1" dur="5.208">but probably it would require both of them
and that&apos;s hard.</text><text start="1969.308" dur="1.332">Nate Hagens:
Yeah.</text><text start="1973.94" dur="6.3">Let me just ask you a sidetrack question and
I have a note here to myself &quot;do not ask Daniel</text><text start="1980.24" dur="4.8">sidetrack questions on this episode,&quot; but
it&apos;s only a partial sidetrack.</text><text start="1985.04" dur="8.34">So you just described the logic of how nations
are compelled to continue to grow so that</text><text start="1993.38" dur="1.32">they don&apos;t get behind.</text><text start="1994.7" dur="3.66">What about individuals listening to this?</text><text start="2001.96" dur="5.22">Can they get out of that trap in their own
behaviors and plans?</text><text start="2007.18" dur="5.28">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, it&apos;s an interesting one.</text><text start="2016.36" dur="5.46">Can individuals change their behaviors in
certain ways that are important to do regarding</text><text start="2023.26" dur="5.1">their consideration of, did this meat come
from a factory farm?</text><text start="2028.36" dur="2.16">Did this product come from a sweat shop?</text><text start="2030.52" dur="2.1">How much total shit do I actually need?</text><text start="2034.0" dur="4.86">Is this packaging ever going to break down
in the environment?</text><text start="2038.86" dur="3.48">Can they start to be considerate of those
things and should they be?</text><text start="2042.34" dur="0.54">Yes.</text><text start="2042.88" dur="6.3">Should they be because that choice will make
much difference to the whole?</text><text start="2049.18" dur="1.14">No, it&apos;s not going to.</text><text start="2050.32" dur="6.6">Should they be because if they do and communicate
about that and all the people who are compelled</text><text start="2056.92" dur="5.7">to do, that it can change the nature of culture
and status enough that enough people do that</text><text start="2062.62" dur="1.38">the cumulative effects are meaningful?</text><text start="2064.0" dur="1.5">Yes, that&apos;s true.</text><text start="2068.5" dur="7.74">Is there a lot of tricky stuff to consider
like then everyone&apos;s incentive to virtue signal</text><text start="2076.24" dur="5.52">in the hope that, that compels other people
to do things in a way that oftentimes actually</text><text start="2081.76" dur="6.24">produces more backlash than anything, there&apos;s
sensitive things there.</text><text start="2088.0" dur="6.84">I think a lot of people who are smart and
caring get hopeless around their own personal</text><text start="2094.84" dur="1.56">behavior for a couple reasons.</text><text start="2096.4" dur="9.6">One, you and I are both talking on a computer
right now so that we can do this, where we</text><text start="2106.0" dur="4.38">know for sure that the mining of the rare
earths needed to make these semiconductors</text><text start="2110.38" dur="5.94">were in mines that employ slave labor and
in supply chains that put toxic mining tailings</text><text start="2116.32" dur="5.04">into freshwater and that use fuck tons of
energy and on and on.</text><text start="2121.36" dur="6.48">The alternative green laptop doesn&apos;t exist
because there&apos;s not a completely separate</text><text start="2127.84" dur="5.372">supply chain for cobalt somewhere or for lithium
or for semiconductor manufacturing.</text><text start="2133.212" dur="2.428">Nate Hagens:
Well, the green laptop is you and I living</text><text start="2135.64" dur="4.5">in the same community and meeting in a forest
glen instead of on the computer.</text><text start="2140.14" dur="4.476">But we are trying to maximize our impact,
not minimize our impact.</text><text start="2144.616" dur="2.544">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So that&apos;s the point is that, a lot of people</text><text start="2147.16" dur="7.68">will start to realize, &quot;Okay, every single
product I can find, for the most part, has</text><text start="2154.84" dur="7.14">some input from global supply chains,&quot; even
if the materials to do it were transported</text><text start="2161.98" dur="4.62">across roads that were paid for by nation
states that were backed up by militaries and</text><text start="2166.6" dur="3.0">taxes that go to those things, whatever it
is.</text><text start="2169.6" dur="3.36">And so then you&apos;re, &quot;All right, well, I&apos;m
going to live in the forest and only use shit</text><text start="2172.96" dur="1.98">that I make by hand that I find on the forest
floor.&quot;</text><text start="2174.94" dur="3.42">The chance that I&apos;m going to radically influence </text><text start="2178.36" dur="3.48">the world is pretty low and 
my decreased consumption</text><text start="2181.84" dur="1.74">is not going to affect the overall story.</text><text start="2183.58" dur="7.98">So there&apos;s almost a way in which that&apos;s more
of a &quot;I want to wash my hands clean of being</text><text start="2191.56" dur="4.38">part of our species at this time, but I&apos;m
actually not taking responsibility for what</text><text start="2195.94" dur="1.68">I do to meaningfully affect it.&quot;</text><text start="2197.62" dur="2.88">And I think that there is an ethics of action
and inaction.</text><text start="2200.5" dur="4.14">I&apos;m ethically responsible for what I could
do and don&apos;t as well as what I do.</text><text start="2204.64" dur="2.28">Nate Hagens:
I like that.</text><text start="2206.92" dur="7.02">There&apos;s also the positive externality of using
less and all that, making you personally more</text><text start="2213.94" dur="2.52">flexible on the bumpy road to come.</text><text start="2216.46" dur="4.5">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Well, so I think people should be thoughtful</text><text start="2220.96" dur="3.72">about this, though I don&apos;t think they should
try to be perfect about it because if they</text><text start="2224.68" dur="3.06">try to be perfect, they will be in the forest
using-</text><text start="2227.74" dur="0.291">Nate Hagens:
You can never be perfect.</text><text start="2228.031" dur="0.789">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Nothing.</text><text start="2228.82" dur="0.6">Yeah.</text><text start="2230.44" dur="2.52">But I think one of the things that&apos;s important
is to get...</text><text start="2233.68" dur="5.22">I am complicit with the world system every
time I use my phone.</text><text start="2238.9" dur="6.24">I&apos;m complicit with the world system every
time I use money itself as an exchange for</text><text start="2245.14" dur="0.18">anything.</text><text start="2245.32" dur="2.76">Every time I drive on a road I&apos;m complicit
with the world system.</text><text start="2248.08" dur="4.5">As such, I can&apos;t think of myself as an individual
separate from the whole.</text><text start="2252.58" dur="4.44">There is this Ubuntu, I am because we are
and this is the way the human world is right</text><text start="2257.02" dur="7.38">now and so I can&apos;t make myself in perfect
ethical alignment, independent of helping</text><text start="2264.4" dur="1.5">the species as a whole to move.</text><text start="2265.9" dur="7.44">And there&apos;s something actually more humble
and interconnecting and important about getting</text><text start="2273.34" dur="0.36">that.</text><text start="2273.7" dur="6.84">And now that doesn&apos;t mean, okay, well because
I&apos;m complicit with those things, fuck it,</text><text start="2280.54" dur="2.34">I&apos;ll just buy everything that I want with
no consideration.</text><text start="2282.88" dur="7.2">One should absolutely endeavor to do the best
they can on a number of areas and also say...</text><text start="2292.3" dur="4.56">I know how environmentally bad it is when
I use planes, but you and I both go to places,</text><text start="2296.86" dur="4.44">whether we&apos;re interacting with governments
or major corporations to try to help them</text><text start="2301.3" dur="6.24">do better, where the impact of the fuel on
that plane makes sense relative to the possible</text><text start="2307.54" dur="1.68">impact we can have on those institutions.</text><text start="2309.88" dur="6.0">And it&apos;s hard because it&apos;s so easy, once you
accept that it&apos;s both, it&apos;s so easy to bullshit</text><text start="2315.88" dur="0.18">yourself.</text><text start="2316.84" dur="3.42">So all there is, is earnest consideration
of this.</text><text start="2321.16" dur="3.12">So I think some people can get a little hopeless
when they try to be perfect with it.</text><text start="2324.28" dur="7.62">I think the other place people can be hopeless
is when they recognize that most of the harm</text><text start="2331.9" dur="4.74">is on a parade or distribution that is not
the result of just consumer behavior.</text><text start="2336.64" dur="4.74">It&apos;s the result of military behavior, major
corporations, things that aren&apos;t going to</text><text start="2341.38" dur="4.86">change not just based on my behavior but my
behavior plus the voluntary movement I try</text><text start="2346.24" dur="0.3">to create.</text><text start="2346.54" dur="3.3">And that all of that doesn&apos;t converge to adequate
in time.</text><text start="2350.5" dur="5.64">And so that&apos;s why there is also this other
thing got a factor of, okay, it&apos;s not just</text><text start="2356.14" dur="6.96">about being less bad on the environment, it&apos;s
about transforming the human techno sphere,</text><text start="2363.1" dur="4.5">social sphere complex to actually be compatible
with the biosphere that it depends upon.</text><text start="2367.6" dur="6.48">So not just how do I use less of this one
that is incompatible, but what is my role</text><text start="2374.08" dur="4.68">to play in the transition of the human presence
on earth to one that actually works with earth</text><text start="2378.76" dur="0.66">long term?</text><text start="2379.42" dur="4.38">Nate Hagens:
Well, that&apos;s the going to be, I hope the topic</text><text start="2383.8" dur="6.36">of our next conversation, is what are the
pathways at the various scales on what we</text><text start="2390.16" dur="3.3">can do once we understand this meta overview.</text><text start="2393.46" dur="3.36">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So we didn&apos;t get to yet...</text><text start="2396.82" dur="4.02">We just started to touch on the fact that
the economy as we understand it, is incompatible</text><text start="2400.84" dur="6.42">with the biosphere, that the production of
goods and services, that profit is both a</text><text start="2407.26" dur="5.34">measure of production but also a measure of
extraction and externalization, that until</text><text start="2412.6" dur="3.48">the economy does not have 
extraction and internalization </text><text start="2416.08" dur="3.6">as realities within it, then it&apos;s accounting</text><text start="2419.68" dur="0.84">is wrong.</text><text start="2420.52" dur="6.54">It&apos;s basically just got messed up books because
it&apos;s unrenewably taking from the balance sheet</text><text start="2427.06" dur="5.58">of nature and it&apos;s unrenewably taking assets
from the balance sheet of nature and unrenewably</text><text start="2432.64" dur="4.08">putting costs into the balance sheet of nature,
not accounting for it in a way that breaks</text><text start="2436.72" dur="4.08">that if you just even get the accounting right,
then you start to have an economy that makes</text><text start="2440.8" dur="0.24">sense.</text><text start="2441.76" dur="7.5">But that does require changes that would look
nothing like capitalism, socialism or any</text><text start="2449.26" dur="1.74">type of system we&apos;ve had to date.</text><text start="2451.0" dur="4.68">Nate Hagens:
Well, for one reason, because if you to use</text><text start="2455.68" dur="8.34">ecological economics terms, if you internalize
all the externalities, most industries on</text><text start="2464.02" dur="2.1">the planet would be unprofitable.</text><text start="2466.12" dur="7.86">So if you try to close loop this stuff, who
bears the cost of that?</text><text start="2473.98" dur="5.28">Because the closed loop stuff is going to
be a lot more costly and so either the governments</text><text start="2479.26" dur="5.94">bear that cost or consumers bear it with much
higher prices or using less stuff and we&apos;re</text><text start="2485.2" dur="2.496">not going to voluntarily on mass choose that.</text><text start="2487.696" dur="0.984">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="2491.26" dur="6.24">That&apos;s another way of stating the multipolar
trap, which is that this system where the</text><text start="2497.5" dur="6.12">cost is externalized to the environment and
the commons does seem to short term benefit</text><text start="2503.62" dur="6.24">us and whether us means corporation, country
or person.</text><text start="2509.86" dur="6.9">And even though the aggregate effect of that
system does self terminate for everybody.</text><text start="2517.66" dur="8.76">And so we do have to voluntarily at a minimum
adequate scale, create a new system that doesn&apos;t</text><text start="2526.42" dur="8.4">self terminate or
we get the plausible deniability of saying</text><text start="2534.82" dur="4.8">we couldn&apos;t have done anything else while
being chained to and part of a system that</text><text start="2539.62" dur="4.86">is on a self termination path, which is why
understanding what the alternatives look like</text><text start="2544.48" dur="0.42">is key.</text><text start="2545.44" dur="1.5">Nate Hagens:
How did we get here?</text><text start="2546.94" dur="1.32">How does everything fit together?</text><text start="2551.08" dur="5.64">Energy, materials, human behavior, technology,
bird&apos;s eye view.</text><text start="2556.72" dur="3.3">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So I think the key insight that I want to</text><text start="2560.02" dur="9.9">emphasize has to do with what is unique about
humans relative to the rest of the species</text><text start="2569.92" dur="1.2">as best we can observe.</text><text start="2571.9" dur="8.34">And when I say humans right now, I mean homosapien
relative to everything else, but it probably</text><text start="2580.24" dur="6.72">started with earlier hominids that had early
tool making.</text><text start="2586.96" dur="4.2">So somewhere between Australopithecus and
homo habiles...</text><text start="2591.16" dur="3.18">Obviously all those other hominids are not
with us.</text><text start="2596.98" dur="3.9">But that&apos;s important for the early part of
this story because we&apos;re talking about a curve</text><text start="2600.88" dur="3.06">that&apos;s maybe 2 million years old rather than
just 200,000 years old.</text><text start="2603.94" dur="4.26">Nate Hagens:
As you brought up pre-hominid species, it</text><text start="2608.2" dur="5.22">made me think that what you were just describing
between nation states today that there&apos;s not</text><text start="2613.42" dur="6.66">going to be a nation that&apos;s going to voluntarily
give up power and reduce GDP, you could maybe</text><text start="2620.08" dur="2.4">apply that to pre-hominid species too.</text><text start="2622.48" dur="3.9">And that&apos;s why we are here and the Neanderthals
are not.</text><text start="2626.38" dur="2.76">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, there are obviously arguments between</text><text start="2629.14" dur="6.42">scholars on how this happened but one of the
hypotheses definitely is that the reason the</text><text start="2635.56" dur="7.5">other hominids aren&apos;t here is inter-species
inter-tribal warfare and that sapiens dominance</text><text start="2643.06" dur="7.92">at various aspects of technology and coordination
had them win that game.</text><text start="2650.98" dur="8.04">Could be seen as the beginning of this whole
trajectory that we&apos;ve been facing since.</text><text start="2659.8" dur="8.76">But I do want to emphasize a distinction between
humans and everything else in nature.</text><text start="2669.22" dur="5.82">This is always tricky because there&apos;s an old
story of the difference between humans and</text><text start="2675.04" dur="8.64">the rest of nature that looks like man&apos;s dominion
over nature because we want to rise above</text><text start="2683.68" dur="5.52">our animal nature to some angel, godly over
self and that makes us separate enough that</text><text start="2689.2" dur="0.9">we have dominion over.</text><text start="2690.1" dur="3.48">And then there&apos;s kind of an environmental
movement that wants us to say men are not</text><text start="2693.58" dur="2.34">the web of life, we&apos;re merely a strand within
it.</text><text start="2695.92" dur="3.54">Whatever we do to the web, we do to ourselves
and see our unity with nature and our dependence</text><text start="2699.46" dur="0.48">on it more.</text><text start="2699.94" dur="4.44">And wanting to offer something that has elements
of both but is kind of distinct, which is</text><text start="2705.4" dur="4.32">humans don&apos;t exist without the rest of nature
so we have to be stewards for it.</text><text start="2709.72" dur="3.96">But what is different about us allows us to
destroy all of nature in a way that nothing</text><text start="2713.68" dur="1.08">else in nature can.</text><text start="2714.76" dur="3.42">Therefore, we have to be stewards or we don&apos;t
continue to exist.</text><text start="2718.9" dur="8.88">And the key distinction is that the adaptive
advantage that every other animal has is the</text><text start="2727.78" dur="3.06">result of genetics that result from evolutionary
process.</text><text start="2730.84" dur="7.86">And the evolutionary process is, genetic mutation
occurs, most of those mutations are not adaptive.</text><text start="2738.7" dur="5.46">Some tiny set of them are adaptive and that
increases survival and reproduction and if</text><text start="2744.16" dur="3.0">it increases survival and/or reproduction,
it gets selected for.</text><text start="2747.16" dur="8.04">The process by which a genetic mutation occurs
is, some copying error because a gamma ray</text><text start="2755.2" dur="3.72">hits the thing or oxidative stress or a virus
or something like that.</text><text start="2758.92" dur="5.16">And those mutation pressures are pretty evenly
distributed across the ecosystem.</text><text start="2764.98" dur="4.32">There&apos;s a million minutia that we could get
into here and of which there are some differences,</text><text start="2769.3" dur="6.24">but I want to kind of stay at the high level
topology of the thing, that I think is relatively</text><text start="2775.54" dur="1.32">easy to agree on.</text><text start="2776.86" dur="9.3">So you don&apos;t get a situation where you have
a mutation that creates a radical difference.</text><text start="2786.88" dur="3.66">The total amount of change that occurs in
a mutation is going to be relatively small.</text><text start="2790.54" dur="6.0">So major speciation changes occur through
lots of compounding mutations over a long</text><text start="2796.54" dur="0.72">period of time.</text><text start="2797.98" dur="6.6">And then you have this because co-selective
process that if you have a mutation that makes</text><text start="2805.84" dur="6.3">say a predator slightly faster, it&apos;s going
to be slightly better at hunting the prey</text><text start="2812.14" dur="0.18">animal.</text><text start="2812.32" dur="2.88">Well, it&apos;s going to catch more of the slower
prey animals.</text><text start="2815.2" dur="5.1">And so the faster prey animals that still
continue to avoid it in breeding with each</text><text start="2820.3" dur="5.22">other because there was already some natural
distribution in their genetics create faster</text><text start="2825.52" dur="0.72">prey animals.</text><text start="2826.24" dur="4.08">So as the predator animal gets a little bit
faster from a mutation, the co-selective forces</text><text start="2830.32" dur="2.82">make the prey animal get faster or vice versa.</text><text start="2833.14" dur="7.26">So the change occurs through these micro changes
and co-selective pressures and then not just</text><text start="2840.4" dur="4.92">the prey animal but the prey animal&apos;s relationship
with the plants that it eats and the adaptive</text><text start="2845.32" dur="6.78">changes that occur there, you end up getting
that the competitive forces end up leading</text><text start="2852.1" dur="3.78">to meta stability of the whole system and </text><text start="2855.88" dur="3.66">upregulation, slow but kind 
of systemic upregulation</text><text start="2859.54" dur="0.54">of the whole.</text><text start="2861.64" dur="7.26">With humans and like I said, this started
with earlier humans, we started with being</text><text start="2868.9" dur="4.26">able to increase our adaptive capacity not
through genetic mutation.</text><text start="2873.16" dur="6.72">We started by being able to increase our adaptive
capacity through abstraction, through tool</text><text start="2879.88" dur="2.88">making and through abstract 
coordination mechanisms.</text><text start="2883.6" dur="3.06">People start to get into, yeah, but animals
make tools.</text><text start="2886.66" dur="6.84">You can see even crows will use tools to break
things open and chimpanzees will use tools</text><text start="2893.5" dur="3.84">and the beaver will make a dam and the birds
make nests.</text><text start="2897.34" dur="3.24">These are extracorporeal adaptations that
they use.</text><text start="2900.58" dur="5.34">Yes, but bird&apos;s nest for any species are about
the same as they were 10,000 or 100,000 or</text><text start="2905.92" dur="1.8">500,000 years ago for that species.</text><text start="2907.72" dur="5.82">They&apos;re not evolving their tool set and adaptation
occurred for them that involved them engaging</text><text start="2913.54" dur="1.68">with their environment in a particular way.</text><text start="2915.22" dur="4.14">But they&apos;re not recursively making changes
on how they do that tooling.</text><text start="2919.36" dur="2.16">The same with beavers, the same with chimpanzees.</text><text start="2921.52" dur="5.52">And so you can see that a chimpanzee will
use a sharp rock to cut something.</text><text start="2927.04" dur="4.74">It&apos;ll experiment with the rocks around to
see which one experientially cuts faster.</text><text start="2931.78" dur="4.5">And if you give it a knife, it&apos;ll use the
knife but it doesn&apos;t design a knife, it doesn&apos;t</text><text start="2936.28" dur="5.52">design the beginning of stone tools because
the design of it requires this kind of recursive</text><text start="2941.8" dur="4.98">abstraction that says, this rock is sharp,
this rock is sharper or could I make one that</text><text start="2946.78" dur="0.66">is sharper yet?</text><text start="2947.44" dur="4.08">In order to do that, I have to understand
the abstract principle of sharpness and say</text><text start="2951.52" dur="1.08">what mediates sharpness.</text><text start="2952.6" dur="4.2">So it has to do with the hardness of one material
relative to another and it has to do with</text><text start="2956.8" dur="1.92">the angle of the edge.</text><text start="2958.72" dur="6.42">And so the ability for the recursive abstraction
that allows us to make a better tool and then</text><text start="2965.14" dur="6.18">see how to make it again and again, that occurred
with some degree of complexity of recursive</text><text start="2971.32" dur="5.28">abstraction process where probably chimpanzee
was right here and just on the other side</text><text start="2976.6" dur="4.38">of a line of neural development was homo habilis
and they had that ability.</text><text start="2981.94" dur="1.68">Then, it got doubled down with sapiens.</text><text start="2983.62" dur="5.52">And so you can see that we take an abstraction
and then we do abstractions on top of it.</text><text start="2989.14" dur="3.78">We don&apos;t just see how do we make a sharper
thing, but then how do we attach it to a bow</text><text start="2992.92" dur="0.54">and arrow.</text><text start="2995.14" dur="0.6">Go ahead.</text><text start="2995.74" dur="6.48">Nate Hagens:
So I and my colleagues, like John Gowdy, attribute</text><text start="3002.22" dur="5.7">the origin of the super organism to around
10,000 years when we found agriculture and</text><text start="3007.92" dur="2.7">started to optimize for surplus.</text><text start="3010.62" dur="4.5">And you&apos;re saying that the origins of the
super organism was much earlier than that?</text><text start="3015.12" dur="1.98">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="3017.1" dur="4.14">When you look at an exponential curve that
can be fairly flat for a long time and then</text><text start="3021.24" dur="6.54">start to verticalize, roughly 10,000 years
ago, agrarian revolution was a major jump,</text><text start="3027.78" dur="5.16">but I am going to go back and look much earlier.</text><text start="3032.94" dur="6.3">Because already before that happened, you
had humans behaving as apex predators in almost</text><text start="3039.24" dur="2.7">every single environment in the world 10,000
years ago.</text><text start="3041.94" dur="2.82">And there&apos;s no other animal at all that is
like that.</text><text start="3044.76" dur="2.52">And that&apos;s already a critical thing to understand.</text><text start="3048.3" dur="2.58">It goes along with your extincting of the
other hominids.</text><text start="3051.78" dur="7.92">So as amazingly well adapted as the cheetah
is to the Savannah or the polar bear is to</text><text start="3059.7" dur="2.1">the Arctic, neither of them survived in the
other environment.</text><text start="3062.76" dur="5.22">And yet we were able to because of tool making
put on clothes, create shelters and go become</text><text start="3067.98" dur="1.86">the apex predator of every single environment.</text><text start="3069.84" dur="5.04">That was already really different because
it wasn&apos;t just that we could over-optimize</text><text start="3074.88" dur="2.04">a single environment and then come back into
check.</text><text start="3076.92" dur="5.58">We had the ability to go become not only adaptive
but apex predators in every environment.</text><text start="3083.22" dur="2.04">After we over hunted an environment-</text><text start="3085.26" dur="4.26">Nate Hagens:
It&apos;s not only the recursive ability to imagine</text><text start="3089.52" dur="4.44">abstractions and to invent technology, but
it&apos;s also because we&apos;re ultra social.</text><text start="3093.96" dur="2.34">We&apos;re not a solitary species.</text><text start="3096.3" dur="8.82">Jonathan Haidt, who&apos;s going to be on this
show soon, in his book, The Righteous Mind,</text><text start="3105.12" dur="3.9">says that humans are 95% ape and 5% bee.</text><text start="3109.68" dur="6.84">Like we have a lot of be behavioral attributes
of the social insects so that we copy and</text><text start="3116.52" dur="3.18">we coordinate and we collaborate in ways that
other species don&apos;t.</text><text start="3120.66" dur="4.08">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Chimpanzees are pretty social, they&apos;re not</text><text start="3124.74" dur="2.88">solitary and bonobos are very social.</text><text start="3128.34" dur="5.82">I wouldn&apos;t say that it&apos;s about us being more
social than them, I would say it&apos;s about us</text><text start="3134.16" dur="5.22">applying our abstractions recursively to our
coordination mechanisms.</text><text start="3140.1" dur="7.32">So language allows a type of sociality and
then written language and formal hierarchies</text><text start="3147.42" dur="5.58">and those are all basically technologies,
techne, of social coordination.</text><text start="3153.84" dur="6.72">And so obviously a wolf pack that coordinates
is able to take down a bison that a lone wolf</text><text start="3160.56" dur="0.54">never could.</text><text start="3162.66" dur="6.66">So we&apos;re not just looking at the adaptive
capacity of an animal but of its coordination.</text><text start="3170.22" dur="5.04">Our recursive abstraction gave us the ability
to keep making our coordination mechanisms</text><text start="3175.26" dur="7.08">change so we could go from the coordination
that happens in a band to a tribe to much</text><text start="3182.34" dur="2.16">larger tribes to early cities.</text><text start="3184.5" dur="8.52">And so you can see that we&apos;re able to change
our coordination based on tech that allows</text><text start="3193.02" dur="4.56">more specialization and division of labor
and whatever and able to change our coordination</text><text start="3197.58" dur="5.22">mechanism based on the size of the number
of people that are cooperating in the thing.</text><text start="3204.24" dur="4.26">I would say somewhere around 10,000 years
ago is when we started to regularly pass the</text><text start="3208.5" dur="7.68">Dunbar number and where formalized methods
of animal husbandry and agrarian revolution</text><text start="3216.18" dur="1.92">made a massive jump.</text><text start="3218.82" dur="6.12">But before that, stone tools, language and
fire were massive jumps that distinguished</text><text start="3224.94" dur="0.84">us from everything else.</text><text start="3226.62" dur="6.36">And you can see that stone tools was us applying
recursive abstraction to the domain of atoms</text><text start="3232.98" dur="3.42">and we could extend our body&apos;s capacity.</text><text start="3237.0" dur="4.62">Rather than the genetic time it takes to grow
a longer fang, we could just make a spear</text><text start="3241.62" dur="2.1">that&apos;s longer than any fang.</text><text start="3243.72" dur="6.0">And then we could keep making longer, harder,
sharper ones.</text><text start="3249.72" dur="5.4">And we are able to increase our predative
capacity through a different mechanism.</text><text start="3255.12" dur="2.58">It&apos;s not genetic selection anymore, it&apos;s tool
making.</text><text start="3257.7" dur="5.58">We&apos;re able to increase our predative capacity,
that&apos;s our capacity for violence and extraction</text><text start="3263.28" dur="4.26">faster than anything else in nature can increase
its resilience.</text><text start="3267.54" dur="5.46">So co-selection breaks and it&apos;s no longer
that as the lion gets a little bit faster,</text><text start="3273.0" dur="4.86">the gazelle&apos;s get faster, it&apos;s that we get
faster and we can over hunt an entire ecosystem</text><text start="3277.86" dur="4.02">faster than genetic mutation can take up and
then we can go move to another ecosystem,</text><text start="3281.88" dur="2.82">over hunt it until we start farming ecosystems.</text><text start="3284.7" dur="2.76">And so this is really different.</text><text start="3288.66" dur="5.64">So you can see that the stone tool was our
recursive abstraction applied to the domain</text><text start="3294.3" dur="5.1">of atoms to extend our corporeal capacity,
our physical body&apos;s capacity into instruments.</text><text start="3299.4" dur="4.44">Fire was abstraction applied to the domain
of energy.</text><text start="3304.62" dur="4.32">We could now generate warmth and move ourselves
to environments that we wouldn&apos;t have been</text><text start="3308.94" dur="5.46">fit and get calories from things that wouldn&apos;t
have been calorically available for us via</text><text start="3314.4" dur="0.42">cooking.</text><text start="3315.84" dur="4.74">And in doing so, though of course we&apos;re converting
the environment in the form of trees or whatever</text><text start="3320.58" dur="7.5">into entropy, into fire for our utility and
language was us applying our abstraction to</text><text start="3328.08" dur="4.92">the domain of bits or information processing
so that we could have more complex signaling</text><text start="3333.0" dur="0.96">and memory.</text><text start="3333.96" dur="3.48">And the memory was so that 
we could take everything </text><text start="3337.44" dur="3.18">that we had learned and 
pass it on via memorization</text><text start="3340.62" dur="2.16">of songs and like that before the written
word.</text><text start="3342.78" dur="5.1">Because if you and I had to learn math from
scratch, we wouldn&apos;t get to Roman numerals</text><text start="3347.88" dur="3.098">but we get to learn what the entire history-</text><text start="3350.978" dur="0.862">Nate Hagens:
Well, you probably could.</text><text start="3352.92" dur="3.0">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
If I was really ambitious, I might get as</text><text start="3355.92" dur="1.14">far as Roman numerals, right?</text><text start="3357.06" dur="4.38">But if you think about we&apos;re able to, by the </text><text start="3361.44" dur="2.7">time we&apos;re kids in grade 
school, get the cumulative</text><text start="3364.14" dur="4.248">effect of the smartest people throughout history,
thousands of years of their compressed knowledge.</text><text start="3368.388" dur="4.512">Nate Hagens:
So language accelerated entropy on planet</text><text start="3372.9" dur="0.3">earth.</text><text start="3373.2" dur="7.14">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
It accelerated localized centropy and systemic</text><text start="3380.34" dur="10.62">entropy and profit is localized centropy and
systemic entropy which goes along with privatized</text><text start="3390.96" dur="1.14">gain and socialized losses.</text><text start="3394.14" dur="7.68">And so I would say with the capacity for recursive
abstraction and the ability to increase our</text><text start="3401.82" dur="5.52">adaptive capacity through a different process
and a faster and more recursively fast process</text><text start="3407.34" dur="4.44">than the rest of nature, began the beginning
of this thing we call the human super organism</text><text start="3412.38" dur="5.1">and the beginning of a process that is ultimately
self terminating unless it changes process.</text><text start="3417.48" dur="5.1">And so then of course the agrarian revolution
was a massive jump and it wasn&apos;t one jump,</text><text start="3422.58" dur="5.4">it was like three or four or five jumps that
we kind of stick together because before the</text><text start="3427.98" dur="3.36">plow, goat herding already 
started desertification, </text><text start="3431.34" dur="0.9">right?</text><text start="3432.96" dur="6.24">Our ability to steward a whole herd of goats
and protect them from predators meant that</text><text start="3439.2" dur="4.08">we could again change the environment pretty
radically where because we could predict them</text><text start="3443.28" dur="6.36">from predators, the goats could decimate an
ecosystem of its plant life and yet it could</text><text start="3449.64" dur="4.38">convert a bunch of plants that we can&apos;t eat
into a bunch of goat milk or goat meat that</text><text start="3454.02" dur="0.54">we can eat.</text><text start="3454.56" dur="8.16">So I would say that was already an ability
for us to maximize caloric extraction at the</text><text start="3462.72" dur="1.68">cost of ecosystems.</text><text start="3464.4" dur="6.66">Then, the plow and animal husbandry was the
single biggest massive step, corresponding</text><text start="3471.06" dur="2.16">with mechanisms of storage.</text><text start="3473.22" dur="4.08">So that grains became really a thing and we&apos;ve
talked about that before.</text><text start="3477.3" dur="4.74">And then irrigation and hydrological systems
became a massive thing.</text><text start="3482.04" dur="3.3">So there were a few jumps in the thing that
we call the agrarian revolution, but they</text><text start="3485.34" dur="6.96">were all jumps in techne, all jumps in our
capacity to convert the rest of the environment</text><text start="3492.3" dur="5.1">into things useful for us, faster than the
rest of the environment could deal with the</text><text start="3497.4" dur="1.62">adaptive pressures we were putting on it.</text><text start="3499.02" dur="4.98">Nate Hagens:
And then we found the turbo booster in the</text><text start="3504.0" dur="3.78">18th century and 19th century with fossil
carbon and hydrocarbons.</text><text start="3507.78" dur="3.6">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And I would say</text><text start="3516.48" dur="4.86">you could look at all along before we used
fire to after we used fire, we started getting</text><text start="3521.34" dur="3.54">those extra somatic or extracorporeal calories
you&apos;re talking about, right?</text><text start="3526.92" dur="4.74">There&apos;s a lot of energy being burnt up in
that fire to be able to make food that I couldn&apos;t</text><text start="3531.66" dur="2.46">eat raw, food that I could eat when cooked,
right?</text><text start="3534.12" dur="7.2">So now the total amount of calorie per capita
is going up beyond the amount that people</text><text start="3541.32" dur="5.4">are eating, that is being used to warm the
homes and cook the food and all like that.</text><text start="3549.78" dur="1.44">So a few things happened.</text><text start="3551.22" dur="6.18">One was the population started growing and
two was the amount of resource per capita</text><text start="3557.4" dur="0.24">growth.</text><text start="3557.64" dur="4.74">So we&apos;re on an exponential resource curve,
both because of an exponential population</text><text start="3562.38" dur="3.72">curve and a resource per 
capita curve simultaneously.</text><text start="3566.76" dur="3.24">And each new technological innovation increased
this.</text><text start="3570.9" dur="4.86">Either allowed us to increase the population
faster or the resource per capita or both.</text><text start="3576.36" dur="6.6">And of course again, if you have a tribe that
says we&apos;re not going to use the plow, we think</text><text start="3582.96" dur="0.6">that&apos;s fucked.</text><text start="3583.56" dur="4.68">We don&apos;t want to yoke an animal and beat it
all day long because the spirit of the animal,</text><text start="3588.24" dur="4.38">we&apos;re going to keep our animistic ideas and
live in harmony with nature, then they&apos;re</text><text start="3592.62" dur="0.84">not going to grow their population.</text><text start="3593.46" dur="2.4">The one who does yolk it and beat it will
grow their population.</text><text start="3595.86" dur="2.7">They&apos;ll win in tribal warfare, wipe the other
ones out.</text><text start="3598.56" dur="5.28">And so the memes, the value systems, man&apos;s
dominion over whatever, that corresponds with</text><text start="3603.84" dur="1.92">the tool used, will be the ones that proliferate.</text><text start="3607.02" dur="5.94">And that means nothing about them being more
true or good or beautiful, it means them being</text><text start="3612.96" dur="2.52">more adaptive in short term zero sum type
games.</text><text start="3615.48" dur="4.44">Nate Hagens:
And it also doesn&apos;t mean that they were happier.</text><text start="3621.06" dur="6.0">The tribe that remained animist might have
had happy, healthy lives, they just died out</text><text start="3627.06" dur="2.916">because they weren&apos;t competitive versus the
other tribe.</text><text start="3629.976" dur="2.184">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Now I have to come to, because since I just</text><text start="3632.16" dur="0.96">mentioned zero sum.</text><text start="3633.78" dur="5.58">If you look at a book like Nonzero by Robert
Wright that argues that the long arc of history</text><text start="3639.36" dur="4.92">is that humans have been 
more and more positive-some </text><text start="3644.28" dur="4.32">in their dynamics via moving from tiny bands</text><text start="3648.6" dur="3.96">to tribes to much larger groups that have
division of labor across the larger group</text><text start="3652.56" dur="1.98">where each person, rather than have to do </text><text start="3654.54" dur="2.46">everything they would need 
to survive by themselves,</text><text start="3657.0" dur="4.2">is able to do specialty roles because of trade
where they can depend on others so that you</text><text start="3661.2" dur="3.06">get more specialization, so you get more total
goodness.</text><text start="3666.12" dur="3.9">And that inside of the 
group, you get fundamentally </text><text start="3670.02" dur="2.46">positive sum behaviors getting selected for</text><text start="3672.48" dur="0.18">cause.</text><text start="3672.66" dur="2.34">The group that does more positive some behaviors
gets through.</text><text start="3675.0" dur="6.96">This is partly true, and it&apos;s key to underlying
the kind of Pinker-Rosling narrative on the</text><text start="3681.96" dur="0.96">things that are getting better.</text><text start="3683.58" dur="7.92">But it&apos;s of course also true that the group
that does more coordination or positive sum</text><text start="3691.5" dur="7.38">type of behavior within that in group does
better in a war with an out group.</text><text start="3698.88" dur="2.94">And the war is zero sum or even negative sum.</text><text start="3701.82" dur="5.16">And the pressure of the war forces that other
thing to happen.</text><text start="3707.64" dur="9.48">And so there is a relationship between positive
sum things and zero sum things that has to</text><text start="3717.12" dur="0.84">be factored together.</text><text start="3717.96" dur="4.98">And it&apos;s also true that what was positive
some for the humans within the group, was</text><text start="3722.94" dur="1.2">negative sum for nature.</text><text start="3725.28" dur="5.1">It was those humans coordinating with more
diversity and specialization, which meant</text><text start="3730.38" dur="4.32">more people able to extract more stuff from
nature and turn it into useful stuff from</text><text start="3734.7" dur="2.16">humans at the cost of the ecosystems.</text><text start="3736.86" dur="4.02">And then the zero sum dynamics with other
groups, meaning they had to race to do it</text><text start="3740.88" dur="1.2">faster than the other groups.</text><text start="3742.08" dur="7.2">Thus, the net effect of the total human social
activity was debasing the ecosystem that it</text><text start="3749.28" dur="0.6">depended upon.</text><text start="3750.72" dur="4.92">And so that&apos;s the other key thing we have
to get is that when we&apos;re talking zero sum</text><text start="3755.64" dur="4.86">or positive sum, it&apos;s always the pressure
between the two of those and that all of them,</text><text start="3760.5" dur="6.24">including the positive sum ones are positive
sum between humans, which is still externalizing</text><text start="3766.74" dur="1.2">the cost to nature.</text><text start="3767.94" dur="3.96">And that&apos;s a really critical thing to get
as we&apos;re getting near the planetary boundaries</text><text start="3771.9" dur="0.24">now.</text><text start="3772.14" dur="6.36">Nate Hagens:
So our anthropocentric bias has started long</text><text start="3778.5" dur="0.36">ago.</text><text start="3783.6" dur="2.88">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
When we talk about the agricultural revolution,</text><text start="3786.48" dur="7.74">we start moving from Dunbar size tribes to
early city states of a hundred thousand and</text><text start="3794.22" dur="0.78">then a million people.</text><text start="3795.0" dur="7.32">And with them, you get the earliest kind of
formalized religions and you get massive class</text><text start="3802.32" dur="4.716">systems, hierarchy, different kinds of division
on gender roles.</text><text start="3807.036" dur="3.324">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
So the social systems and the cultures change</text><text start="3810.36" dur="0.96">correspondingly.</text><text start="3811.32" dur="7.8">Once you get a whole lot of grain that is
better storable calorie than the meat of the</text><text start="3819.12" dur="6.72">vegetable stuff earlier, you start to also
get way more class system because who owns</text><text start="3825.84" dur="6.84">that starts to be very unevenly provisioned
and then with the class system emerges all</text><text start="3832.68" dur="4.14">the aspects of social hierarchy and all that,
you also now get more incentive to get raided</text><text start="3836.82" dur="1.14">for all your surplus.</text><text start="3837.96" dur="2.46">And so you have more incentive for the tribal
warfare.</text><text start="3840.42" dur="3.36">So now you have to make more defenses around
it and on and on.</text><text start="3845.76" dur="7.32">Before we get to oil, we get lots of innovations
during that time that have from obviously</text><text start="3853.08" dur="3.36">the water wheels being used to the on and
on.</text><text start="3856.44" dur="8.76">But we do get a pretty massive jump at oil
and people talk about the fourth industrial</text><text start="3865.2" dur="1.14">revolution that we&apos;re in now.</text><text start="3866.34" dur="4.5">The first industrial revolution being oil,
the second being electricity, the third being</text><text start="3870.84" dur="4.44">computation, the fourth, now being AI and
all the Kurzweil exponential tech.</text><text start="3876.84" dur="1.2">That&apos;s a roughly good model.</text><text start="3878.04" dur="5.58">We could, some people talk about six industrial
revolutions but basically we can look at that.</text><text start="3883.62" dur="4.62">There&apos;s like a step function in tech and then
a whole bunch of evolution within that epoch</text><text start="3888.24" dur="3.18">and then another step function and then evolution
within the epoch.</text><text start="3891.42" dur="4.5">Nate Hagens:
So I would put an asterisk on that.</text><text start="3895.92" dur="8.82">That those revolutions all happened while
the total scale and quality of energy for</text><text start="3904.74" dur="8.28">the human enterprise was increasing every
single year other than the 1930s, 2020, 2009.</text><text start="3913.02" dur="6.84">And at some point the depletion part of the
story for coal oil and natural gas, of which</text><text start="3919.86" dur="5.34">we get a hundred billion barrel of oil equivalents
per year, which is 500 billion human labor</text><text start="3925.2" dur="1.02">equivalent worth.</text><text start="3926.22" dur="5.4">Although you once told me that was a gibberish
number, but plus or minus, even if it&apos;s a</text><text start="3931.62" dur="5.82">hundred billion, it&apos;s a lot what happens with
those revolutions.</text><text start="3937.44" dur="6.9">The tech revolutions, the industrial revolutions
as we have fewer of those exogenous laborers,</text><text start="3944.34" dur="5.34">fossil laborers added to our economy is a
question I think about a lot.</text><text start="3949.68" dur="1.74">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="3954.06" dur="6.72">When you demonstrate, in the animation you
made the carbon pulse, and how significant</text><text start="3960.78" dur="3.0">the step function that was 
and it really corresponds </text><text start="3963.78" dur="3.12">to population well, right, from the agricultural</text><text start="3966.9" dur="5.76">revolution until the industrial revolution,
the population stayed under a half a billion</text><text start="3972.66" dur="0.6">give or take.</text><text start="3973.26" dur="8.16">And to go from a half a billion to eight billion
in 300 years, given 10,000 years under a half</text><text start="3981.42" dur="2.04">a billion, you&apos;re like, &quot;Whoa, that&apos;s huge.&quot;</text><text start="3983.46" dur="8.52">And we hit the first billion at 1815 and that
the other technologies that sit on top of</text><text start="3991.98" dur="5.94">that, the electrification, the computer-ification
of everything, sit on top of and  </text><text start="3999.18" dur="2.04">used at underlying</text><text start="4001.22" dur="5.4">energy substrate that as soon as we hit the
point of diminishing energy return on energy</text><text start="4006.62" dur="2.94">investment of that energy substrate, the story
starts to change.</text><text start="4009.56" dur="6.18">We hit an inflection point in the story and
this is what I think is so important about,</text><text start="4015.74" dur="7.5">I mean, one of the things I think is so important
about your work is that it&apos;s kind of obvious</text><text start="4023.24" dur="10.92">when you zoom back that the exponential growth
requirements of the economy and the finite</text><text start="4034.16" dur="2.64">planetary boundaries of earth are incompatible.</text><text start="4036.8" dur="1.968">That thing doesn&apos;t get to go forever and that&apos;s-</text><text start="4038.768" dur="2.832">Nate Hagens:
It is kind of obvious, but I really don&apos;t</text><text start="4041.6" dur="8.22">know if more than a quarter percent, I mean
25% of the population sees that, maybe intuitively</text><text start="4049.82" dur="1.8">or in their gut they do.</text><text start="4051.62" dur="4.86">But that sentence you just said should be
understood by a first grader.</text><text start="4056.48" dur="1.38">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yes.</text><text start="4057.86" dur="5.1">And it is, I think it&apos;s a fair thing to say.</text><text start="4063.56" dur="2.64">Let&apos;s get everybody to understand that and
start to wrestle with it.</text><text start="4066.2" dur="1.02">So let&apos;s say it again.</text><text start="4071.72" dur="5.34">So originally the financial, what does originally
mean with the financial system?</text><text start="4077.06" dur="13.32">We can go back to shell&apos;s mediating barter,
the idea of having a currency that was not</text><text start="4090.38" dur="6.42">the value itself but was an accepted mediation
for things that have value for goods and services,</text><text start="4101.54" dur="7.98">it&apos;s supposed to be that money equals access
to an ability to exchange goods and services.</text><text start="4109.52" dur="2.52">What we&apos;re ultimately interested in is goods
and services.</text><text start="4112.04" dur="5.16">But of course as soon as you start getting
banking and you start getting the concept</text><text start="4117.2" dur="4.02">of interest, because if I loan you some money,
I stop having access to be creative with it.</text><text start="4121.22" dur="3.6">And if I was creative and I was growing stuff,
I&apos;d be growing it during that time.</text><text start="4124.82" dur="2.34">So when you pay me back, you pay me back with
some interest.</text><text start="4127.16" dur="4.08">That represents the growth that I would&apos;ve
had had I kept it, which all seems reasonable.</text><text start="4131.9" dur="5.64">Now we get a situation where the financial
system has its own physics, right?</text><text start="4137.54" dur="4.14">There is a compounding interest of you&apos;re
going to make whatever percent return you</text><text start="4141.68" dur="3.66">get and then if you leave it in there the
next year you&apos;re going to make compounding</text><text start="4145.34" dur="0.9">return on that much.</text><text start="4146.24" dur="3.96">Again, compounding return curves give you
exponential growth rate.</text><text start="4150.2" dur="5.4">So the whole global financial system has an
embedded growth obligation that is exponential,</text><text start="4156.38" dur="7.5">meaning there has to be exponentially more
total currency in the system every year than</text><text start="4163.88" dur="0.36">previous.</text><text start="4165.26" dur="7.08">And then to not debase the value of the currency,
that means there has to be exponentially more</text><text start="4172.34" dur="1.68">goods and services that it&apos;s related to.</text><text start="4174.02" dur="3.12">Otherwise you debase the value of the currency
and the financial system collapses.</text><text start="4177.14" dur="7.5">So now the physics of the financial system,
rather than the financial system being indexed</text><text start="4184.64" dur="4.5">to the real goods and services now the real
goods and services are indexed to the financial</text><text start="4189.14" dur="4.62">system where the embedded growth obligation,
just to keep up with interest let alone the</text><text start="4193.76" dur="5.88">many other aspects of the financial system
that create embedded growth obligation, mean</text><text start="4199.64" dur="7.56">that there is a demand for exponential extraction
and exponential energy moving through the</text><text start="4207.2" dur="2.16">materials economy turning 
into waste and pollution.</text><text start="4209.36" dur="8.4">You cannot run exponentially more of a finite
planet through a linear materials economy</text><text start="4217.76" dur="4.8">that has limits on both the front and backside
of that linear materials economy forever.</text><text start="4222.56" dur="3.18">So you hit limits of growth 
or planetary boundaries.</text><text start="4225.74" dur="4.02">Nate Hagens:
And since our last conversation there&apos;s been</text><text start="4229.76" dur="11.28">a wellspring of media and research and Twitter
comments and TED talks not so much about the</text><text start="4241.04" dur="6.06">energy side because that&apos;s been known but
about the material limits, because lithium</text><text start="4247.1" dur="4.14">is 900% more costly than it was a few years
ago.</text><text start="4253.58" dur="8.88">A woman named Olivia Lazard is going to be
on this show soon and she has a pithy phrase</text><text start="4262.46" dur="9.3">which I like, which is in an attempt to decouple
our economy from carbon, we will recouple</text><text start="4271.76" dur="1.92">our economy to materials.</text><text start="4274.46" dur="9.12">So there&apos;s an exponential driver there on
materials needed for any energy infrastructure</text><text start="4283.58" dur="1.08">scaling.</text><text start="4284.66" dur="1.14">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Right.</text><text start="4287.12" dur="9.48">So as you point out so well, the hydrocarbons
are a very energy dense source of energy.</text><text start="4296.6" dur="8.1">And for transportation in particular, this
is very useful, the storage dynamic.</text><text start="4304.7" dur="5.46">So either if we want to get off them, you
need a lot of batteries or you need to make</text><text start="4310.16" dur="3.06">hydrogen fuel safe or something like that.</text><text start="4313.22" dur="6.9">And if you want to move to renewables for
the grid, you still need a lot of storage</text><text start="4320.12" dur="4.8">because of intermittency and you need all
the materials necessary to make the windmills,</text><text start="4324.92" dur="7.26">the solar panels, whatever other physical
technology.</text><text start="4334.22" dur="0.588">Go ahead.</text><text start="4334.808" dur="0.672">Nate Hagens:
I just had a thought.</text><text start="4335.48" dur="4.02">Is that trade off or that choice or that path, </text><text start="4340.28" dur="3.18">similar to what you said 
earlier in this conversation</text><text start="4343.46" dur="4.44">about a nation choosing to not grow?</text><text start="4347.9" dur="8.34">So a nation that chooses to live differently
using renewable flows is giving up some of</text><text start="4356.24" dur="1.86">the other attributes.</text><text start="4358.1" dur="7.26">There&apos;s a lot of nations that try to do a
hundred percent or a large percentage of renewable</text><text start="4365.36" dur="5.34">energy in their electricity sector, which
globally is only around 20% of our energy.</text><text start="4370.7" dur="1.8">But look at Germany right now.</text><text start="4372.5" dur="5.52">They were the poster child of let&apos;s do the
right thing environmentally and let&apos;s build</text><text start="4378.02" dur="2.1">a low carbon economy.</text><text start="4380.12" dur="10.5">But now energy security is taking front seat
over low carbon transition and look at what&apos;s</text><text start="4390.62" dur="1.351">happening to Germany economically.</text><text start="4391.971" dur="0.029">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="4392.0" dur="5.1">You were seeing... so they were focused on
building a low carbon economy in terms of</text><text start="4397.1" dur="6.48">their domestic production of energy, but obviously
their carbon demands were imported when they</text><text start="4403.58" dur="1.458">stopped being able to import it.</text><text start="4405.038" dur="0.018">Nate Hagens:
Right.</text><text start="4405.056" dur="1.824">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Now they have to make up for it.</text><text start="4406.88" dur="4.62">This is a point that you and I mentioned in
the first or second one, which is that the</text><text start="4411.5" dur="4.44">sustainability metrics we look at have to
be global, not national because otherwise</text><text start="4415.94" dur="3.66">you just export your shitty environmental
metrics somewhere else.</text><text start="4419.6" dur="8.04">So it&apos;s easy to say, &quot;Look, we produce more
dollars per joule than other countries.</text><text start="4427.64" dur="7.98">So we&apos;re beating the Garrett Relation because
we don&apos;t do any mining or infrastructure in</text><text start="4435.62" dur="0.3">our country.</text><text start="4435.92" dur="5.46">We do software, but in order to meet all of
our needs, we&apos;re using money to import that</text><text start="4441.38" dur="1.8">stuff from countries that do that.&quot;</text><text start="4443.18" dur="4.44">And if you balance it out, the energy and </text><text start="4447.62" dur="3.9">joule dynamic is 99% coupled 
or our Gini coefficient</text><text start="4451.52" dur="3.84">is better, meaning our poorest people relative
to our wealthiest people, there&apos;s less of</text><text start="4455.36" dur="3.66">a gap but it&apos;s because we import all the stuff
from countries that have slave labor.</text><text start="4459.02" dur="6.06">And so if you really want to see how good
a country&apos;s doing, you also have to factor</text><text start="4465.08" dur="3.42">its import export dynamics and figure out
how to do attribution on that.</text><text start="4468.5" dur="4.68">Nate Hagens:
So real quick, ten second stat.</text><text start="4473.18" dur="5.16">The average American, meaning you take all
of our energy and divide by 330 million people</text><text start="4478.34" dur="5.1">uses 57 barrel of oil equivalents of fossil
fuels per year.</text><text start="4483.44" dur="7.08">And we use another 17 that are burned in other
countries in the finished products that we</text><text start="4490.52" dur="0.24">buy.</text><text start="4490.76" dur="1.86">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah.</text><text start="4492.62" dur="7.86">There&apos;s also the very good, there&apos;s an online
slave calculator where you put in the how</text><text start="4500.48" dur="3.9">many plane flights you use and how many kilowatts
your house uses and how much stuff you buy,</text><text start="4504.38" dur="1.2">how many people in your household.</text><text start="4505.58" dur="7.68">And it says how many people are in the third
world in slave like or indentured servitude</text><text start="4513.26" dur="1.62">positions to make your life work.</text><text start="4515.84" dur="0.82">That&apos;s another-</text><text start="4516.66" dur="1.016">Nate Hagens:
Oh god, I&apos;ve never seen that.</text><text start="4517.676" dur="2.544">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, it&apos;s another eye-opening one because</text><text start="4520.22" dur="5.88">again the Gini coefficient in my country might
be really nice, but the Gini coefficient in</text><text start="4526.1" dur="3.72">the supply chain that my life depends upon
is probably not very nice.</text><text start="4531.74" dur="4.26">And so again, this is where we have global
dependency, global effects.</text><text start="4536.0" dur="3.48">So you have to have global governance otherwise
everybody just does, &quot;not in my backyard&quot;</text><text start="4539.48" dur="5.7">and sends the messed up stuff to countries
that don&apos;t really have much of a choice and</text><text start="4545.18" dur="2.34">then has plausible deniability on their own
metrics.</text><text start="4547.52" dur="1.02">But it&apos;s like that&apos;s not real.</text><text start="4549.56" dur="4.38">Nate Hagens:
Well I sure am looking forward, probably not</text><text start="4553.94" dur="5.76">on this episode, but I&apos;m really keen to hear
your insights and wisdom on the possibility</text><text start="4559.7" dur="5.28">and the pathway towards global governance
because boy what&apos;s going on in the world right</text><text start="4564.98" dur="3.24">now seems like we&apos;re moving further away from
that than towards it-</text><text start="4568.22" dur="3.42">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And I want to say just because it&apos;s such an</text><text start="4571.64" dur="6.9">easy knee-jerk reaction to have that when
I say global governance, what I mean is global</text><text start="4578.54" dur="6.96">government that this is some new world order,
one world government agenda for top down total</text><text start="4585.5" dur="4.68">control in the debasement of good nationalism
and checks and balances on power and blah</text><text start="4590.18" dur="0.42">blah blah.</text><text start="4592.34" dur="1.44">No of course I don&apos;t want that.</text><text start="4593.78" dur="6.12">No thinking person wants that unless they
assume they&apos;re the one who runs the thing,</text><text start="4599.9" dur="1.08">in which case they probably do.</text><text start="4601.76" dur="7.48">And that&apos;s important because... but this is
the trade off we have to deal with.</text><text start="4609.24" dur="1.7">Nate Hagens:
I think there&apos;s a good... there&apos;s a reasonable</text><text start="4610.94" dur="2.04">percentage of the environmental movement that </text><text start="4612.98" dur="3.036">wants that, some sort of 
environmental authoritarianism...</text><text start="4616.016" dur="4.284">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Unfortunately they probably have over focused</text><text start="4620.3" dur="5.22">on the environment and under focused on other
critical aspects of what makes the world not</text><text start="4625.52" dur="6.36">suck or suck to that they&apos;re not realizing
how dystopic a system that has no checks and</text><text start="4631.88" dur="1.02">balances on power would be.</text><text start="4632.9" dur="2.34">Humans don&apos;t have a good track record  </text><text start="4635.24" dur="1.26">at stewarding
power well.</text><text start="4636.5" dur="1.68">Noblesse Oblige.</text><text start="4638.18" dur="6.48">The obligation of the nobility class to be
noble does not have a good statistical track</text><text start="4644.66" dur="0.66">record, right?</text><text start="4645.32" dur="4.44">That power is abused pretty universally has
a better track record.</text><text start="4650.6" dur="6.12">And so we talk about the third attractor where
there&apos;s currently two attractor states for</text><text start="4656.72" dur="4.98">the future, meaning states that are most likely
based on the kind of general dynamics we&apos;re</text><text start="4661.7" dur="0.18">on.</text><text start="4661.88" dur="2.46">There&apos;s an attractor state 
of increasing catastrophes </text><text start="4664.34" dur="2.4">and there&apos;s an attractor state of increasing</text><text start="4666.74" dur="1.2">dystopias.</text><text start="4667.94" dur="4.98">The catastrophes largely result from not having
more coordinated governance.</text><text start="4672.92" dur="6.36">And so everybody, all the countries racing
to grow their GDP to grow their military presence</text><text start="4679.28" dur="6.24">and things like that, equals passing planetary
boundaries and the destruction of the environment</text><text start="4685.52" dur="4.56">and that leads to cascading catastrophes of
lots of types.</text><text start="4690.08" dur="5.34">Climate change leads to extreme weather events,
leads to human migration, leads to resource</text><text start="4695.42" dur="4.32">wars, leads to large scale wars, leads to
breakdown of infrastructure and supply chain,</text><text start="4699.74" dur="2.64">leads to more resource wars, blah blah blah.</text><text start="4702.38" dur="0.12">Right?</text><text start="4702.5" dur="3.9">So that&apos;s the catastrophe model and there&apos;s
a million different ways that can go.</text><text start="4707.24" dur="5.1">To avoid that model, you have to be able to
prevent those bad things from happening.</text><text start="4712.34" dur="8.1">You have to prevent people in the age of cheaper
and cheaper gene synthesis capabilities, from</text><text start="4720.44" dur="2.58">building pandemic weapons in their basements
in the next few years.</text><text start="4723.02" dur="4.5">You have to prevent all the countries from
racing forward on using up all the resources</text><text start="4727.52" dur="2.28">as fast as they can in competition with each
other.</text><text start="4729.8" dur="3.24">You have to prevent them from military escalation
and whatever.</text><text start="4733.04" dur="4.98">In order to do that you have to have some
powerful control systems because incentives</text><text start="4738.02" dur="0.84">alone won&apos;t do it.</text><text start="4738.86" dur="4.08">You will need deterrents and we can do some
proofs of why incentives alone don&apos;t do it.</text><text start="4743.78" dur="7.98">Well if you create powerful enough control
systems to check all the exponential tech</text><text start="4751.76" dur="5.1">and to check all of the externalities, how
does that not become dystopic?</text><text start="4756.86" dur="1.98">How do you have checks and balances on something </text><text start="4758.84" dur="2.28">that has that much assymetry 
of power on everything</text><text start="4761.12" dur="0.48">else?</text><text start="4761.6" dur="5.88">So one attractor is increasing catastrophes,
the other is that the answer to the increasing</text><text start="4767.48" dur="6.06">catastrophes is control mechanisms with no
checks and balances that become top down dystopic</text><text start="4773.54" dur="0.42">forces.</text><text start="4773.96" dur="4.38">And even if we say, &quot;No, no, no, they won&apos;t
be because we will make sure that there is</text><text start="4778.34" dur="8.82">some good process of jurisprudence bound to
the collective will of the people somehow</text><text start="4787.16" dur="5.82">and transparency and checks and balances,&quot;
If you make a system that&apos;s centralized, even</text><text start="4792.98" dur="5.22">if the initial governance of it is good, isn&apos;t
it capturable by negative forces eventually?</text><text start="4798.2" dur="5.58">So how do you make a system that has that
much power that is not capturable or corruptible?</text><text start="4803.78" dur="1.2">That&apos;s the other big question.</text><text start="4804.98" dur="6.0">So the third attractor we&apos;re looking for is
able to prevent all the catastrophes and have</text><text start="4810.98" dur="9.06">the coordination system that does that not
be corruptible or capturable and that is threading</text><text start="4820.04" dur="0.96">the eye of a needle.</text><text start="4821.0" dur="6.66">And I don&apos;t think it is impossible and it&apos;s
also not easy.</text><text start="4827.66" dur="5.64">Nate Hagens:
Yeah, I&apos;ve heard you say that many times or</text><text start="4833.3" dur="3.42">some version of that and it sounds great.</text><text start="4836.72" dur="1.56">I agree.</text><text start="4839.12" dur="11.76">So let&apos;s thread the needle and I may be naive,
probably am naive, but I still believe that</text><text start="4850.88" dur="7.74">people listening to this program and people
meeting each other that are developing and</text><text start="4858.62" dur="6.42">understanding and a vocabulary and an awareness
of the time and place that we are all on this</text><text start="4865.04" dur="0.54">planet together.</text><text start="4865.58" dur="6.54">Roughly eight to 10% of homo sapiens of all
time are alive right now.</text><text start="4872.12" dur="6.54">That this is, we have to recognize how we
got here in order to change where we&apos;re going.</text><text start="4878.66" dur="7.26">And I&apos;m hopeful that something emergent happens,
but I just don&apos;t know, I think we&apos;re going</text><text start="4885.92" dur="3.96">to have to use less materially and we&apos;re not
going to choose to do that.</text><text start="4889.88" dur="8.94">And there are dangers on both sides, like
you said, oppression and catastrophe.</text><text start="4899.54" dur="7.68">So I really am keen to get to the point of
this conversation where we frame out possible</text><text start="4907.22" dur="3.24">responses at the international level, at the </text><text start="4910.46" dur="3.36">national level and you&apos;re 
probably less interested,</text><text start="4913.82" dur="4.8">but I also want to talk about responses at
the community and individual levels.</text><text start="4918.62" dur="6.78">So what else would you like to cover on the
macro overview before we get to that point?</text><text start="4926.06" dur="3.36">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, you were talking about some percentage</text><text start="4929.42" dur="6.3">of homo sapiens coming to understand how we
got here.</text><text start="4935.72" dur="5.34">I want to come back to the argument we had
at the beginning of what is unique about homo</text><text start="4941.06" dur="4.2">sapiens, to say let&apos;s have some percentage
of homo sapiens understand what is unique</text><text start="4945.26" dur="12.6">about them that then also says what must become
true of them, factoring that because we haven&apos;t</text><text start="4957.86" dur="1.02">said that quite clearly enough.</text><text start="4960.92" dur="5.82">We were obviously the result of evolutionary
process but we were the result of evolutionary</text><text start="4966.74" dur="4.86">process that gave us the ability to increase
our adaptive capacity relative to everything</text><text start="4971.6" dur="3.9">else in a way that is different than the rest
of evolutionary process.</text><text start="4975.5" dur="2.04">It is no longer genetic mutation  </text><text start="4978.8" dur="3.3">that is determining
our adaptive capacity.</text><text start="4982.1" dur="4.74">So if you want to understand the adaptive
capacity of humans first it wasn&apos;t individual</text><text start="4986.84" dur="1.26">humans that were selected for.</text><text start="4988.1" dur="3.84">There were very few places where they were
individual, solo humans, it was groups of</text><text start="4991.94" dur="4.62">humans and it was groups of humans with their
coordination mechanisms that were themselves</text><text start="4996.56" dur="6.78">the result of our capacity for abstraction
where we did language and we left markers</text><text start="5003.34" dur="4.2">for each other and we started to do early
things and then obviously written language</text><text start="5007.54" dur="0.42">and whatever.</text><text start="5008.68" dur="3.06">But it was also those early humans with our
tools.</text><text start="5011.74" dur="6.18">It wasn&apos;t a group of humans with their bare
hands that could take down a mammoth and it</text><text start="5017.92" dur="2.82">wasn&apos;t an individual human with a spear that
could take down a mammoth.</text><text start="5020.74" dur="2.64">It was a group of humans 
with spears and coordination </text><text start="5023.38" dur="1.2">that could do that.</text><text start="5024.58" dur="1.652">And obviously-</text><text start="5026.232" dur="3.208">Nate Hagens:
So coordination and technology were both required?</text><text start="5029.44" dur="3.78">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, we talked before about Marvin Harris&apos;s</text><text start="5033.22" dur="5.4">model, that a civilization can be modeled
in terms of its infrastructure, its social</text><text start="5038.62" dur="1.44">structure and its super structure.</text><text start="5040.06" dur="6.78">Its infrastructure is the physical tooling
that it mediates meeting its physical needs</text><text start="5046.84" dur="5.76">with, its social structure is the collective
agreement field law, basically, law governance</text><text start="5052.6" dur="8.28">and its super structure is its shared values
that are hopefully the basis of its law and</text><text start="5060.88" dur="2.4">its coordination, what it&apos;s coordinating in
service to.</text><text start="5063.28" dur="4.32">So it might be its religion, its clan identity,
it&apos;s national identity, whatever.</text><text start="5068.44" dur="7.68">So we can say that from early on humans, what
was being selected for was groups of humans</text><text start="5076.12" dur="3.12">with their infrastructure, social structure
and super structure.</text><text start="5080.38" dur="5.58">So it was groups of humans with their entire
tech stack because also it wasn&apos;t like, it&apos;s</text><text start="5085.96" dur="6.84">not the spear, it&apos;s also the hammer that we
used to make the spear and the ability to</text><text start="5092.8" dur="3.9">latch it onto... with leathers to the base.</text><text start="5096.7" dur="4.62">And it was also the fact that we were able
to feed ourselves with previously stored stuff</text><text start="5101.32" dur="3.84">because of the capacity to dry meats and store
them in storage vessels.</text><text start="5105.16" dur="2.04">It was that whole interrelated tech stack.</text><text start="5107.2" dur="0.48">Right?</text><text start="5107.68" dur="6.48">And so what was selected for was the group
of humans, their coordination mechanisms,</text><text start="5114.16" dur="4.08">which included their social structure and
their super structure and their tech stack.</text><text start="5118.24" dur="6.12">And then groups of humans relative to each
other were in inter tribal coordination.</text><text start="5124.36" dur="1.86">They would trade but also conflict.</text><text start="5126.22" dur="4.44">They would war, which drove them to up-regulate
relative to each other.</text><text start="5130.66" dur="6.9">But all of them were up-regulating relative
to nature on vastly faster time scales, meaning</text><text start="5137.56" dur="2.7">able to convert more of nature into human
useful stuff.</text><text start="5143.56" dur="5.88">And so given our capacity, so the first thing
I want to say is you can&apos;t think about sapiens</text><text start="5149.44" dur="2.34">without thinking about the group of sapiens.</text><text start="5151.78" dur="2.4">It&apos;s coordination mechanisms and it&apos;s tooling.</text><text start="5154.18" dur="3.12">Like implicit in us is all of that.</text><text start="5157.3" dur="5.34">Because we were not selected for based on
what&apos;s in our genome, it&apos;s our genome plus</text><text start="5162.64" dur="1.2">the extension of that.</text><text start="5163.84" dur="1.5">That was actually what was selected for.</text><text start="5165.34" dur="1.74">So when you think about sapiens, you actually </text><text start="5167.08" dur="2.76">have to think about the tech 
stack, the coordination,</text><text start="5169.84" dur="2.82">you have to think about all of that as a thing
that&apos;s being selected for.</text><text start="5172.66" dur="10.92">And then to say, because we have the ability
to build these adaptive abstractions on top</text><text start="5183.58" dur="6.96">of each other, recursively faster than nature
can build resilience to that we have the ability</text><text start="5190.54" dur="5.64">to advantage ourselves at the expense of each
other and at the expense of nature.</text><text start="5196.18" dur="4.44">But in so far as at the expense of each other
drives us both up, it&apos;s all at the expense</text><text start="5200.62" dur="0.48">of nature.</text><text start="5202.66" dur="4.02">We have the ability to destroy whole ecosystems
in a way that no other animal can.</text><text start="5207.28" dur="5.94">We have the ability now to genetically engineer
new creatures.</text><text start="5213.22" dur="5.1">We have the ability to... it&apos;s so easy to
see that we are not apex predators.</text><text start="5218.32" dur="5.88">When you think about a polar bear on a rampage,
how much destruction it could do versus what&apos;s</text><text start="5224.2" dur="4.86">the video of the Tsar bomb when we detonated
a large nuclear weapon, it&apos;s like we just</text><text start="5229.06" dur="1.62">are not apex predators.</text><text start="5230.68" dur="1.44">We&apos;re a totally different creature.</text><text start="5233.32" dur="4.86">Because we have the capacity to ruin the biosphere
upon which we depend, we have the necessity</text><text start="5238.18" dur="0.78">to steward it.</text><text start="5240.7" dur="5.52">But no other animal has to consciously steward
all of the ecosystem because they don&apos;t have</text><text start="5246.22" dur="1.32">the capacity to destroy it.</text><text start="5247.54" dur="5.22">The ecosystem as a whole stewards itself because
of the relative symmetries of power of everything</text><text start="5252.76" dur="4.56">with everything because we broke those relative
symmetries of power and we have so much power</text><text start="5257.32" dur="1.26">relative to everything else.</text><text start="5258.58" dur="7.38">Either we use that power in service of everything
or in service of our own short term interests,</text><text start="5265.96" dur="1.62">we debase our long term existence.</text><text start="5267.58" dur="3.6">That&apos;s the new super structure that we have
to get.</text><text start="5271.18" dur="4.74">I am because we are, and the we extends to
not just our in group but all people.</text><text start="5275.92" dur="1.86">Because otherwise our in group is in an arms </text><text start="5277.78" dur="3.12">race with others that 
eventually is too destructive</text><text start="5280.9" dur="1.14">for anybody to make it through.</text><text start="5282.04" dur="4.98">But I am because we are, where the we means
everything that we depend upon, which means</text><text start="5287.02" dur="4.2">all the other inhabitants of the biosphere
that make it bio-inhabitable for us.</text><text start="5292.48" dur="10.32">So what I&apos;m saying is actually really simple
because our adaptive capacity has surpassed</text><text start="5302.8" dur="6.0">the process by which evolution usually creates
adaptive capacity, our motive also has to</text><text start="5308.8" dur="2.1">transcend normal evolutionary motive.</text><text start="5310.9" dur="4.92">Nate Hagens:
So does that come from education or  </text><text start="5316.66" dur="1.74">gut realization</text><text start="5318.4" dur="8.22">or cultural evolution and emergence or awareness
by elites?</text><text start="5327.58" dur="0.96">I don&apos;t know.</text><text start="5328.54" dur="3.48">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, all the above.</text><text start="5334.24" dur="7.5">There&apos;s obviously a disproportionate amount
of influence that some people have relative</text><text start="5341.74" dur="0.54">to other people.</text><text start="5342.28" dur="5.024">If you run a major financial institution or
you run a military or a nation state, so-</text><text start="5347.304" dur="3.556">Nate Hagens:
But all those people that you... those are</text><text start="5350.86" dur="6.96">hyper agents and they are going to try to
optimize their surplus to get more power in</text><text start="5357.82" dur="1.74">the game that you said earlier.</text><text start="5359.56" dur="5.46">So unless they recognize that they&apos;re going
to lose all that or they&apos;re going to lose</text><text start="5365.02" dur="6.48">their excess versus the rest of humans or
they&apos;re going to lose their planet or life</text><text start="5371.5" dur="5.46">because of a nuclear bomb or a runaway climate
change or something, they&apos;re still part of</text><text start="5376.96" dur="3.9">the rushing river going downstream with no
incentive to change.</text><text start="5380.86" dur="6.48">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, obviously the overall system disposition</text><text start="5387.34" dur="1.98">is kind of pulling everybody along with it.</text><text start="5389.98" dur="10.02">We do though, this same capacity for abstraction
that allows us to build whole built worlds</text><text start="5400.0" dur="6.84">that are different than the ones that we evolved
to fit into, this same capacity for abstraction</text><text start="5406.84" dur="5.64">can allow us to see this whole conversation
that you and I are having and say, &quot;Oh we</text><text start="5412.48" dur="3.9">actually have to get off 
of the current trajectory.</text><text start="5416.38" dur="0.96">What would it take to do that?</text><text start="5417.34" dur="2.28">What are minimum thresholds that it would
take to do that?</text><text start="5419.62" dur="1.86">And how do we go about bringing that about?&quot;</text><text start="5423.46" dur="10.08">Popular support absolutely does put real pressure
on economic and political lever pullers.</text><text start="5434.08" dur="3.54">So do you need a popular zeitgeist to change?</text><text start="5437.62" dur="1.32">Yes.</text><text start="5438.94" dur="5.4">Do you need people in key decision making
to change their understanding?</text><text start="5444.34" dur="0.72">Also yes.</text><text start="5445.06" dur="1.38">Those inter-inform each other.</text><text start="5446.44" dur="0.48">Both.</text><text start="5450.82" dur="6.78">And it&apos;s... what we&apos;re talking about is definitely
a cultural enlightenment of a particular type,</text><text start="5458.98" dur="4.68">a cultural enlightenment, meaning distributively,
everyone coming to understand the nature of</text><text start="5463.66" dur="5.1">the world they live in differently and better,
more clearly in a way that leads to different</text><text start="5468.76" dur="7.8">types of coordination and where the default
is, if I don&apos;t they&apos;re going to, therefore</text><text start="5476.56" dur="0.66">I have to.</text><text start="5477.22" dur="6.42">If that remains the default, we don&apos;t make
it for very long as a species or at least</text><text start="5483.64" dur="3.54">we have enough catastrophe that whoever makes
it through makes it through on a biosphere</text><text start="5487.18" dur="0.9">nobody wants to be on.</text><text start="5491.08" dur="6.36">And so we have to get off of the, if I don&apos;t
they&apos;re going to, so I have to, which means</text><text start="5497.44" dur="6.54">we have to get the capacity for coordination
that does not maximize short term self-interest.</text><text start="5503.98" dur="9.78">But that is absolutely aligned with both longer
term self-interest and a different definition</text><text start="5513.76" dur="1.26">of self-interest.</text><text start="5515.02" dur="5.58">Because as you were mentioning before, the
culture that did the plow might have been</text><text start="5520.6" dur="3.72">less happy overall, and we&apos;re not saying it
was, we&apos;re just saying might have been less</text><text start="5524.32" dur="2.04">happy or fulfilled than an animistic one.</text><text start="5526.36" dur="1.2">But that wasn&apos;t what mattered.</text><text start="5527.56" dur="5.26">The definition of best self-interest game
theoretically and the definition of best self</text><text start="5532.82" dur="2.54">interest in any other meaningful way are not
the same.</text><text start="5536.5" dur="5.82">And that&apos;s another really critical thing when
we talk about profit and what&apos;s fundamentally</text><text start="5542.32" dur="0.72">wrong with it.</text><text start="5543.04" dur="4.56">We enjoy breathing, we value breathing a lot.</text><text start="5547.6" dur="4.5">We don&apos;t pay for breathing because we all
just have access to an atmosphere.</text><text start="5552.76" dur="5.58">If I cut some trees down, is there less CO2
sequestered and less oxygen produced?</text><text start="5558.34" dur="7.02">So a worse atmosphere, yes, but so marginally
so that it affects my breathing, seemingly</text><text start="5565.36" dur="0.6">none at all.</text><text start="5565.96" dur="2.88">But I immediately get the value of that lumber.</text><text start="5568.84" dur="5.4">And so for me it makes total sense to cut
down these trees, get the immediate benefit,</text><text start="5574.24" dur="1.8">and still get the benefit of the atmosphere.</text><text start="5576.7" dur="3.84">Does everybody running that calculus threaten
the atmosphere as a whole?</text><text start="5580.54" dur="2.4">Yes, but unless we all agree to do something </text><text start="5582.94" dur="2.4">different, I don&apos;t want to 
be relatively disadvantaged</text><text start="5585.34" dur="5.16">and I notice the advantage of the trees more
than I notice the disadvantage of the decreased</text><text start="5590.5" dur="0.42">atmosphere.</text><text start="5590.92" dur="4.86">So none of us pay for the atmosphere even
though every other thing that we value isn&apos;t</text><text start="5595.78" dur="1.5">worth shit if we lose our atmosphere.</text><text start="5598.6" dur="7.14">And so if something is abundant, we don&apos;t
bother putting it in the accounting system</text><text start="5605.74" dur="0.42">at all.</text><text start="5606.16" dur="3.78">Therefore we end up damaging and debasing
it.</text><text start="5609.94" dur="8.16">We all want to watch the sunset and the sunrise
and to hear birds chirp, but we don&apos;t have</text><text start="5618.1" dur="0.6">to pay for that.</text><text start="5619.3" dur="10.68">And so what we end up putting our money into
is not things that we value, but the subset</text><text start="5629.98" dur="4.74">of things that we value that we can extract
that we wouldn&apos;t have access to without the</text><text start="5634.72" dur="6.24">money and that we can extract and exchange
for other type of game theoretical things.</text><text start="5640.96" dur="5.82">So this is, it&apos;s not just that we get the
value calculus wrong of we&apos;re not pricing</text><text start="5646.78" dur="2.76">in the real cost of the 
environmental externalities </text><text start="5649.54" dur="2.1">of the thing and what it would cost to produce</text><text start="5651.64" dur="0.3">a thing.</text><text start="5651.94" dur="5.64">It&apos;s also that what we put dollars into and
what we value don&apos;t equal each other because</text><text start="5657.58" dur="2.82">there&apos;s a lot of things we value that we don&apos;t
have to put dollars into.</text><text start="5660.4" dur="3.3">And if I did put some of 
my dollars into protecting </text><text start="5663.7" dur="2.64">those things, then I&apos;m not maximizing my return</text><text start="5666.34" dur="0.72">on agency.</text><text start="5667.06" dur="3.18">Because someone else who just takes those
things for granted and puts all their dollars</text><text start="5670.24" dur="2.4">into making more dollars ends up winning in
a war.</text><text start="5672.64" dur="6.9">And so what that means is what seems most
game theoretically beneficial and what actually</text><text start="5679.54" dur="2.4">optimizes for real value aren&apos;t the same thing.</text><text start="5681.94" dur="2.76">Game theoretical value and real value have
a major delta.</text><text start="5685.42" dur="5.04">So the thing that we&apos;re saying we have to
do does not equal a decrease in quality of</text><text start="5690.46" dur="0.24">life.</text><text start="5690.7" dur="5.22">It does equal a decrease in immediate game
theoretic capacity relative to someone else,</text><text start="5695.92" dur="4.56">but could be not only more sustainable long
term, but higher quality of life for everybody</text><text start="5700.48" dur="0.96">simultaneously.</text><text start="5701.44" dur="3.24">So long as we get off of that coordination
failure calculus.</text><text start="5704.68" dur="7.62">Nate Hagens:
But by the time we recognize the loss of the</text><text start="5712.3" dur="8.46">birds or the inability to breathe oxygen,
A, it&apos;ll be too late and we&apos;ll just miss them</text><text start="5721.84" dur="3.404">or not be around, and B, I guess the opportunity
is to currently use our ability to-</text><text start="5725.244" dur="3.556">Nate Hagens:
The opportunity is to currently use our ability</text><text start="5728.8" dur="9.48">to have abstractions and coordination to imagine
those costs and have that imagination influence</text><text start="5738.28" dur="2.557">our current behavior and governance, et cetera.</text><text start="5740.837" dur="0.516">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
That or bust.</text><text start="5741.353" dur="1.187">Nate Hagens:
That or bust.</text><text start="5744.1" dur="1.8">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Mm-hmm.</text><text start="5745.9" dur="1.68">Which I think maps to bend or break.</text><text start="5747.58" dur="8.1">Nate Hagens:
We have to queue up our next episode, which</text><text start="5755.68" dur="1.68">is going to be, what do we do?</text><text start="5757.36" dur="6.84">What is the framework, what is these four
introductions to the main course of how do</text><text start="5764.2" dur="1.2">we bend and not break?</text><text start="5765.4" dur="3.0">Let me first give you a chance to summarize.</text><text start="5768.4" dur="9.66">You talked a lot about homo sapiens history
of coordination, atoms, tools, inventions,</text><text start="5778.06" dur="0.6">fire.</text><text start="5780.34" dur="4.5">How does that correlate to 
our current macroeconomic </text><text start="5784.84" dur="0.6">overlay?</text><text start="5785.44" dur="2.46">How do those things all fit together?</text><text start="5787.9" dur="6.72">If you want to give a few minutes summary
that we can close on and then queue up the</text><text start="5794.62" dur="0.66">next episode.</text><text start="5798.7" dur="3.24">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
You and I talked before about how the super</text><text start="5801.94" dur="5.82">organism perspective that you&apos;ve shared, that
I think is really important and good, has</text><text start="5809.86" dur="6.0">put energy at the center of the consideration
and said the global human super organism is</text><text start="5815.86" dur="7.08">increasing its ability to use available energy
in the environment and convert everything</text><text start="5822.94" dur="1.68">in the environment to available energy.</text><text start="5824.62" dur="7.44">And that with the agricultural revolution,
it made a pretty big leap in its ability for</text><text start="5832.06" dur="0.96">caloric surplus.</text><text start="5833.02" dur="7.32">The ability to convert whole areas of ecosystem
into grazing land or monocrop land and be</text><text start="5840.34" dur="8.46">able to then convert that to storable grain
was a huge jump in how much calorie we could</text><text start="5848.8" dur="1.02">extract from nature.</text><text start="5849.82" dur="1.86">Obviously, we were mentioning that fire was </text><text start="5851.68" dur="3.6">a pretty big one even before 
that and agriculture&apos;s</text><text start="5855.28" dur="1.02">quite a few steps.</text><text start="5856.3" dur="7.44">And that the ability to extract hydrocarbon
energy and then turn that into tractors and</text><text start="5863.74" dur="2.76">everything was a massive step.</text><text start="5866.5" dur="5.1">And the way you visualized the hydrocarbon
pulse I think is really illuminating for people.</text><text start="5872.86" dur="7.74">But what we&apos;re looking at is thinking about
the maximum power principle from the point</text><text start="5880.6" dur="4.92">of view of a super organism, from the point
of view of energy return on energy investment.</text><text start="5886.12" dur="5.4">Even if we are already at the point of diminishing
energy return on energy investment, as long</text><text start="5891.52" dur="4.02">as there is positive return at all, meaning
we get back a little bit more energy than</text><text start="5895.54" dur="3.96">we put in, we&apos;ll continue to use energy to
do so.</text><text start="5899.5" dur="4.92">On a system purely of incentive, it takes
deterrent to do something other than that.</text><text start="5904.42" dur="4.98">And that we&apos;ve continued to innovate on methods
of extracting energy.</text><text start="5909.4" dur="4.62">We&apos;ve figured out how to take it from rock
that has uranium in it, when we hadn&apos;t realized</text><text start="5914.02" dur="0.3">that before.</text><text start="5914.32" dur="6.54">After figuring out how to take it from fossil
fuels, it seemed like a totally useless thing</text><text start="5920.86" dur="3.0">before and et cetera.</text><text start="5923.86" dur="1.2">What do we use the energy for?</text><text start="5927.64" dur="4.56">We use the energy to move stuff around and
to configure stuff into different forms that</text><text start="5932.2" dur="0.78">are useful for us.</text><text start="5932.98" dur="6.12">So the use of the energy and the movement
of atoms are correlated.</text><text start="5939.1" dur="7.86">We use the energy to mine atoms, to refine
them, to manufacture stuff out of them, to</text><text start="5946.96" dur="2.1">process the waste of them, move the waste </text><text start="5949.06" dur="5.46">out of our area and it 
takes information processing</text><text start="5954.52" dur="2.94">to be able to do all of this well.</text><text start="5957.46" dur="8.58">So there&apos;s this pretty tight coupling between
the utility associated with atoms, the utility</text><text start="5966.04" dur="2.88">of energy and the utility 
of the bits or information.</text><text start="5968.92" dur="3.72">And as we mentioned in terms of early humans, </text><text start="5972.64" dur="3.06">stone tools were beginning 
of recursive abstraction</text><text start="5975.7" dur="1.44">in the domain of atoms.</text><text start="5977.98" dur="4.26">Fire was one of the important leaps in the
domain of energy, but even the ability to</text><text start="5982.78" dur="5.28">use tools like clothing to maintain body heat
energy as opposed to dissipating it faster</text><text start="5988.06" dur="3.6">to make us adaptive in other environments
could already be thought of as innovations</text><text start="5992.2" dur="2.4">in energy and atoms intersecting each other.</text><text start="5996.1" dur="7.44">That language was this recursive abstraction
applied to information processing.</text><text start="6006.78" dur="6.12">And so right now we can see that with, what
some people call, the third industrial revolution</text><text start="6012.9" dur="5.34">computation, there&apos;s been this radical growth
and information processing and a lot of new</text><text start="6018.24" dur="4.2">types of services and value and change in
the manufacturer of goods that come from that.</text><text start="6023.22" dur="6.66">And a lot of people have this hope that the
information processing gives us the ability</text><text start="6029.88" dur="5.22">to produce more value per unit of energy and
per unit of physical goods.</text><text start="6035.1" dur="5.1">And therefore, we can keep growing GDP without
putting all of that as demand on the environment</text><text start="6040.2" dur="3.3">because we can just do it through growing
the value of software.</text><text start="6044.7" dur="1.177">And I think you and I-</text><text start="6045.877" dur="1.615">Nate Hagens:
Which will require materials and atoms.</text><text start="6047.492" dur="2.788">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
... You and I would both say yes and no.</text><text start="6050.28" dur="10.62">Yes, software might have less energy and material
demand per dollar worth of output, but that&apos;s</text><text start="6060.9" dur="2.46">not an exponential curve, it&apos;s another S-curve.</text><text start="6063.36" dur="5.88">Where eventually, you have a limit on human
attention and it doesn&apos;t matter how many movies</text><text start="6069.24" dur="3.78">there are or how much new software there is,
you get diminishing return on the value of</text><text start="6073.02" dur="2.46">the digital stuff limited to human attention
seconds.</text><text start="6076.38" dur="3.96">And then when what you&apos;re competing for, is
as you do more in the domain of software,</text><text start="6080.34" dur="4.92">you&apos;re either applying software to human attention
or you&apos;re applying it to the materials&apos; economy,</text><text start="6085.26" dur="0.84">because what else is there?</text><text start="6086.1" dur="3.96">So if you&apos;re applying it to the materials&apos;
economy, the innovation and software equals</text><text start="6090.06" dur="8.52">more efficiency at extracting atoms and energy,
extracting, converting whatever.</text><text start="6098.58" dur="2.88">Or it equals  </text><text start="6103.38" dur="5.22">human attention seconds for engagement,
whether it&apos;s Netflix or Facebook or TikTok</text><text start="6108.6" dur="0.36">or whatever.</text><text start="6108.96" dur="8.1">And if you do that, then the competition against
groups doing that is a competition for human</text><text start="6117.06" dur="4.8">attention, which ends up being, as our friend
Tristan Harris and so many others point out,</text><text start="6121.86" dur="6.3">a pretty bad race to the bottom of the brain
stem for making maximally limbic hijacking</text><text start="6128.16" dur="0.24">stuff.</text><text start="6130.5" dur="4.68">And so it&apos;s not like the software proliferation
just solves all the problems.</text><text start="6135.18" dur="7.5">The software creates a whole new set of attention
hijacking, belief hijacking capabilities which</text><text start="6142.68" dur="4.26">are problematic, that can drive polarization,
addiction, low attention spans, all those</text><text start="6146.94" dur="0.24">things.</text><text start="6148.2" dur="7.68">Or it&apos;s simply adding efficiencies to the
materials economy, where if you don&apos;t have</text><text start="6155.88" dur="4.56">some law or deterrents that limit the upper
boundary, you have Jevon&apos;s paradox that, when</text><text start="6160.44" dur="4.32">you increase the efficiency you just end up
using more total stuff because more new markets</text><text start="6164.76" dur="0.84">open up.</text><text start="6165.6" dur="7.74">And so what we can say, is that sustained
competitive advantage of a nation or whatever</text><text start="6173.34" dur="5.76">is not their energy or their atoms or their
information processing, it&apos;s the binding of</text><text start="6179.1" dur="3.66">all three of those together and their coordination
of the humans within that.</text><text start="6182.76" dur="6.18">And that those are fundamentally all tightly
coupled to each other.</text><text start="6190.26" dur="7.92">And that from a purely incentive standpoint,
there will always be an incentive to pursue</text><text start="6198.18" dur="4.02">whatever the maximum area of return is, but
to still pursue things that have any return</text><text start="6202.2" dur="3.06">on at all, which ends up meaning you extract
everything.</text><text start="6205.98" dur="7.14">And that doesn&apos;t work long term viability
wise so we do end up having to get something</text><text start="6213.12" dur="3.0">that is not just incentives but deterrents.</text><text start="6216.12" dur="4.14">The only reason you can have a national park
is because the incentive for logging is stopped</text><text start="6220.26" dur="3.96">by a deterrent called the rule of law that
says, we&apos;re not going to cut these trees down.</text><text start="6225.12" dur="11.04">And yet the problem is, if we&apos;re trying to
prevent dead zones in oceans from where no</text><text start="6236.16" dur="4.32">one country&apos;s putting all of the nitrogen
there, it&apos;s coming from lots of areas or putting</text><text start="6240.48" dur="2.34">all of the trash or forever chemicals or whatever
it is.</text><text start="6245.1" dur="3.9">And in order to stop someone else from doing
it and it&apos;s another country, you actually</text><text start="6249.0" dur="4.02">have to have war, not just law because you
don&apos;t have monopoly of violence.How do you</text><text start="6253.02" dur="1.38">solve those types of things?</text><text start="6255.78" dur="5.82">This is where we realized that the global
issues that we face, the global market, we</text><text start="6261.6" dur="6.24">have a global market, we don&apos;t have national
markets, we have a global market and it&apos;s</text><text start="6267.84" dur="3.06">important to say that, of course, we have
national markets but not really because the</text><text start="6270.9" dur="2.58">laptop that we&apos;re both speaking on required
global supply chain.</text><text start="6273.48" dur="2.04">So without global trade we actually can&apos;t
make anything.</text><text start="6276.36" dur="11.64">And so we have global markets but we don&apos;t
have global governance.The incentive</text><text start="6288.0" dur="4.5">alone system is fundamentally incompatible
with the biosphere, it will continue to extract</text><text start="6293.22" dur="0.84">and externalize.</text><text start="6294.06" dur="3.18">And so you have to have some system of deterrents.</text><text start="6297.24" dur="2.76">No, we&apos;re not allowed to do that at a global
system.</text><text start="6300.0" dur="6.3">How do we create that and how do we create
that is both enforceable and non dystopic?</text><text start="6306.3" dur="2.64">I think that&apos;s some of the tee up of where
we go next.</text><text start="6308.94" dur="4.2">Nate Hagens:
And the other constraint that I will just</text><text start="6313.14" dur="5.16">add there is, the biosphere limits as severe
as they are, are not what&apos;s going to get us</text><text start="6318.3" dur="6.48">first because your concept of the third or
fourth industrial revolution using technology</text><text start="6324.78" dur="8.04">or in the modern 2020s case AI, what that
does do, is it allows us to increase enough</text><text start="6332.82" dur="4.02">productivity to pay back prior financial claims.</text><text start="6336.84" dur="6.06">The moment we&apos;re not able to service existing
financial claims, there is a musical chairs</text><text start="6342.9" dur="6.54">moment which may be getting closer because
of what happened in Russia and Ukraine and</text><text start="6349.44" dur="0.78">in the UK.</text><text start="6350.22" dur="6.12">And so that is an additional constraint on
top of all the other ones that you look at.</text><text start="6357.54" dur="1.56">But do you agree with that?</text><text start="6359.1" dur="7.8">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
All of the various domains are interacting</text><text start="6366.9" dur="4.2">with each other, so global finance is interacting
with the environment, is interacting with</text><text start="6371.1" dur="1.68">tech, is interacting with regulation.</text><text start="6372.78" dur="5.04">And so you can&apos;t look at them in isolation
and say, do we get the catastrophe in this</text><text start="6377.82" dur="1.44">one first or in this one first?</text><text start="6381.0" dur="8.46">When we talk about planetary boundaries with
climate change, before we hit the planetary</text><text start="6389.46" dur="7.56">boundary of runaway climate change from albedo
effect or whatever it is that would mean we</text><text start="6397.02" dur="8.22">can never fix it, or before we hit the point
of venus-ification, well before then, we will</text><text start="6405.24" dur="5.508">hit the point at which extreme weather events
start causing human migration that will cause-</text><text start="6410.748" dur="2.292">Nate Hagens:
That&apos;s already locked in, we&apos;ve already passed</text><text start="6413.04" dur="0.36">that point.</text><text start="6413.4" dur="5.1">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
... On small scale, so far, Syria was relatively</text><text start="6418.5" dur="3.18">small population and Australia was low population
density.</text><text start="6422.4" dur="5.7">But as soon as you have Australia scale things
in high population density areas, then you</text><text start="6428.1" dur="2.04">start getting world changing effects from
that.</text><text start="6430.14" dur="8.22">And so that&apos;s a place where we&apos;ve already
passed a planetary tipping point, not in terms</text><text start="6438.36" dur="4.86">of the habitability of the planet biosphere
wise, but the habitability of some areas for</text><text start="6443.22" dur="5.82">short periods of time that are enough to cause
migrations of people that cause resource pressures</text><text start="6449.04" dur="2.22">that cause wars, that cause supply chain issues.</text><text start="6454.26" dur="5.76">There&apos;s a lot of very near term things that
can start to cause breakdown of the world</text><text start="6460.02" dur="5.04">systems that meet people&apos;s needs that happen
at the interface of a lot of these areas,</text><text start="6465.06" dur="2.58">not just one of them going catastrophic on
its own.</text><text start="6469.44" dur="6.54">Nate Hagens:
How would you like to lay some breadcrumbs</text><text start="6475.98" dur="1.68">and a teaser for our next episode?</text><text start="6477.66" dur="10.92">Do you have an outline for how we should approach
the bend versus break possible interventions</text><text start="6488.58" dur="8.28">for humans listening to this show, thinking
about it and maximizing their impact on the</text><text start="6496.86" dur="2.28">human predicament as opposed to minimizing
it?</text><text start="6499.14" dur="4.5">Daniel Schmachtenberger: </text><text start="6503.64" dur="2.16">Yeah, there&apos;s a few things that we might talk</text><text start="6505.8" dur="0.78">about next time.</text><text start="6507.24" dur="8.16">We could talk about, what are some of the
nearest term risks that are quite possibly</text><text start="6515.4" dur="2.04">catastrophic enough that we really want to </text><text start="6517.44" dur="2.76">prevent them, otherwise we 
lose a lot of possibility</text><text start="6520.2" dur="0.708">if we don&apos;t.</text><text start="6520.908" dur="4.392">Nate Hagens:
Well, nuclear war is all the elephants in</text><text start="6525.3" dur="5.16">the room as of October 3rd when this conversation
is being recorded, in my opinion.</text><text start="6530.46" dur="4.74">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I would say large scale war, not including</text><text start="6535.2" dur="2.4">nuclear, is a big issue, nuclear war is one.</text><text start="6537.6" dur="7.32">Nuclear war is not only at Ukraine, between
Russia and NATO forces, but since that has</text><text start="6544.92" dur="5.16">happened and the whole world has got pulled
into various aspects or taken advantage of</text><text start="6550.08" dur="10.62">conflict, Israel and Iran, Armenia, Azerbaijan,
India, Pakistan, China, Taiwan, there&apos;s a</text><text start="6560.7" dur="5.4">lot of places where the conflict has escalated
in terms of the possibility of kinetic conflict.</text><text start="6566.1" dur="7.56">And a number of those places are nuclear equipped
places so meaningful war that was not possible</text><text start="6573.66" dur="3.18">during Pax Americana is definitely possible
now.</text><text start="6576.84" dur="5.46">Nate Hagens:
Well, you and I talk about this a lot off</text><text start="6582.3" dur="5.88">camera, so this would be completely another
episode, but let me just add one more thing</text><text start="6588.18" dur="0.48">to that.</text><text start="6588.66" dur="8.82">I can&apos;t believe today there&apos;s this gleeful
narrative on Twitter, Francis Fukuyama and</text><text start="6597.48" dur="6.54">others today are tweeting that Russia collapse
is not far away and the next few days are</text><text start="6604.02" dur="2.58">going to be a enormous retreat for Russia.</text><text start="6606.6" dur="6.06">And I&apos;m just thinking to myself, are they
that naive that if Russia were to collapse,</text><text start="6612.66" dur="2.64">that would be one of the worst possible scenarios?</text><text start="6615.3" dur="6.48">Because they have thousands and thousands
of nuclear bombs, who would be in control</text><text start="6621.78" dur="0.54">of those?</text><text start="6622.32" dur="3.72">Why would they not want to sell them to other
countries?</text><text start="6626.58" dur="8.52">The mind boggles at the risk there, but that&apos;s
digressing from our conversation.</text><text start="6636.9" dur="4.2">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
I won&apos;t get into the specific content of that,</text><text start="6641.1" dur="5.16">but what I will say is, as you were mentioning
earlier, that some people, for environmental</text><text start="6646.26" dur="3.72">concerns, want to one world government because
they don&apos;t think anything else will be able</text><text start="6649.98" dur="1.68">to address the environmental issues in time.</text><text start="6651.66" dur="5.1">But they might be under factoring how bad
a one world government would be from any type</text><text start="6656.76" dur="5.46">of government we&apos;ve ever had so far, as far
as class system dynamics and oppression goes.</text><text start="6664.26" dur="7.32">Most people are much more aware of the parts
of the world system that they look at than</text><text start="6671.58" dur="4.86">the other parts and so they&apos;re able to see
something that looks like a win within that</text><text start="6676.44" dur="3.6">domain without factoring how much that can
actually be a loss in other domains.</text><text start="6680.76" dur="5.52">And this is the problem of siloing and hyper
specialization in a radically interconnected</text><text start="6686.28" dur="0.24">world.</text><text start="6686.52" dur="4.44">And I would argue that one of the deepest
generator functions of all of the issues that</text><text start="6690.96" dur="4.8">we face is that our primary processes for
solving problems externalize problems somewhere</text><text start="6695.76" dur="0.12">else.</text><text start="6696.78" dur="6.12">Because we define the problem too narrowly
and then we look for a solution to that narrowly</text><text start="6702.9" dur="3.96">defined problem that interacts with complex
systems where the externalities go somewhere</text><text start="6706.86" dur="2.1">else and then either someone notices those </text><text start="6708.96" dur="2.58">externalities says, no way, 
and you get polarization</text><text start="6711.54" dur="3.78">or nobody notices it happens and you actually
get the externality.</text><text start="6715.32" dur="2.58">Nate Hagens:
That&apos;s half of it.</text><text start="6717.9" dur="5.46">I think the other half is that we use social
sorting mechanisms to solve physical world</text><text start="6723.36" dur="0.6">problems.</text><text start="6723.96" dur="5.88">And the higher status person that you meet
with, people defer to that person whether</text><text start="6729.84" dur="8.16">or not they actually have the technical or
wisdom to carry out the risk analysis or the</text><text start="6738.0" dur="0.48">intervention.</text><text start="6739.68" dur="4.38">It&apos;s just amazing to me at conferences and
other places that we defer to the highest</text><text start="6744.06" dur="6.78">status person to make the decisions, which
in our trial ancestral world made sense.</text><text start="6750.84" dur="1.92">Daniel Schmachtenberger: </text><text start="6752.76" dur="4.56">If we think about 1776 and 
the ideas of representative</text><text start="6757.32" dur="6.96">democracy at that time, it was, one, coming
out of modernity, you had this idea of the</text><text start="6764.28" dur="4.14">renaissance man, polymath individual who had
a classical education who  </text><text start="6769.2" dur="2.82">could actually understand</text><text start="6773.22" dur="7.92">the science of government as George Washington
called it, meaning the politics, history,</text><text start="6781.14" dur="4.8">economics, sociology, as well as all of the
areas of industry and infrastructure that</text><text start="6785.94" dur="2.88">were relevant well enough to represent for
their local needs.</text><text start="6789.96" dur="3.12">And because the complexity of the overall </text><text start="6793.08" dur="2.58">tech stack did not require 
that level of specialization,</text><text start="6796.62" dur="3.12">obviously today, that&apos;s utter nonsense.</text><text start="6799.74" dur="2.1">You couldn&apos;t have a representative understand </text><text start="6801.84" dur="4.14">the issues of nuclear 
deterrents and the electrical</text><text start="6805.98" dur="3.9">grid and dead zones in the ocean and manufacturing
chemicals and all those things.</text><text start="6809.88" dur="2.64">So you&apos;re supposed to have subcommittees that
figure that out.</text><text start="6812.52" dur="6.84">But we could identify lengthily the problems
in that system, but there is a place where</text><text start="6819.36" dur="4.44">the total complexity of the decision making
stack does require different decision making</text><text start="6823.8" dur="0.768">processes.</text><text start="6824.568" dur="1.152">Nate Hagens:
Exactly.</text><text start="6825.72" dur="3.66">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And if you don&apos;t ... and the status thing</text><text start="6829.38" dur="0.66">often was,  </text><text start="6836.88" dur="5.52">what it takes to actually politically
actuate or make something happen is a different</text><text start="6842.4" dur="3.24">set of skills than what it takes to figure
out what the right thing that should happen</text><text start="6845.64" dur="0.24">is.</text><text start="6846.48" dur="8.22">And so the people who have the capability
to navigate the status hierarchies and prestige</text><text start="6854.7" dur="3.6">hierarchies and influence and whatever it
is to make sure it happens given those positions,</text><text start="6858.3" dur="4.62">they&apos;re supposed to, of course, be advised
by groups of specialists, but they&apos;re also</text><text start="6862.92" dur="6.24">advised by vested interest groups that want
particular things to go through and that has</text><text start="6869.16" dur="1.08">all the problems that it does.</text><text start="6871.14" dur="9.06">If we don&apos;t take the current system of governance,
any aspect of it as a given, that we will</text><text start="6880.2" dur="4.26">have representatives at the level of states
that are called congressmen and senators and</text><text start="6884.46" dur="2.82">that we&apos;ll vote on propositions made by special
interest groups.</text><text start="6887.28" dur="5.16">And we just said if we were going to rebuild
governance from scratch using all the 21st</text><text start="6892.44" dur="5.76">century technologies and factoring the types
of problems that we have, the speed at which</text><text start="6898.2" dur="2.1">they occur, the complexity, how would we do
it?</text><text start="6900.3" dur="3.54">We would do it in a way that doesn&apos;t look
like how any nation state in the world runs</text><text start="6903.84" dur="0.168">today.</text><text start="6904.008" dur="1.092">Nate Hagens:
Exactly.</text><text start="6905.1" dur="2.88">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
And ultimately, that is one of the things</text><text start="6907.98" dur="0.78">that we have to do.</text><text start="6908.76" dur="1.776">So now we were leaving breadcrumbs-</text><text start="6910.536" dur="1.524">Nate Hagens:
That is the we have to do.</text><text start="6913.92" dur="2.46">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
We were leaving breadcrumbs, so let me come</text><text start="6916.38" dur="1.2">back to breadcrumbs.</text><text start="6918.12" dur="4.92">There are some very near term risks, you mentioned
nuclear, and I think there are very near term</text><text start="6923.04" dur="5.64">risks in AI, in bio weapons, in planetary
boundaries, in supply chains and quite a few</text><text start="6928.68" dur="0.18">things.</text><text start="6928.86" dur="7.98">Meaning, there are certain problems that the
existing NGOs and nation states and corporations</text><text start="6936.84" dur="3.66">and IGOs collectively are not on course to
solve in time.</text><text start="6940.5" dur="5.76">That if some additional action doesn&apos;t take
place, catastrophic problems will occur.</text><text start="6946.26" dur="5.52">And so those of us who are thinking about
what to do are like, well, there&apos;s a delta</text><text start="6951.78" dur="4.02">between what is on track to happen and what
needs to happen, how do we close that delta?</text><text start="6956.4" dur="5.22">And anything that is on track to probably
happen, awesome, be very grateful that people</text><text start="6961.62" dur="0.84">are tending to that.</text><text start="6962.46" dur="5.58">Look at the stuff that is not probably going
to happen that needs to if you&apos;re looking</text><text start="6968.04" dur="3.42">at putting new energy under the system somewhere.</text><text start="6972.06" dur="3.06">I think there&apos;s a bunch of near term stuff,
where we&apos;re not going to be talking about</text><text start="6975.12" dur="4.38">fundamental change of the systems, we&apos;re just
talking about, how do we avoid this bad thing</text><text start="6979.5" dur="0.54">from happening?</text><text start="6980.04" dur="9.84">And maybe we do it through existing mechanisms
like legislation or getting the right people</text><text start="6989.88" dur="2.82">in the right elite positions to change their
mind about something or whatever.</text><text start="6994.14" dur="1.5">So I think of that as triage.</text><text start="6995.64" dur="5.1">There&apos;s all of the things that we have to
do to simply buy time to get to keep working</text><text start="7000.74" dur="4.8">on deeper things and there&apos;s a lot in that
category unfortunately.</text><text start="7006.98" dur="4.02">Then I think of transitional things, which
is how do we work with the existing systems</text><text start="7011.0" dur="0.66">that run the world?</text><text start="7011.66" dur="5.1">So capitalism as it currently exists, nation
states, corporations as they exist, and how</text><text start="7016.76" dur="3.72">do we make changes to them that are intelligible
to them, that vector to them in the right</text><text start="7020.48" dur="0.24">direction?</text><text start="7022.04" dur="7.02">When you look at whatever the work that Larry
Lessig and so many folks are looking at regarding</text><text start="7029.06" dur="3.3">rank choice voting that 
would decrease radicalization </text><text start="7032.36" dur="3.84">on both sides and getting off of just two-party</text><text start="7036.2" dur="7.68">system and fixing gerrymandering and public
campaign finance and things like that, those</text><text start="7043.88" dur="2.58">are not building totally new systems.</text><text start="7046.46" dur="3.48">They&apos;re things that are intelligible to the
current system that would make it less terrible</text><text start="7051.38" dur="0.72">and they&apos;re worth doing.</text><text start="7052.1" dur="6.0">And there&apos;s a lot of things like that, that
you can do to change nation state behavior</text><text start="7058.1" dur="1.92">or corporation behavior or things like that.</text><text start="7061.16" dur="6.36">The B Corp type change in legislation that
says, the directors are not fiduciary obligated</text><text start="7067.52" dur="4.56">to maximize profitability for shareholders,
but they are fiduciary obligated to maximize</text><text start="7072.08" dur="5.34">movement on stated mission while maintaining
profitability, being able to get those types</text><text start="7077.42" dur="1.8">of little legal changes that would affect
corporations.</text><text start="7079.22" dur="4.74">There&apos;s a bunch of stuff that is like, it&apos;s
not triage, meaning it&apos;s not preventing one</text><text start="7083.96" dur="5.34">immediate problem and it&apos;s not rethinking
the fundamental logic of the system, it&apos;s</text><text start="7089.3" dur="2.7">moving the logic of the system in a hackable
direction forward.</text><text start="7092.0" dur="2.04">And then there&apos;s the long term stuff.</text><text start="7094.04" dur="3.48">If we were going to rethink it all from scratch,
we might not have nation states at all.</text><text start="7097.52" dur="2.82">We might have networks of city states because
that makes more sense.</text><text start="7100.34" dur="3.72">Or we might have, how would we redo it from
scratch?</text><text start="7104.06" dur="5.58">Factoring not just did all of our issues involve
global supply chain so there have to be global</text><text start="7109.64" dur="1.08">dynamics involved.</text><text start="7110.72" dur="6.36">Factoring that, if regulation moves slower
than the speed of tech, then it&apos;s not going</text><text start="7117.08" dur="2.64">to be able to regulate the thing that is moving
much faster than it.</text><text start="7119.72" dur="6.12">So if tech is moving on compounding curves
with exponential tech, how do we make a system</text><text start="7125.84" dur="2.16">of regulation that can keep up with that?</text><text start="7129.38" dur="5.88">Now that we&apos;re in a new era where open publishing
had always been good for science, but open</text><text start="7135.26" dur="5.34">publishing of the pandemic viral gene sequences
that are found through gain of function equals</text><text start="7140.6" dur="2.58">increasing everybody&apos;s 
ability to make decentralized </text><text start="7143.18" dur="2.82">catastrophe weapons, in the 
age of gene synthesizers,</text><text start="7146.0" dur="2.46">we have to rethink info sharing.</text><text start="7148.46" dur="5.82">There&apos;s a lot of places where it&apos;s like, the
problem space of the world and the affordances</text><text start="7154.28" dur="4.86">of the new tech mean that we have to rethink
long term governance from scratch.</text><text start="7159.98" dur="5.28">And so triage transition and long term are
three time horizons in which I think about</text><text start="7165.26" dur="0.66">moving forward.</text><text start="7166.82" dur="0.96">That&apos;s one model.</text><text start="7170.36" dur="4.44">I&apos;ll just add this before you comment because
I&apos;ll put these two together and then I think</text><text start="7174.8" dur="3.96">... and then the infrastructure, the social
structure and the super structure is another</text><text start="7178.76" dur="0.36">model.</text><text start="7179.12" dur="6.6">What do we have to change in culture in our
collective values and what the definition</text><text start="7185.72" dur="2.46">of the good life and what&apos;s meaningful is?</text><text start="7188.18" dur="3.3">What do we have to change in our governance
and coordination systems?</text><text start="7191.48" dur="1.68">And what do we have to change in our fundamental </text><text start="7193.16" dur="2.272">technology, governance, 
coordination and economics?</text><text start="7195.432" dur="4.208">What do we have to change in our fundamental
technologies and how do those affect each</text><text start="7199.64" dur="0.18">other?</text><text start="7199.82" dur="4.92">And what are necessary activities in each
that lead to necessary and sufficient collectively</text><text start="7204.74" dur="1.68">across those time horizons?</text><text start="7208.46" dur="3.36">That&apos;s one way of thinking about what we might
want to cover next.</text><text start="7213.44" dur="2.58">Nate Hagens:
Would that be a three by three grid?</text><text start="7216.02" dur="3.72">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Yeah, there are some other threes that we</text><text start="7219.74" dur="2.04">might add in there to dimensionalize the grid.</text><text start="7221.78" dur="2.28">Nate Hagens:
Three by three by three grid?</text><text start="7225.04" dur="4.3">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
If we added that the agents that are playing</text><text start="7229.34" dur="4.98">are hyper agents, egregores and institutions,
then we could add that as a Z axis.</text><text start="7235.16" dur="3.24">Nate Hagens:
This is a good place to stop.</text><text start="7239.06" dur="7.38">So let us promise our listeners and viewers
that we will try to fill out that grid with</text><text start="7246.44" dur="9.3">ideas, directions, hypotheticals to pass the
baton to more humans to engage on this.</text><text start="7255.74" dur="5.22">Because a lot of people are the walking worried,
they know something is horribly wrong, that</text><text start="7260.96" dur="5.82">something is on the horizon and are willing
to play a role in this.</text><text start="7266.78" dur="7.32">So let&apos;s try to really, both of us, think
about that grid and come up with some suggestions</text><text start="7274.1" dur="6.6">and directions in a live creative conversation
between the two of us.</text><text start="7280.7" dur="2.22">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Good, I look forward to it.</text><text start="7282.92" dur="4.14">I have really enjoyed the way that this series
has progressed so far.</text><text start="7288.8" dur="1.62">There&apos;s one last thing I would share this
time.</text><text start="7291.32" dur="7.98">It&apos;s a little bit weird, might seem off topic,
but I&apos;ve had a busy last week and was under</text><text start="7299.3" dur="1.98">slept and so I slept long last night.</text><text start="7301.28" dur="9.42">And I had one recurring dream all night long
and it&apos;s just relevant as we&apos;re coming into</text><text start="7310.7" dur="1.92">this podcast, which I knew I would be doing
today.</text><text start="7313.64" dur="10.32">And the dream that I had all night long was,
this movement the world had that people had</text><text start="7323.96" dur="10.56">at scale, it started with recognizing water
as sacred and rather than seeing how much</text><text start="7334.52" dur="3.66">water we could divert for 
irrigation and agriculture </text><text start="7338.18" dur="3.18">or for industry and the power associated with</text><text start="7341.36" dur="6.18">hydrological warfare and domination and that,
there was a sense of the sacredness of the</text><text start="7347.54" dur="6.66">cleanness and the aliveness of all the water
that was deep enough that it changed the motive,</text><text start="7354.2" dur="4.08">where everyone was really trying to steward
the cleanness and the availability of water.</text><text start="7358.28" dur="4.86">And then of course, that also moved from water
to all of the flows of life.</text><text start="7363.92" dur="6.36">And so a movement from the utility value of
nature is a natural resource, which is, of</text><text start="7370.28" dur="9.54">course, an inherently commodifying term for
life to the sacredness of it and the honor</text><text start="7379.82" dur="2.7">of getting to be in a stewardship role of
the sacred.</text><text start="7384.2" dur="4.98">And it was just interesting, as we were about
to have this podcast today, that I had 12</text><text start="7389.18" dur="2.04">hours of just that dream on repeat all night.</text><text start="7391.22" dur="3.0">Nate Hagens:
I love that.</text><text start="7395.24" dur="6.66">But given the framing that you just said,
we are approaching a life or growth choice.</text><text start="7402.62" dur="8.76">But to recognize that water and other life
is sacred would be outcompeted by people and</text><text start="7411.38" dur="6.84">nations and egregores that choose growth over
life until something else happens.</text><text start="7418.22" dur="2.556">And that is one of the questions.</text><text start="7420.776" dur="3.624">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Life or growth, unless we talk about growth</text><text start="7424.4" dur="4.02">on a different dimension, we just talked about
the Z axis.</text><text start="7430.28" dur="7.5">I would say that in the next phase, we don&apos;t
stop having a evolutionary imperative or a</text><text start="7437.78" dur="5.64">growth imperative, but it moves dimension
and it requires increasing the dimensionality</text><text start="7443.42" dur="5.46">of our reason for being, of our calculus.</text><text start="7448.88" dur="4.32">That the increase of the 
quality of life personally, </text><text start="7453.2" dur="2.76">interpersonally, transpersonally, the sacredness</text><text start="7455.96" dur="2.94">is actually the domain in which growth starts
to happen.</text><text start="7460.46" dur="9.54">And that there is a way to coordinate towards
that, that actually isn&apos;t outcompeted by the</text><text start="7470.0" dur="3.36">existing violence domination, extraction profit
stack.</text><text start="7473.96" dur="9.6">And that can both remove the pathological
competition mindset from itself while not</text><text start="7483.56" dur="1.38">being outcompeted by it.</text><text start="7486.32" dur="5.16">And maybe hopefully, we get some color on
what that could look like next time.</text><text start="7491.48" dur="4.8">Nate Hagens:
I look forward to your human porcupine tree</text><text start="7496.28" dur="3.12">hypnotic explanation of that.</text><text start="7500.24" dur="3.24">To be continued, my friend, thank you so much.</text><text start="7503.48" dur="2.16">Daniel Schmachtenberger:
Likewise brother, thank you.</text><text start="7505.64" dur="4.02">Nate Hagens:
If you enjoyed or learned from this episode</text><text start="7509.66" dur="5.52">of the Great Simplification, please subscribe
to us on your favorite podcast platform and</text><text start="7515.18" dur="4.38">visit thegreatsimplification.com for more
information on future releases.</text></transcript>