<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="4.5" dur="8.01">So if I’m in a competitive game and I have
some information about reality, the reality</text><text start="12.51" dur="5.67">of the playing field that I’m in then that
information can be a source of strategic competitive</text><text start="18.18" dur="4.57">advantage against whoever I’m competing
against and so I have an incentive to withhold</text><text start="22.75" dur="4.19">that information from other players and maybe
even disinform the other players.</text><text start="26.94" dur="3.079">So we see this is actual games.</text><text start="30.019" dur="1.361">This is bluffing in poker.</text><text start="31.38" dur="4.52">This is fake left and go right in soccer,
football.</text><text start="35.9" dur="5.02">But we also would see this in keeping the
knowledge to ourselves of where the water</text><text start="40.92" dur="4.2">is or where the goal is from another tribe
or another kingdom or whatever and maybe even</text><text start="45.12" dur="4.99">trying to throw them off the scent trail with
an intentional leaked fake treasure map that</text><text start="50.11" dur="3.88">has them going the wrong direction so they
don’t accidentally discover what we discovered.</text><text start="53.99" dur="1.55">Things like that.</text><text start="55.54" dur="5.42">So within a rival risk context where information
is strategic competitive advantage there is</text><text start="60.96" dur="3.39">an incentive to disinform.</text><text start="64.35" dur="7.8">And as we get increasing information technology
which is media technology and computational</text><text start="72.15" dur="6.259">technology and statistics and all these things
we have, we really have exponential information</text><text start="78.409" dur="5.811">processing but applied to disinformation,
the incentive to disinform we have exponential</text><text start="84.22" dur="8.74">disinformation capacity which means the ability
to customize inflammatory, fake news, propaganda,</text><text start="92.96" dur="4.24">narrative warfare to specific demographics
and all the way down to specific types of</text><text start="97.2" dur="5.8">people that are the types that are most likely
for that person to believe, be upset by, affect</text><text start="103.0" dur="1.65">their actions.</text><text start="104.65" dur="7.609">So we see with social media platforms like
Facebook the capacity to be able to target</text><text start="112.259" dur="3.741">the things that are going to be the stickiest
for an individual and the stickiest often</text><text start="116.0" dur="5.78">is by appealing to limbic hijacks of what
is scariest to them or hits addiction buttons</text><text start="121.78" dur="4.71">the most or creates a sense of ingroup-outgroup
dynamic or things like that.</text><text start="126.49" dur="7.48">So when you think about having a society that
has an incentive to both withhold information</text><text start="133.97" dur="7.58">and to disinform and you think about a huge
number of different agents who all have increasing</text><text start="141.55" dur="5.769">disinformation capacities and you also think
about the radical asymmetry between an individual</text><text start="147.319" dur="4.25">just trying to make sense of the world and
a huge platform like Facebook or Google or</text><text start="151.569" dur="7.131">a company that is doing split test, optimized
marketing you have an asymmetric information</text><text start="158.7" dur="6.85">warfare of the largest powers in the world
with agendas that are not the same as the</text><text start="165.55" dur="7.93">agenda of the individual for themselves being
put forth on radically powerful information</text><text start="173.48" dur="1.32">technology platforms.</text><text start="174.8" dur="5.461">So you look at the world today and whether
it’s climate change or whether it’s what</text><text start="180.261" dur="4.228">the extent of the damage at Fukushima is or
what the actual tactical capabilities of North</text><text start="184.489" dur="6.381">Korea are or how long we actually have with
coral die off or most any of the things that</text><text start="190.87" dur="1.88">are the most critical issues in the world.</text><text start="192.75" dur="7.54">What goal other countries or what effect other
countries had in influencing U.S. elections.</text><text start="200.29" dur="6.74">No one really knows the most important things
clearly to be able to inform good choice-making</text><text start="207.03" dur="3.01">even about how we survive as a species.</text><text start="210.04" dur="3.949">So this is critical when we’re trying to
understand the current information ecology.</text></transcript>