<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="5.41" dur="1.58">Imagine that we have a cylinder.</text><text start="6.99" dur="5.89">A cylinder is a very simple, three-dimensional
object but imagine that we have two-dimensional</text><text start="12.88" dur="1.76">creatures trying to make sense of a cylinder.</text><text start="14.64" dur="3.29">It’s like the flatland conversation.</text><text start="17.93" dur="6.92">So two-dimensional creature intersects the
cylinder this way and they see a circle.</text><text start="24.85" dur="4.82">And in a two-dimensional world a circle is
a very clear object, makes perfect sense.</text><text start="29.67" dur="3.22">They can describe the mathematics of it.</text><text start="32.89" dur="4.19">And they can verify that empirically they
really did see a circle.</text><text start="37.08" dur="4.8">Of course a two-dimensional create that happens
to be in another plane could bisect the cylinder</text><text start="41.88" dur="2.1">like this and see a rectangle.</text><text start="43.98" dur="3.98">And they could be very clear on that also
and they’re both partially true but they’re</text><text start="47.96" dur="4.91">also both totally wrong in that rectangle
and circle are both two-dimensional objects</text><text start="52.87" dur="3.98">and the thing they’re encountering is a
three-dimensional object that actually can’t</text><text start="56.85" dur="3.25">be understood in the dimensionality that they’re
in.</text><text start="60.1" dur="7.28">So then we can see that a debate ensues between
the two-dimensional creatures in orthogonal</text><text start="67.38" dur="6.61">planes, the circlers and the rectanglers,
who are both utterly sure that the thing that</text><text start="73.99" dur="4.14">they’re seeing is what they think it is
and obviously rectangle and circle are mutually</text><text start="78.13" dur="2.73">exclusive descriptions of reality.</text><text start="80.86" dur="2.66">One has no corners and straight lines.</text><text start="83.52" dur="3.05">One is define exclusively by corners and straight
lines.</text><text start="86.57" dur="5.24">So it’s easy to see how one can hold a kind
of reductive fundamentalist perspective without</text><text start="91.81" dur="1.17">even thinking that it is that.</text><text start="92.98" dur="2.51">It’s just what I’m observing.</text><text start="95.49" dur="2.41">An so then they can debate.</text><text start="97.9" dur="3.81">Let’s imagine that one of the two-dimensional
creatures was able to switch planes and see</text><text start="101.71" dur="3.37">the other one and see that there was some
truth in both of them.</text><text start="105.08" dur="5.75">Then they could flip flop between perspectives
at different times or they could say we just</text><text start="110.83" dur="1.0">need to hold paradox.</text><text start="111.83" dur="5.59">It’s both and neither which mostly means
give up on making sense of reality.</text><text start="117.42" dur="2.53">Or they say it’s a middle path that’s
somewhere between the two.</text><text start="119.95" dur="4.08">And a middle path in two dimensions is like
a rounded rectangle where you kind of do something</text><text start="124.03" dur="6.259">that’s a little bit circle-ish and a little
bit rectangle-ish which isn’t even any true</text><text start="130.289" dur="2.471">part of what a cylinder is.</text><text start="132.76" dur="5.11">And the thing is that they’re just at too
low of a dimensional perspective to properly</text><text start="137.87" dur="2.62">understand the nature of cylinder which is
actually a very simple thing.</text><text start="140.49" dur="1.56">It doesn’t require holding paradox.</text><text start="142.05" dur="3.2">It doesn’t require a middle path in that
way.</text><text start="145.25" dur="3.47">And it’s because when we think of middle
path oftentimes we’re thinking of extremes</text><text start="148.72" dur="2.76">on left or right in a gradient.</text><text start="151.48" dur="4.52">But sometimes the two different perspectives
aren’t on a gradient on a single axis.</text><text start="156.0" dur="2.45">They’re orthogonal to each other.</text><text start="158.45" dur="5.76">And the reason why this is kind of actually
an interesting example is because perception</text><text start="164.21" dur="5.11">itself, a perspective on something defined
by perception is inherently a reduction of</text><text start="169.32" dur="1.22">information of the thing.</text><text start="170.54" dur="4.69">My perspective of it is going to be a lot
less total information than the actual thing</text><text start="175.23" dur="1.0">is.</text><text start="176.23" dur="6.55">So I can look at the object from the east
side or the west side or the top or the north</text><text start="182.78" dur="2.35">side or the inside, microscopically, telescopically.</text><text start="185.13" dur="2.19">They’ll all give me different information.</text><text start="187.32" dur="3.85">None will give me the entirety of the information
about the situation.</text><text start="191.17" dur="5.76">And so there is no all encompassing perspective
that gives me all of the information about</text><text start="196.93" dur="3.15">really almost any situation.</text><text start="200.08" dur="4.0">And so what this means is that reality itself
is trans perspectival.</text><text start="204.08" dur="2.61">It can’t be captured in any perspective.</text><text start="206.69" dur="6.02">So multiple perspectives have to be taken,
all of which will have some part of the reality,</text><text start="212.71" dur="1.0">some signal.</text><text start="213.71" dur="1.0">There may also be distortion.</text><text start="214.71" dur="4.53">I may be looking at the thing through a fisheye
lens or through a colored lens that creates</text><text start="219.24" dur="1.0">some distortion.</text><text start="220.24" dur="6.469">But then let’s say I’m looking at a building
and the picture, the 2D picture from the east</text><text start="226.709" dur="4.391">side and from the west side and from inside
a particular room and the aerial view are</text><text start="231.1" dur="5.3">all obviously very different pictures and
it’s because the 3D complex building actually</text><text start="236.4" dur="3.53">can’t be seen in a 2D process.</text><text start="239.93" dur="5.36">So I could take a lot of pictures and I could
seam them together into a kind of video that</text><text start="245.29" dur="1.64">moves through the building.</text><text start="246.93" dur="4.51">Now by having a video I added the dimension
of time and I got back to kind of the right</text><text start="251.44" dur="1.909">dimensionality to be able to understand the
thing.</text><text start="253.349" dur="1.491">But that’s not a perspective.</text><text start="254.84" dur="2.869">That’s a lot of perspectives that we’re
able to put together.</text><text start="257.709" dur="2.71">So why does this matter.</text><text start="260.419" dur="7.271">Well, when we’re looking at political processes
and we think about classically political left</text><text start="267.69" dur="4.46">kind of perspectives that have more to do
with the orientation of the collective and</text><text start="272.15" dur="4.7">the whole and political right that have more
to do with the individual and sovereignty.</text><text start="276.85" dur="6.95">On the right do we want people who are more
self-responsible and who are more sovereign</text><text start="283.8" dur="2.86">and who are more empowered.</text><text start="286.66" dur="3.4">And do we want to give more power to people
who are doing a better job.</text><text start="290.06" dur="1.63">All of that makes perfect sense.</text><text start="291.69" dur="1.4">Left perspective.</text><text start="293.09" dur="4.77">Do we want to create situations that actually
influence the individuals in the situation</text><text start="297.86" dur="3.85">to do better – social systems, education,
healthcare.</text><text start="301.71" dur="1.66">Does the environment affect the individual.</text><text start="303.37" dur="4.61">You can really think of it as does the environment
affect the individual while understanding</text><text start="307.98" dur="5.24">evolutionary theory that individuals are really
formed by their environment, of course.</text><text start="313.22" dur="3.84">With humans that are niche creators do the
individuals effect their environment.</text><text start="317.06" dur="1.24">Of course.</text><text start="318.3" dur="7.7">If you hold either of those as the only perspective
obviously you’re just missing so much which</text><text start="326.0" dur="2.15">is that the individual is affecting the whole.</text><text start="328.15" dur="4.52">The whole is, in turn affecting the individuals
and how do we create systems that have virtuous</text><text start="332.67" dur="4.249">cycles between empowering individuals and
creating better social systems that have the</text><text start="336.919" dur="4.441">effect of creating humans that are not dependent
on the social systems but that are more sovereign</text><text start="341.36" dur="2.83">and can, in turn, create better social systems.</text><text start="344.19" dur="5.37">And whether we’re thinking about a political
issue like that or we’re looking at a psychologic</text><text start="349.56" dur="5.76">issue like the orientation of being and enjoying
reality as is and accepting ourselves and</text><text start="355.32" dur="5.31">others as is and doing and becoming which
is adding to life, adding to ourselves, seeking</text><text start="360.63" dur="1.27">to improve ourselves.</text><text start="361.9" dur="1.09">How do we hold these together.</text><text start="362.99" dur="5.55">They don’t just have to be held as paradox
or holding one or flip flopping.</text><text start="368.54" dur="5.659">There’s a way that when understanding how
they relate to each other – so in that example</text><text start="374.199" dur="5.541">if I understand the nature of a person as
a noun that is static then it seems like accepting</text><text start="379.74" dur="5.58">them the way they are unconditionally, removes
the basis for growth.</text><text start="385.32" dur="3.97">But if I understand that the person is a dynamic
process, that they’re actually a verb that</text><text start="389.29" dur="5.0">intrinsic to what they are in the moment is
desire and impulse to grow and become.</text><text start="394.29" dur="7.56">And like that loving someone unconditionally
involves wanting for them their own self-actualization</text><text start="401.85" dur="5.37">and there’s no dichotomy between accepting
someone ourselves as is or the world and seeking</text><text start="407.22" dur="2.75">to help it grow, advance, express.</text><text start="409.97" dur="5.419">So it’s a very simple process of saying
the ability to take multiple perspectives,</text><text start="415.389" dur="4.59">to see the partial truth in them and then
to be able to seam them together into something</text><text start="419.979" dur="1.41">that isn’t a perspective.</text><text start="421.389" dur="5.731">It’s a trans perspective capacity to hold
the relationships between many perspectives</text><text start="427.12" dur="7.62">in a way that can inform our choice-making
is fundamental to navigating reality.</text></transcript>